All right, I got 210.
Let's get started.
All right, so we finished
our last lecture
today about vapor and
combined power cycles.
Loud, loud. All right.
So after today's lecture,
you'll be able to analyze
a combined gas
vapor power cycle
and analyze an ideal
cogeneration plant.
The way to think
about this
is until now, right,
we were putting heat in,
trying to get work out,
and then rejecting
the heat.
All right. We had
some efficiency.
And the question that
was asked before was,
how does one improve
the efficiencies
of these cycles?
And in short,
what you want
to do is you want to
squeeze out every
last bit of,
like, Q in that you,
um, that you can.
We've looked so far at
concepts like
regeneration,
essentially taking, let's
say exhaust gases out,
using it to preheat,
compress air before
entering the combustor and
then into a turbine
regeneration.
Last time we
looked at reheat.
Essentially, after you do
one pass through
a turbine,
reheat that low pressure,
relatively lower
pressure vapor
to pass through a
second turbine.
The idea there was that we
extended the Qin, right?
So we were
transferring most of
the heat in then at
a high temperature,
that was the
strategy of reheat.
The other way
that you can do
it is to do what's
called creating a top
and a bottom cycle.
So here, what
you would have
in this concept is that
you would take a
Brighton cycle, right?
And instead of
taking that heat,
and putting it
into a regenerator
prior to the
combustor to heat it,
what you do is you
actually take
all of that heat
out and you transfer it
into a rankin
cycle, right?
Maybe the most
common one I know of
is called organic
rankin, right?
And it's organic because
it doesn't run
on water, right?
So use things that
boil at, let's say,
lower temperatures
there and you,
um and you run it.
And by doing these top and
these bottom cycles here,
you can really boost
the efficiency.
So I pulled this number
from the textbook.
I mean, above 60% is like,
I mean, that's really
something substantial.
If you take the
temperatures
and stuff into
here and said,
what would it be
if it was Carn?
Carn was about, you
know, 80% there.
So, I mean, 62 to 80.
That's a pretty,
uh, um, you know,
for a real
efficiency, that's
quite an impressive
number, okay?
So we'll focus on this.
So we'll go through
and analyze this one,
and I'll take you through
the process of it.
The only really the
thing here that is
conceptually new is that
we need to do a
matching, right?
So, essentially,
we've analyzed
the Brayden cycle
as applied to um,
power generation,
you've analyzed
the Rankin cycle
there where
the heat in was
essentially into a boiler.
And so what you need
to remember is that
both of these cycles
run on their own
mass flow rates.
There's going
to be some MDOT
of air that circulates
through there.
There's going
to be an MDOT
of water that circulates
through here.
And so you have to
have matching, okay?
And so what does
that matching
look like? All right.
So let me see here.
Am I visible on my video?
No, I am. All right.
Before we get
into the weeds,
I'll just say that
it's at a high level.
All right.
So here's your
heat exchanger,
as it would be
in Brighton.
So this is like state
eight. All right.
Um, This is then how
would it look like?
Yeah, it would
be open, right?
This is then
out state nine.
And then for the water,
which you would
have because
this is a closed loop.
So your heat exchanger
probably look like that.
And then that would
be exiting in.
So this would
be your state I
should say nine. I
should say nine.
This should say eight,
this should say two,
and then this should
stay three, all right?
And so this
heat exchanger,
if I draw the control
volume on the outside
of it, All right.
If I draw the
control volume,
let's say on the
entire device here.
It's adiabatic, right?
There is no heat in,
and there is no heat
out of the heat exchanger.
It's kind of like that
doesn't make any, you
know, sense, okay?
But
all the heat exchange
happened internally.
So the control volume
with respect to
the outside,
there's no heat in or out.
There's no work, right?
There's no work in or
out there, all right?
And so what are
the ways that
energy is carried
in and out of this?
It's an enthalpy, right?
So if I write my,
um, conservation of
energy equation here.
What I'll have is, and
let's say that I
have an M dot here.
So the mass flow rate
entering through this,
what do they call it?
I think I called it dot T,
indicating that
that's the top cycle.
And then here on this,
I have an M dot B,
which I think I was
calling the
bottoming cycle,
right? And this
is heat exchange.
It's not a mixing chamber.
You're not mixing
air and water.
The purpose of this is
just to transfer heat.
So if I say that I
have a steady flow
device here, right?
So DE, CV, dt for this
red one right as my E
dot N. Minus my E
dot out and steady flow,
so that goes away.
Neglect changes in kinetic
and potential energy.
No work in or out,
no heat in or out of it.
And so what you'll
have is you
have to look at
the fluid streams that
are entering here.
I'm going to
have an M dot T
at enthalpy eight
that's entering.
What else do I
have entering?
I have plus M dot B,
here times enthal
P at state two,
and this must be equal
to what's exiting.
So then I can go
dot T times H nine,
and then that'll be
minus or plus dot,
bottom, and where is that?
Exiting? That's exiting at
H three, all right?
And so if we divide
because what do I need?
I'm looking here
in this problem,
which I'm not going
to read to you.
But essentially in part A,
we're looking at getting
the ratio of the
mass flow rate
between the steam and
the combustion gases.
So the steam is
going to be M dot B,
and the combustion
gases is M dot T.
So if I divide
both sides by
M dot T, All right.
And I rearrange.
So what's going to
go away, right?
This is going to
sack and sack.
And so what I'll have
here is I can write
M dot B divided by M
dot T. Times H two.
I have the same
thing on this side,
so maybe minus H three,
and that'll be
equal to my H
nine minus H eight.
What this implies
then is that
dot B divided by M
dot T is equal to
H nine minus H
eight divided by
H two minus H three. Good.
And this is an
important relation
because we're going to
get to refrigeration next,
and in refrigeration,
this is a common
approach to run
an upper and a lower or a
topping and a
bottoming cycle.
They are also to
boost efficiency.
So remembering that
you have to have
a matching criterion here,
that's important, okay?
Of course, what
does this mean?
What does this mean? So
I wrote all of this.
What does this mean?
Like in simple terms.
If I ask this side of
the room in layperson
terms to tell
me what is the meaning
of this formula here.
Shall I start at
the back, LS.
How much of what is going
out and how much of
what is going in?
What do I care about? Yes.
But I'm thinking
about the power,
the efficiency of
a power plant,
what are things
that I care about?
I enthalpy.
Let's start
simpler, right?
I said, this is a
big number, right?
And France said they
have a big number.
So what goes into
the efficiency
of a thermal power plant?
Like, what is the
definition of
the efficiency of
a thermal engine?
All right. So the
thermal efficiency
of an engine is your
w.net divided by
your q.in, right?
This is what we
care about, okay?
And what I'm saying
here, right is I
took this rank
in cycle where
I had aq.in that was from
the boiler and
I just stacked
it onto the Braden, okay?
So having said that again,
what do you think
is the meaning
of this analysis?
Now I'm opening it up
to the floor. Sure.
This would help us
to understand some
inefficiencies
that are there,
I'll give you
that. But simpler.
Yes, we're talking
about the waste heat.
Exactly.
So we're saying the right
word now heat here.
So that's an enthalpy,
but I want to stay
with heat, okay?
So this heat exchanger
that I'm
approximating here,
when I ran that as
a Braden cycle,
what was that?
So state seven
to 88 to nine
there in a Braden cycle,
what was this? Cody?
Condenser.
Kind of like a
condenser. Let's say
a low temperature
heat exchanger,
because in the Braden
it's a working fluids a,
so I'm not going
to condense it,
but let's say the
temperature heat exchanger.
Now, I've connected it to
here on the rankin cycle.
What was this heat
exchanger here,
Cody on the rakincycle
between the pump
and the turbine?
What do we call
that when it was
a rank in a water, a
steam power plant?
Boiler. Okay. So
I'm saying that
the low grade heat out
of right out of
the cold condenser
my Brayton,
is the high
temperature heat
that goes in, okay?
So if I want to say this
in a different way,
how would I say that,
having said all
of these words
The heat out of
the top cycle is equal to
the heat in of
the bottom cycle.
That's what's
important, okay?
It's not that
hard. This is
actually not rocket
science, right?
So, like, that's it.
So in writing this,
that's all I've done.
But the key thing you
have to remember,
and I swear I don't want
to grade a
single exam that
does this is you're going
to have different M dots.
These are not
mixing, right?
These are in separate
loops, all right?
Clear? Other
questions about
this before I
continue now with
this slog that is a
combined gas vapor
power cycle.
All right.
All right. So
that's really
the only new thing
that we've seen.
Maybe I guess I
guess I wrote it
there, right?
So the theral
efficiency is the
w.net I should write
out there, right?
So that's aw.net
out, right?
So if we solve
for this, right,
that's going to help
us to get to part B,
and we have to get
that to get to part A.
All right. So if we
pick up, though,
from our w.net, all?
So that's the first piece.
The second piece
to keep in mind
here is that when
we write this
thermal efficiency,
the thermal efficiency,
I said was the
w.net out,
divided by q.in.
We said before
that how else can
I write this w.net out
for a cycle is equal
to what? Q.in.
We can write
this as q.net in
q.net in divided
by q.in, right?
Now, the thing to pay
attention to here.
So what you're going
to want to do in
this problem,
you know, if you went
this route, you will
be fine, right?
If you went this route,
you'd be fine. Why?
Because net out is nothing
but your W dot out from,
let's say the
gas turbine plus
the W dot out from
the let's say the
steam turbine,
and then that's going
to be minus the
w.in for
the compressor
and plus the
w.in for the pump, okay?
And then that's all
going to be divided by
q.in, right? That's fine.
So we'll do this,
and we'll get into
analyzing each of those
steady flow devices.
If you decided
in this problem
to go with the net Q in,
this is going to
be problematic
in this problem,
all right?
Um, and why is that?
I have air coming
into my compressor.
I have some work in here.
I have the
combustor, I have
a cubed out in
that looks great.
Seven to eight gas tb,
I have some amount
of work out.
Eight to nine and
I have a heat
exchanger, and it's good.
The point though, is
that in this problem,
the exhaust gases leave
at state nine here at 450.
Do we think that
450 Kelvin is going
to be the same temperature
as when I draw air
in from the outside?
Yes or no? No, okay?
So if you want to
go that route,
what you need to do is
you'd have to model,
essentially another
heat exchanger,
to say, okay, now I
took all of that out.
If you didn't do
that and you just
plugged and chugged
and, Hey, look,
I have this as my
heat in, workout,
workout, heat out, you're
going to be wrong
in this problem.
It's because this
above as it's
drawn and presented is
actually not a
complete cycle.
State five is
not state nine,
okay? All right.
And now we're starting
to get like real, right?
Like, now I'm not
idealizing as much.
I'm starting to give
you real conditions.
Again, this is
another way in
which if you again,
go with these analysis
and with this,
this is not going
to be a way
to go with how
it's presented.
You'd have to
add another one.
Is there a question?
No. Okay.
Okay, good.
So if we come here
and we think about
then how we define
each of these terms,
what we'll have
to do, right,
is to draw control volumes
around each of
these devices.
These are steady
flow devices.
For each of these, we
neglect changes in
kinetic and potential
energy. All right?
So if we think about now,
let me see if I have
a different marker.
Okay. That's better.
Okay. All right.
All right.
So if we go bit by
bit through this,
so the W dot out
for your compressor
or I'm sorry,
your W dot out
for your gas
turbine is there is going
to be the dot T of there
and that's going
to be the enthalpy
at state seven H
seven minus H
eight actual?
And the reason
why that I write
H eight actual is
because in this problem,
you were told that there's
isotropic efficiencies
for the compressor
and the turbine.
So just to remind you,
when it comes
to the turbine,
the isentropic
efficiency of
a turbine is the ratio
of the actual work out
of it divided by
the isentropic
work out of it.
So it means that
the initial state
here is always a seven
divided by a seven,
in the bottom that's
the isentropic,
so that's h8s,
and then this
is minus H eight
actual, okay?
Since this is a
given, great.
H seven,
we're going to be able
to determine, right.
A lot of times
in these cycles,
what's given generally is
the hottest temperature
and the highest pressure.
You generally will
know the inlet state
right into your work
transfer device,
in this case, the turbine.
So you'll know that.
You'll be able to get to
h8s because
the downstream pressure is
probably also going to be,
um uh, given, especially
in this case,
it's going to be
essentially the atmosphere.
So isotropic and
you know that.
H seven, again, you know,
and then you solve
for HA, right?
So HA is going
to be equal to E,
so the negative,
that is E to T H seven
minus h8s, right?
That's then minus H seven.
If we make that a
positive, we make
this a negative, make
that a positive.
That's how you'll
determine that enthalpy,
right?
So that's the workout of
out of the gas
turbine, right?
The work out of
the steam turbine is
then going to be
your mass floor
to your bottoming
cycle again,
steady flow
device, neglect
changes in kinetic
and potential energy.
And so here, what
you're going to have
is H three minus,
again, H four A,
with the actual, except
that in this case,
you're told that
the efficiency
of the steam turbine
is 100%, okay?
What's the
language for this?
The bottom mean cycle is
an ideal, an ideal, right?
This is an ideal
ranking cycle,
which means that it's
going to operate
isentropically. What
does this mean?
It means that
your H four A
is going to be equal
to your h4s, okay?
Good. For the work in,
so if we have our w.in
for our well, let's
be consistent.
We call this like gas.
So this is w.in for
the gas turbine.
Again, that's going
to be the M dot T
because it's
the top cycle.
And here, it's
going to be a six,
actual minus H five.
You recall the
isentropic efficiency
as it's given for a
compressor, right?
So it's the
minimum work in
divided by the
actual work in.
The minimum work in is
when it's isotropic.
So here, that
would then be
the minimum work would
be H six minus H five,
and the actual
one is H six A
minus H five, okay?
You can solve for
this. So then
your actual would be what?
It would be equal to
H six minus H five.
That's a bad 55.
So swap this E to C,
goes below, which
is a given.
Then, um, plus H five.
And then this is H six A.
So you have H six A.
Here, your actual enthalpy
for something like
a compressor,
would be given,
we'll analyze
this when we get
to properties,
but the inlet
state is given.
Generally, with
compressors,
you given what's
called the
compression ratio.
So the ratio of
the outlet pressure
to the inlet.
So by knowing the state
one, by knowing that,
and now by knowing
the enthalpy
specific enthalpy,
you're going to know also
that state at six
if you cared.
And then w.in When
it comes to
call this pump,
maybe just to
be consistent,
I can call this
ST for the steam,
w.ns that's the bottom
cycle, which is there.
Your pump here is
going to be HSA,
I'm sorry, HA minus H one.
Again, because the problem
here is telling
you that it's
an ideal ranking cycle
with no other information
about isotropic
efficiencies or
anything like that.
What this means is that
the isentropic
efficiency of
your pump it's going
to be equal to one,
which means that H two
A is equal to H twos.
How do you determine
that state?
You determine
this state here
because you would
assume that
this device operates
isentropically and you're
generally given
the high temperature
pressure of this cycle.
You know the
specific entropy,
you know the
pressure, you then
know the state.
You can determine
H two A from that.
The final one is your
Q dot N. Your
q.in All right.
This is occurring your
q.in is happening in
the combustion chamber,
so that's going to
be your M dot times
the top cycle,
and this is going to
be the specific enthal
pH seven, okay?
And then minus, pay
attention to this.
This will then
be six A, right?
So the actual state
there, right.
So now we put that
all together.
So what we'll have, what's
easier for me to write?
Maybe I can try to
fit it with this.
So the actual efficiency
then is let's
write it out.
So we have our out, right?
So we have dot
T. Let's start with
the gas turbine,
H seven minus HA
plus the bottom
cycles contribution
to the out,
which will be H
three minus H fours.
Okay? That's great.
And then minus
the network out.
So for our network out,
what we will have is
an M dot top here.
So in, I'm sorry,
for the in.
So the w.in, we can
start with that.
The top one is H
six A minus H five,
and that's plus an M
dot of our bottom,
which is then steam,
which will be All right.
So the bottom is there,
that's H two A
minus r one.
Great. Then all of that
is divided by our Qn,
which is the dot T times
H seven minus six A.
And so what we'll
see out of this is
that actually for a
problem like this,
I need not give you a
mass flow rate in order
to actually get in
order to actually get
to the efficiency
because all of
this is just going
to be ratios of the
dots, all right?
All right. So if we
take this and we put
this here, right,
M dot T dot T dot T,
and then dot T, right?
This is going to be gone,
and then that's going
to be All right,
and that's
essentially going
to be gone, all right?
So now we'll go state
by state, all right?
So we have now from
our first
principles, right?
We have our formulas.
So this is one that's
important to us.
Okay. I blow this up.
This is the second one,
which is important to us.
All right. And so now we
just have to go
state by state
and determine this.
Are there any questions
at this point?
Yes, please, Elias.
Louder. Yeah, this would
be two because it
would be fine.
I said that they're equal,
but I tried to be,
so this is h2s,
but because the pump
rates an ideal ranking,
H twoA would be
H twos because
the isotropic efficiency
is one, but that's
a good catch.
Other questions?
No. Great.
Okay. So let's
get the states.
So we start here.
Well, we can go a
number of ways,
but what's going
to be easiest?
Let's see how I did
it in my notes.
Combined Great.
Okay.
All right.
So we'll write a couple
of pieces of information.
Questions? I hear
voices in my head.
I don't want to hear
actual voices, right?
But if you have questions,
please ask. All right.
So as this problem
is written, okay,
we're given,
right, this PR, right,
a pressure ratio,
which is equal to eight
for the compressor.
So what does this imply?
This implies for the
compressor that P six,
right, divided by P
five is equal
to PR, right?
And because P five is
essentially
atmospheric pressure,
you'll then know the
pressure at state six.
That's the first
one, okay?
So state one, Okay.
We have P one,
which is equal to
101 pa. All right.
And a temperature T one
that's equal
to 300 Kelvin.
Now, you're not given
this pressure here,
but I expect you to
infer that, okay?
I'm taking in air.
Air is at a pressure.
This is a power plant, it
is not up in
the sky, okay?
Unless space force wants
it up there, right?
Otherwise, it's on the
ground, all right?
So you have this
as your pressure.
Give me one, and then
the temperature
was a given.
Yes, please. Question.
I'm sorry. This
is State five.
I apologize. Good catch.
State five is what
I meant, right?
So you have
state five here,
which is at
this condition.
This is a give me.
It means from this, you
would be able
to know H five
and you'd be able to
know little S
five there, okay?
So reason I started
one in my life, right?
Here we are at a
little bit different.
Okay, you have
this piece of
information, right?
So we have this
with the PR,
and essentially what that
means then for State six,
with State six let's say
state six S for the
isentropic case,
as we know that P
six is equal to
PR times P five.
And if I did the
entropy analysis
of that device,
it's a steady flow device,
adiabatic reversible.
It means that the
specific entropy at
the inlet is equal to
the specific entropy
of the outlet
for the isentropic case.
So little S six is
equal to little five.
What it means here is
that you will know
H sixS, all right?
Not enough
information, right?
You need to then
go through, use
the isotropic efficiency
for a compressor,
and then you can
determine H six A, okay?
But this is the
way, all right?
This is the way.
All right, um,
Good, good, good.
What was that efficiency
that we were given
in this problem?
The isotropic efficiency
of this compressor,
I think is 0.8.
So that's important for
the analysis to
a six A there.
I said this already that
this was atmospheric
pressure.
And is there any
other information
that I need to
give on this?
No, I do not.
All right, State seven.
So going along
to State seven.
So for its state seven,
you're given you're
basically given
the temperature of the air
as it enters into
the turbine.
So your T seven
is exactly that.
That's 13 Calvin,
so that's good.
And since this
is, you know,
it's a combustion chamber,
but until we get to
the last week of
this semester,
we're essentially
treating those things
as city flow
heat exchangers.
And so what it means is
for a heat exchanger,
we have no pressure
drop across it, right?
So it means that P seven
is equal to P six.
How do I know P six?
Because from knowing right
from state All right,
to get to state six A,
what you're going
to know is you will
determine H six A,
and you will know
P six, right?
So from this, you will
be able to get to
P six actual from that.
So you have this
information, and from here,
you'll be able to
get then H seven,
and you'll get a
seven from that.
All right, State seven.
We're going to
state eight, State
eight. State eight.
And for state eight,
the first step is to
get to state eight S
before we then
go to eight A.
All right? And again,
you need to look
a little bit forward.
So you have exhaust
gases coming out of
the turbine that are just
exhausting to
the atmosphere.
So what you'll
expect here is that
p eight will be equal to
101 pa. All right.
Because essentially that
the heat exchange
isobaric,
State nine is
going to be at
atmospheric pressure,
so that's going to
be state eight.
And again, if you
did your steady
flow entropy
analysis of this,
you would see that S eight
here for this case
is going to be
equal to little S seven.
And from this, what
you'll have is h8s.
You'll remember that
the istropic efficiency
for this turbine
is given as 0.85.
So you use this
information
with the formula
that I gave you
before for determining,
um eight A.
And so what
you'll have an is
state eight A, right?
So by knowing the
isentropic efficiency,
by knowing the
isotropic enthalpy,
you will be able to from
our formula here to
get to H eight A,
and the pressure
doesn't change, right?
So the pressure
is still P eight.
And so from
this, you know,
you could determine
things like,
um, Let me think about
this for a second.
What do I actually
need at state A?
I don't really
need anything,
but you know it, right?
So basically,
with this, the
state's complete.
But what you care
about for the purposes
of computing
efficiency was
getting to eight
A there, okay?
So that's for
our Brighton.
We can then move
on to the states
for water, all right?
What's the best
thing to do here?
The best thing to do here
is just to write
on the board.
All right, um, So
coming along then onto
the rank in side.
So the rank inside,
what are we told here?
This is an ideal rank
in cycle that operates
between seven PA and
five kPa, right?
So operating between this,
you have to recognize
that generally the boiler,
what we call the
heat exchanger
here is your high
pressure side,
and the condenser is
low pressure side.
Why am I saying
that, right?
It's isobaric. So here
to here is the
same pressure,
here to here is
the same pressure.
So high pressure
and low pressure.
One and two, you're
given the temperature
of the steam, okay?
So we know the temperature
at state three.
So state three
state three,
you're basically given
T three is an equal to
your 500 degrees
C. P three is
equal to the higher
pressure of seven
PA seven pA. What
it means from this
is that you know
H three and you
know S three.
That's a good start.
On to state four,
State four, This is
an ideal ranking so
that turbines can
operate isotropically,
the steam turbine.
If you did
your entropy analysis
on that device,
you would see that
specific entropy at
the exit is equal to
that of the inlet.
So little S four is
equal to little S three,
and the pressure at
state four, right,
because it's connected
to the condenser
is going to be at the
low pressure, right?
So then P four here
is equal to the
low pressure,
which looks to me
like five kpa?
So five KPA there.
And it means from
this that you know
your you know
the age four.
I'll write H for A because
H four A is equal
to H four here.
You know H fourS
but that's also
equal to H A.
Okay? That's good.
You then move along
to state one.
It's crucial to recognize
that for a Rankin cycle,
one piece of
information which is
implicit from that
is the condenser.
It means that at X one,
you're a saturated liquid,
your condensed state, it's
equal to zero, right?
And because it's
a heat exchanger,
P one is then going to
be equal to P four,
then you know S one
and you know H one.
The final piece of
information then
is its state two.
So at state two here,
you do entropy analysis.
Little S two is going to
be equal to little S one.
It's an isotropic process,
and the pressure you're
going to have here,
P two is the high
pressure side.
It's going to be
equal to P three.
And so what it
means is that
you have h3s here,
which is basically equal
to or H twoS here,
which is equal to H two
A because it's ideal.
The isotropic efficiency
is 100%, okay?
Yes, please.
If we go mark to 868
isn't the guess,
but it was one of
the ideas is that
you would use
the p68 and the
actual mental reason
to find P weird
because it's like
you use P six to use
p68 and I don't
understand how it works.
An elastic. State six,
when you go into the
compressor state,
so at the exit of
the compressor,
what you're generally told
is what that pressure is.
You're generally
told what this is.
That's equal to the
inlet pressure,
which is P five times
the pressure ratio PR.
The second step into
getting to the
actual enthalpy
is you assume it operates
isotropically first,
adiabatic and reversible,
you get H six.
To get to H six A,
I need to know H six
and I need to know ESC,
the isentropic
compressor efficiency.
With that, Here, I
can get to H six A
through this, right?
Because I have h6s.
I determine H five I
knew E to C was given.
Now I have H six A.
And I got to this
state, and I said,
What the hell can I tell
you with this exercise?
And I thought, Well,
maybe pressure
is interesting.
But yeah,
so that's essentially
that's what I have.
And then if you
continue, right,
you go to that's
about six.
You'd go to state
seven, right?
P seven is equal
to P six A,
which is then
where I used that,
I suppose, and then with
the temperature,
I have that.
But what's
recursive about it?
So just to clarify, P
value possibilities.
Oh, I see what
you mean here.
Yeah, no, no, it's not.
Yeah. That would
just be P six.
So at this day, you
have the information.
Of course, you
could know what
the actual entropy is,
but we don't need
actually anything
more at this point
to continue on in our
analysis because again,
at State seven, we
already know that
information at State seven.
Yeah, that's a good catch.
Thank you for that.
Okay. I wanted to
say something. That's
a dangerous thing.
You know what Mark
Twain said, right?
No.
A famous Midwestern,
you know, philosopher.
So better to
remain quiet and
thought a fool
than speak and
remove all doubt, okay?
And if you go to
the Doe library
right here at the
library here,
they have a ton of his
collections, okay?
He was an amazing writer.
Alright. Other
questions about this
so far or Mark Twain?
Short letters,
long letters.
I have a lot of quotes.
Okay. Anyway, so now
that we know, right,
so now we basically know
the enthalpies at
all of these states,
the first step would be to
compute this ratio.
I guess the final thing I
haven't told you
is state nine.
Let's do that.
So state nine state
nine here, right?
So that pressure at
state nine is going
to be equal to the
atmospheric pressure.
So the p eight there,
I'll just write it
one oh one kPa.
You're exhausting
to the atmosphere,
and you're also
given it, right?
You were given 450 Kelvin
was the exit state.
And from this, you
know H nine, right?
So I know H eight
actual there.
I have H two,
which we call H two
actual if we wanted to,
and then minus
our H three.
With this, you know
that ratio of the mass
for rates in the
bottom cycle
in the top cycle.
H seven, we had there
HA H three was
given in the problem
essentially minus h4s.
That could also
be H four A it
operates isentropically.
H six A,
we knew from the
pressure ratio
and the isentropic
efficiency,
H five was given h2s,
that could also be
H two A because
the isotropic efficiency
of this pump is 100%,
and H one was a given.
H seven. Let's
look at this.
H seven was also a
given because
the temperature
and the pressure there,
and then H six A we have.
So you would go in with
all of that and you
would have this and
you'd have this
formula, okay?
It's kind of a
slog to do it.
As you can imagine,
this is not probably
an appropriate
question to ask in
a quiz unless I ask one
question, all right?
So, um, but what
you'll see in a
problem like this
is it still just
has you practice
your fundamentals
through this, right?
So steady flow analysis,
write your
energy equation,
go bit by bit, write
your formulas out.
For that, recognize
if it's ideal,
right, if it's ideal
or if an isentropic
efficiency is given.
If an isentropic
efficiency is given,
you should
automatically be
thinking about how to get
the actual states
using, right,
the inlets and
the isotropic,
um, um, you know,
enthalpies.
And then the final
part of this one
that was kind of a
little bit, you know,
tricky was that it was the
w.net out divided by q.in,
was the correct
route to go.
The reason being
that this was not
actually a closed
loop cycle.
State five and nine
were different.
If you wanted to
connect them,
you totally could,
and therefore,
you could use
this approach,
but you'd have to
have essentially
a fictitious
heat exchanger
that you would draw
here to get that do
that extra Q dot out
turn step to get
you back to state
five, okay?
And again, the whole
reason why you would do
this a top and
bottom cycle
is because you
want to eke out.
You don't just want
to waste, right,
that heat and exhaust
into the atmosphere.
Regenerators do okay,
but with this approach,
according to the
book, you'll get
to a better performance
by combining them, okay?
And again, just
to remind you,
that's a big number, okay?
62% is a large number
for a power
plant, all right?
Questions? Yes, please.
So the pressure ratio
it's only State five.
Yeah, so pressure ratios
is six to five, right?
So PR, I've used it here.
So when I say a
pressure ratio,
the topping cycle is
a gas turbine cycle that
has a pressure
ratio of eight.
This means that the
pressure at state
six is equal to
eight times the pressure
at state five, right?
This applies to
the compressor.
Because, you know,
here we have essentially
a heat exchanger and
a heat exchanger,
it also means that
you know the pressure
at state seven, right?
Because essentially that's
an isoberic device.
But when we did
this analysis,
a pressure ratio that was
specific to the
compressor, right?
Is that clear?
Other questions?
Questions on this side?
No? Okay, cool.
So this is what it
would look like,
the two different ones.
So this is what
you're ranking,
the bottoming cycle
would look like NTS.
This is what the
topping cycle
would look like
for the Brayton.
Of course, if I want
heat exchange to happen,
I'd have to look
at 9-8 A, right?
So nine tops out
at about 400
or so, AA at 800.
And then this is
your heat in, right,
from 300 up to like
750 there, right?
So because we haven't
done 109 yet,
but if you want heat
exchange to happen,
as we recognized from
earlier in this course,
you must maintain
Delta Ts, right?
So it makes sense, right,
that this
temperature is less
than the inlets
and vice versa,
but they can't be too
out of whack, right?
And this problem was
basically given to you,
but that would be
another consideration
is that
ideally you
would perfectly
match your
temperatures there,
minimizing irreversibilities
and all of that,
okay?
And I tried to
draw both these
things on here.
I've done it for
other ones, but yeah,
Pike Are said, No,
not to me today.
Okay. So the final way,
so I'll just I'll say
this one with words.
And if I'm not
going to have time to
go through the
whole thing.
If that one was a slog,
this one is like I mean,
it's, but you
can't follow it.
It is a very
interesting it
is quite an
interesting system,
but I'll explain to
you what we're doing here.
So a lot of times,
so I'll have let's say
I have a gas turbine
and I'll have waste heat
or whatever that's
coming out of it.
Previously,
in the previous
example, we took that,
we ran a steam turbine,
and we got some
efficiencies.
Most of the energy used in
this world is
not electricity,
though, is heat, right?
So a majority of
the energy is used in
some form of heat.
And engineering, we
call this a lot of
times as process
heat process heat.
You want to think
about how you do
refining of something,
think of aluminum.
You know, you think
of any materials
production,
there's a lot
of process heat
involved in those
industries, right? A lot.
So it may make sense then,
depending on
where you are and
where you have
a gas turbine,
to take the heat off of
that and actually
use it just to heat.
I think down in San Diego
and on campus here,
I forget the situation
here on campus,
we're kind of in a, um,
in a state of transition.
But for example, when
I was in Chicago,
we had a lot of hospitals
that were there.
And so what they
would do is we
had a cogen facility.
So this is in energy
speak, is called CoGen.
So the CoGen facility
we had there produced
our own power,
natural gas turbine, and
the waste heat was used
to produce steam, right?
So we basically
district heating.
Hospitals need a lot
of steam, right?
They sterilized
stuff, right?
There's a lot of heat
that's needed for that,
but also buildings.
It's a cold place, right?
And so you could use you
basically would have
sort of this
underground steam
that was used there.
And so you can go into and
do those analysis, um,
And you can also
come up with
a measure of efficiency.
So I can write it,
let's say, maybe here.
And so the one difference.
So if you think
about, you know,
our definition
of efficiency,
something that I
desire divided by
something I have
to pay for, right?
So for a system
like this with
that sort of measure
of efficiency,
what they'll write
is Epsilon, right?
Epsilon would be like,
you know, aw.net
out, okay?
Divided by aq.in plus,
let's say, some
heat transferred
out for process
heat, okay?
And the nice part about
that is that,
like, you know,
what originally
was problematic
where I needed
to take heat
out of my cycle
to make it run
suddenly looks
attractive, right?
That's in my
enumerator with
an addition sign,
not a negative sign.
And so these numbers
can get very large,
right, 80% You know,
you can get to a
very large number
if you run with Cogen,
and that's why it
was done, you know?
So like this was
when I was when
I was a student,
your age, there was
a very popular thing
to do with gas turbines,
Cogen, and get these
things to get up to
a very a very high
value with that.
So again, if you see
that in the textbook,
I don't think we have
any homework
problems with it,
but if you want to see,
like something in this
class that's actually
implemented and used
like that, okay?
Um, And what are, like,
key things in the analysis
of this if you want to
get into it, right?
We have this mixing
chamber, right?
So that's, like, the
first thing. We looked
at the mixing
chambers before.
This is where
streams mix, okay?
So you have
sort of something
cold and something
moderately hot and you mix
it and it goes
into the boiler.
These are isobaric, right?
So they're constant
pressure. That's one.
The second thing,
and I think
the only other thing
that you haven't
seen before is then
this process heater.
What it is not
indicated on this is
that you do have a
Q dot outer, right?
There is a Q dot outerm,
but it's one
that's actually,
you know, helpful for you.
And in the analysis,
as it's done here,
it goes between
like two limits,
one where there's
no workout,
another one where there's
no process heat out,
and another one where
you essentially
split MDOT streams, okay?
So in a problem like this,
you'd have some global
MDOT, let's say,
11-1, and then
at this point,
you have to
split, and that's
information that must
be given, right?
So a fraction of the mass
will go towards my
process heater, right?
Good. A fraction
of the mass out of
my turbine at relatively
high pressure
will go to the
process heater.
The other will
go to it, okay?
That's it. Like, you
know, here's a new thing.
It's a cute out out
term and two pieces of
information about how
much mass is diverted,
and the rest of it
is cookie cutter.
This is really nothing
new there, okay?
With that, I'm going to
close about 5
seconds early.
If you have
questions about
this, please come up.
Otherwise, I will see
you in office hours,
I think tomorrow at noon.
And on Wednesday,
we start,
I believe, with
refrigeration. Thank you.