Okay. I'm going
to get started.
So today, we're
going to continue
with our entropy analysis.
Why is this like?
Better? Better.
Okay. So we'll
continue with that.
Learning objectives.
So after today, you'll
be able to apply
the general entropy
balance now
to heat exchanger
and also a nozzle.
Okay? But first, let's
see where you're at and
your understanding
of this.
So you're given the
following experiment.
We have a container here,
which is kept
at 300 Kelvin
in contact with
the reservoir.
The initial pressure is
1 bar, substance is air.
You have 1 kilogram.
So you know the mass,
and you also know
the specific
gas constant in
kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin.
This is connected to
another container,
which was initially
evacuated, right?
So it is zero
bar of pressure,
and you have this as
a volume, all right?
This is also kept
at 300 Kelvin,
and then you open this
valve, all right?
And the question is,
what is the change in
entropy after you open
the valve and this
system goes equilibrium,
okay?
So take 5 minutes,
look it through, and let's
see if we understand
this very well.
If we don't, we'll
go through it again,
and we'll do another
repetition after that.
Any questions before
we get started?
Okay, let's go.
Problem. This is
not the first time
you've seen this, okay?
Literally not
the first time
you've seen this.
So what you have here
is steam that's
entering into
a heat exchanger at this
temperature, right?
And it's exiting at
this temperature here,
and you have this
mass flow rate
in kilograms per
hour of it, right?
That steam is heating air.
Air is coming in at
20 degrees Celsius.
It's exiting at 30
degrees Celsius.
And you're given
also the properties,
so you don't have to
do PICOor for this.
You know the
specific enthropy
and specific entropy of
the steam entering
and exiting.
You're also given
the specific heat
of air. You have
three questions.
The first is what's
the heat transfer rate
from the steam to the air?
So it's a Q dot out.
What's the Q dot out
from the steam to the air?
What is the mass flow
rate of the air, okay?
And what is the rate of
entropy generation,
all right?
Now, to make this work,
the one assumption that
you have to make is that
the outside of this heat
exchanger is adiabatic.
So I do not have
heat exchange
happening from
the environment
to the heat exchanger.
I only have heat
exchange happening
between the steam
and the air, okay?
This one should be
straightforward,
you know, for you.
I would say it's already
launched. Go through it.
I said 10 minutes,
but, you know,
maybe a little bit less.
We'll talk
through that one.
And then at this
stage, after
you've done this one,
you've seen, like,
the two types of N
should be problems
I can ask,
one in the closed system,
one in the open system.
And from that
understanding,
you should be able
to generalize that to
either of the cases,
okay? Questions?
All right.
Round two, let's go.