Today vapor power cycles.
So after today, we're
able to analyze
a vapor power cycle
in which the fluid is
boiled and
condensed, right?
In the previous part,
we were looking at
the case where
the working floor
remaining gas
the whole time.
All right. So the
most So why do we
care about this?
We care about this because
most of our energy
and electricity
is produced by
this device here, right?
So what does it look like?
It doesn't look too
dissimilar to
the Brayton cycle
that we saw before,
which operated with gas
as a working fluid,
which didn't change phase.
The only real
difference is that
instead of a compressor,
we have a pump.
The heat exchanger
where we
put heat in, we
call a boiler,
turbine is the same,
and the device that
takes heat out is
called the condenser.
Of course, in Brayton,
we idealize it as
a closed loop cycle,
even though it wasn't.
In the case of Rankin,
it is closed loop.
It is closed
loop, all right?
Um, The most commonly
used working fluid
that's in here is water,
and people go to great
pains to characterize
and know the state of this
water through the
cycle, right?
So it's very pure stuff.
Okay, so again, work
in through your pump,
heat in through
the boiler,
work out from the turbine,
heat out from
the condenser.
This is how it's
represented in the book on
the TS diagram, right?
So the work
transfer process
in the ideal rankin cycle,
is isotropic, so
it's vertical.
The heat addition
here is two to three.
This is not right,
like when we did Carne
and we looked at it,
we expected this to
be and also
Sterling, right?
This is like a flat
line. We introduced
heat at a constant
temperature.
That does happen during
the heat addition
during boiling,
but when it's a sub
cooled liquid and then
a superheated vapor,
this does not
happen, okay?
Isotropic workout,
and then the
heat out, right?
One way to visualize
rankin or to think
about rankin again,
thinking about the TS
diagram is to again,
go back to Karno
They look and say,
Okay, so what
did Carn look
like on a TS diagram?
Here's my temperature,
here's my entropy.
Heat addition,
isothermal, right?
So here, work
out, isentropic,
heat out, isothermal,
and then work in
isentropic, right?
So this is your TH,
and this is your TL.
The way to visualize,
really rank in is
it's like trying to
take this box, right,
or rectangle and map
it onto something that
has a vapor dome, okay?
So trying to take this
and make it work,
on something like water
that has saturated
liquid and saturated
vapor, all right?
So how do you
make it work?
What's very important in
a turbine is that
you do not have
phase change, okay?
You want what's passing
through the
turbine to be at
a very high
specific volume
because it's VDP, right?
Your work is
specific volume
times the difference
in the pressure.
So the higher the
specific volume, right,
the more specific work
I'm going to get out.
So you want to be
somewhere out here,
and you do not
want to fall
under the dome, okay?
Actually, maybe
ideally you want
to come up right to
the line and be here.
The second reason
why you do not want
this work transfer
process to fall
into the dome is
when that happens,
you're going to make
it condensed phase.
You're going to make
droplets, right?
And these blades
that are in there,
they spin very,
very fast, right?
And what you
should imagine
is if you make a
lot of fine mist,
those droplets have a
high density to them,
and you're just
going to be hitting
it constantly
over and over,
and it's going to
erode, all right?
So you're
basically going to
erode your blades if
you have you
have that, okay?
So that's like
one part of it.
When we look at the
heat rejection,
so out of the back end
of the turbine, right,
where we're taking
the heat out.
And this is the
one part where
you probably could
keep things.
And indeed, in this almost
in this idealized case,
this process, you know,
happens to
pretty much look
isothermal basically
look isothermal there.
So this is, you know,
you're doing okay.
You condense back
to a liquid.
Part of the reason
why you want
to condense back
into a liquid is,
again, when you're
a liquid, you
have a very low
specific volume.
So if you think about
the work transferred
in, VDP.
I have a very low
specific volume,
but I'm a liquid.
So the amount of
work that I put
in is going to
be much less compared
to what I get out, right?
All right. Yeah, so
we have that heat
transfer out process,
which was isothermal,
and obviously since a
heat exchanger,
it's isobaric.
You have work
that you put in.
So you bring this up to
some pressure that's here,
and the heat
addition process,
right in the boiler like
any heat exchanger
is isobaric.
So the isotherm
is going to
look something
like this, right?
So essentially, when
you start to add
heat, right,
it's going to follow
this isotherm, okay?
So Rankin is like
trying to put arno like
a square peg into,
I don't know,
this parabola,
okay, to make that work.
Does that make
sense? All right.
Again, key
concepts are that,
like work transfer
is V, VP here.
At this case, this is
a very low specific
volume because
it's a liquid,
and in here, it
is very high.
You do not want during
this workout process,
you never want to
be pumping or using
a turbine with a
multi phase, right?
You want to be
single phase.
So here because
of this, right,
I'll be single phase where
I'm a superheated vapor,
single phase while
I'm a liquid.
I do get
a constant temperature
heat rejection
effectively if I stay
within the dome.
And then, given all
those other constraints,
you're not going to
have a constant,
um, TH, okay?
So, what that means
is when you do
compare yourself
to Knel with this,
you will choose this
as your TH, right?
But most of the
process there of
the heat addition is
not at TH, right?
You're at a lower at
a lower temperature,
which means that
you're at essentially,
right, a lower grade of
heat that you're
putting in.
So you'll see significant
deviations of this
compared to Carnal for
that reason, okay.
Okay.
Um What else can
I say about this?
Yeah, so is commonly
what's used.
You can use other
fluids. So there
are other fluids that
can be used for this,
but water is the
dominant one.
The power plants
that operate on
this are fossil
fuel based,
so I think coal and
that, but also
nuclear, right?
So nuclear systems run
on rankin systems.
You have different
different types
like pressurized water and
so on and so forth.
But at the end of the
day, essentially,
all that you have
from nuclear is
that it's still a
heat exchanger.
So the Q and is all
the same, all right?
They just have
limitations in
terms of the upper
operating temperature.
So if you use something
that's like fsiluel,
you're allowed to go
to higher temperature than
nuclear for maybe
obvious reasons.
Yes, please. Would you
want us to memorize
all the different types of
cycles? What
does that mean?
I want you to
make new cycles.
I want you to go
out and create
new things that are
more efficient and
get rich and then remember
me when you become
a donor to this wonderful
university, all
right, David?
Okay.
So, I mean, memorize
all of them.
I want you to able
to classify, right?
So what I keep
repeating here in
the classification is that
I have a power cycle,
and within power cycles,
I think of gas, right?
So gas power cycle or a,
what did I say at the
beginning, vapor, okay?
So what should go off
in your mind when I say
gas is that the
working fluid
should not change a state,
should remain
a gas, right?
And there because
it's a gas,
it's probably a wet.
Idel gas, right?
Which means
it's, you know,
life can get a lot
easier when you get
into the analysis, right?
So the other part of
the classification
is that we have
a vapor power cycle.
There are things
change phase.
You don't have ideal gas.
We have to use Pyclor.
Yeah, so that's kind of
the differentiation.
When it gets to the
device level, right?
I still need you to go
device by device, right?
So maybe I'll give
you a problem,
like, Hey, look
at this thing.
Here's some conditions.
Tell me, is it
good or not.
Tell me, is this
a violation of
a first or a
second law here?
Is this like a
plausible system?
So then I need to
be able to break
down individual
components, right?
Apply steady flow
analysis for, um,
conservation of mass,
conservation of energy,
and entropy control
volume analysis.
Bang, bang, bang,
bang, okay?
And when I get into this,
you'll show that, like,
because you have
good fundamentals
for each of those devices,
you're going to
be able to go
through these
things quickly
because it's going
to get complicated.
Here I have four.
I think at the
end of this,
maybe I had eight
devices, and,
like, I can do more, but
it's not hard, right?
It's just like, you know,
like anything like
any language.
You got to learn sort of,
you know, what's going
on with it, and then
it gets easier.
So, in a sense, you
should remember
the fundamentals.
I would say ranking is
a pretty fundamentally
important cycle
that's there, but, Yeah.
Okay.
Does that answer
your question?
Yeah. That was
long winded.
Other questions?
All right. So let's
get into this.
Let's analyze our
Rankin cycle.
This is Rankin here.
All right. I
will erase this.
Do we look good.
We'll go with this
here. All right.
Okay. To do. All right,
so we drew right,
I'll draw the
schematics here.
I'll have it there,
and then I'll
turn off the monitor.
But basically,
right, we have
a pump, which is here.
I have some w.in,
which I'm putting
into that.
That's then going
into my boiler, okay,
which is essentially
a glorified
heat exchanger,
q.in, right?
All right? This
is then going
into a turbine, right?
So I have here,
semi turbine,
like that. All right?
I have a W dot out
from this. All right.
And then this is
then going into
my condenser.
All right? Cool.
So this has
then a Q dot out.
The way that you cool
these condensers,
all right,
is actually that we
have usually
water can be air,
but a lot of
times it's water.
That will pass
through this and
then we'll put back
into the ground, okay?
And about half
the groundwater
in this country that
we take out every year
passes through that
device through
a surface surface
condenser.
The surface area. So like,
again, this is
like many tubes.
You have like many
tubes, right?
The effective
surface areas
that you have on
the outside of
these tubes are
measured in the size of
Cal Memorial
Stadiums, right?
Like, they're
football pitches
of area, a lot
of material.
So it's a huge
they're huge.
You'll see this on some
of your homework problems.
I think in this specific
case, we use cooling
water to reject heat
out of a
refrigeration system,
but this is what
you do, okay?
We're in a data
center, right,
in Wisconsin,
Microsoft's building
one close to
Lake Michigan.
Guess why. Okay.
Because the lake.
There's a lot of
water there, right?
So they have that
on the do cooling.
So anyways, that's
typically how it's done.
It can also be that
you loop water here,
and then this goes into
like a cooling tower.
So if you ever
drive by and see
a cooling tower,
for example,
maybe nuclear,
all you have here is
this cooling loop,
and then you're
effectively spraying,
where you're atomizing
a bunch of water,
you're letting
it cool down,
it settles, and you
loop it again, okay?
But the key element
for us is that
we have aq.in
from combustion
and a Q dot out
from some cooling,
right, which we
don't have to
specify for this
exact problem.
In terms of states,
just like we had with,
um, With Brighton,
State one will be
what's entering into
the pressurizing device,
let's say the pump.
State two is
at the exit of
the pump entering into
the heat exchanger,
State three at the exit
of the heat exchaner
entering the turbine,
and state four like that.
What we can do
is we can do
steady flow analysis to
each of these
devices, right?
So I can go here
and do this.
Drop my control
volume here for this.
Do another one here.
Do another one.
Another one that's here.
Just at the risk
of confusing,
I will get rid of that.
Okay, so there's
my heat exchanger,
and there's my Q
dot out. All right.
Um, All right,
so in the steady flow
analysis, right?
So we're going
to assume for
each of these devices
that we don't
have a change in the mass
of their control volumes,
no change in the energy of
the control volumes
and no change in
the entropy of their
control volumes, right?
So, what that
means is that
your E dot N is equal
to E dot out, right?
For this, which
is then your w.in
plus q.in plus
your.in times
H in plus velocity
in squared
divided by two plus
gz N is equal to,
your W dot out, plus
your Q dot out,
plus your dot out,
H out plus W,
so velocity out
squared divided by
two plus G Z out, right?
First assumption for
these since we're
not dealing with
nozzles or diffusers,
is you neglect
your changes in
kinetic and
potential energies,
which are there.
That's one part of it.
For our entropy analysis,
we can do our mass now.
Essentially,
because of that,
with the
conservation of mass
and no change in
the mass and the
control volume,
MDT in is equal to MDT
out is equal to M dot,
and for our entropy
analysis, ds CV dt,
the change in
entropy of any of
those control volumes
is going to be
equal to the rate
of entropy coming
in minus the rate
that it leaves
plus the rate that
it's generated
dot gen. All right.
Steady flow.
So this is out. And for
these cycles today,
we're going to
assume, right,
and this is how
we'll handle
at least the first
stage always in
this analysis as we
compute the ideal process.
So the ideal here
really means that
the pump and the
turbine are adiabatic,
and they are reversible.
So what that means is
that there is no
entropy generated.
So out of this,
it means that
capitals.in is equal
to capitals dot out.
What that means is that.in
times little So times
little SN is
equal to m dot
out times little S out.
Mass is gone.
What it means is that
the specific entropy at
the inlet is equal to
the specific entropy
at the outlet.
Good. I'm not saying
anything radical here.
I just reminding him.
Okay.
In case the Amazon web
services shutdown
affected you.
Some of you tried to
use paper tables.
I hope that was a
good experience.
This is where we are.
We can go now one by one.
If we go with our pump,
for the work
process, w.in,
what this is
going to end up
being is that this
is going to be
M dot times the
enthalpy at state two,
H two minus the
enthalpy at state one.
Good. Q.in is going to be
M dot times H
three minus H two.
To stay consistent
with the notation
that we were
using before to
indicate that
something was isentropic,
I will call this
h2s and H twos.
H one is an inlet state,
and H three is going to be
an inlet state
for the turbine.
Our W dot out then is
equal to our dot times
H three minus H
four because that's
at the exit,
and then your Q
dot out here,
which comes from
the condenser
is going to be your dot,
and that's going
to be multiplied
by four minus one.
Questions? Hearing voices.
Cool. It happens.
All right. Good.
So this all
looks good. So
we've got this.
We can write.
Maybe I'll stay
with this slide
just for a second.
From this, right?
So, you know, go ahead.
Yes, please. Why can
we assume that it's
isotropic when
there's a difference?
Because I'm calling
it an ideal cycle.
One. So no, no, no.
So why is it isotropic?
So here, So my
question to you is,
what are you
considering isotropic?
No, no, no. I mean,
which device here?
Which process am
I considering
an isentropic process?
Yes. So which parts don't
have a Q? There's
no Delta Q.
There is Q.
That's it. So these
are adiabatic
and reversible,
which means they are
isotropic, right?
You agree.
So when I'm talking
about a heat addition here
from something
at the exit of
which underwent an
isentropic process,
this would then be
so if state three is
my inlet and I have an
isentropic turbine,
then I have state
four S here, right?
So I would call this h4s.
Now, my heat
rejection is going to
be.h4 minus H one.
So just because I'm
denoting this as h4s,
meaning that to
get to that state,
I underwent
an isentropic work
transfer process
doesn't say anything
about four to one.
Okay? Okay. The side
of the room is on it.
Okay. Other questions?
Clarifications? All
right. Where was I?
Okay, now what
we can do is
we can define an
efficiency, right?
So what is the thermal
efficiency of an engine?
Now, N. N?
Miles. Closer.
Yes, please.
That's one minus TH over
TC is almost Carne,
but not LA Lakers
in the back there?
Okay. It's okay.
You can contribute.
This could be like
a Kobe thing,
you know, so Yes, please.
Name? Sid Network.
Thank you.
Network out w.net over.in.
I'm going to ask
you one question
on the quiz,
and it's going to be that.
Sid's going to nail
it, all right?
Okay, that's going to be
your only question and
spelling your name.
So there you go.
You have a thermal
efficiency of your engine,
the network out over
the net heat in,
okay? So we can
write this.
What's another way
we could write this?
It's a cycle. So from
a first law perspective of
a cycle, what
does that mean?
Yes, the We can plug
in the numbers.
I'm asking more like how
else can I write
this efficiency?
So if I drew the
control volume around
the entire device here.
So if I drew a control
volume around now,
this entire device, Okay.
And I told you
that this also was
a operating under a
steady condition.
What does it mean for
this control volume?
Yes, please. AV, Say
it one more time.
That's it. There's
no change, okay?
So on a good week,
you know, in a
bank account,
what goes in is
what goes out,
right? That's
where you're at.
So I'm saying here that
the thermal efficiency is
my w.net over my.in.
My w.net here is
the w dot workout
minus the w dot
work in, right?
Okay. Good. What must
that be equal to?
Net Q net.
What type of Q
net, though?
Excuse me. Yes,
q.net in, right?
This is q.net out,
this is q.net in,
and that's q.in, okay?
For many cycles, like,
especially when
it was Sterling,
it is much easier
to do this, right?
You could do it this
way. That's fine.
But if it was something
like Sterling,
you got to get
an adiabatic work
transfer processes,
but it's much easier
to calculate this.
So these are two things
that I would say to
David are things to
remember for a
cycle, okay?
This is base stuff to
remember, all right?
Okay. We're having fun.
All right, so
we have this.
If we did our
substitution, right?
So what we have
for the net out,
this is W dot out minus
w.in divided by q.in.
This is equal to
then.h3 minus H
four minus M dot times
h2s minus H one,
and that's all
divided by m dot
times H three minus h2s.
Right? Okay, so
that's one way
to do it, right?
Your masses would
basically cancel
and you could do
some rearrangement.
Another way you
could do it is
the q.net in, right?
Which we can write as
q.in minus Q dot out,
divided by q.in,
which is nothing but
one minus Q dot out
divided by q.in, right?
All right. So here,
if we do it that way,
so we have one minus,
the Q dot out
is going to be
dot times h4s minus H one,
and the q.in is dot
three minus h2s, okay?
And these would go away,
all right? All right.
And so at this point,
What do you do?
Yes, please, David?
I have a question
about the cycle.
The Cary efficiency of
one minus rolled
over to you? Yes.
Do other cycles also have?
I've derived you auto,
diesel, Brayton.
I've told you about
a jet propulsion
efficiency.
I told you that
Sterling becomes Carne.
So yes, I've given you
at least five. I'll
give you a high five.
And by the end of this,
I'll have a couple more,
and then I can give you
two. Alright, good?
They do. They have ones,
but, I mean, at
the end of it,
it's all the same.
This is nothing
but these things.
So that type of thing,
I would not expect you.
Actually, I would like,
be emphatic that
you do not just
go directly to
inefficiency there.
These types of
things, right?
I would expect you to be
able to write out and
show me what they are.
Okay? And you'll see
that if you look
at the practice problems
on Module two review,
I give you a fun one
called Humphrey,
which is a variation
on Brayton
that I gave last year.
They all loved it.
Okay. All right.
Good. So at this point,
what do we do,
though, David?
So now I have the
formulas, right?
So I'm asked to what
I wanted to get
here was the thermal
efficiency of the cycle.
I have a formula for
this. Now, what do I do?
Derive Yeah, you
need to get them.
And the sense of
this is water,
what do I use?
Not ideal guess.
Hopefully not.
Okay. All right.
Yeah, so that's it.
So we can start
to try to figure
out if we know any
of these properties.
So what's given in
our problem, now
that I've done
the derivation,
I can tell you
what's typically
given in a rankin problem.
What's typically given in
a rakin problem is
state three. Why
state three?
Two things. The first
is that it's the
hottest point.
This is where you're
transferring heat in.
It's also the point of
hottest pressure,
all right?
So what literally
sets the limits
of the efficiency
of this cycle is,
can I make a boiler that
does not explode, right?
Can I make a boiler
that does not basically
melt and it's made of
materials, all right?
So here, All right,
we're given state three,
and because it's a
superheated vapor
is super critical
sometimes,
you're going to be
given a T three here,
in this case of
350 degrees Celsius and
a P three here that's
equal to three megapascal,
so 30 times
atmospheric pressure.
These are not
particularly high values.
Yes, please, Mao.
Why would you connect
the water from
the condenser One
more time for me.
I like the water that
goes through condenser
and for
the boil water that's
where it goes through.
So the thing is that
the water that you would
put into this condenser
that I'm not showing
here that I'm
representing as
Q out is water
that's great
for humans and
like the worst diet you
could give a machine.
So they contain
things that
will corrode
these components.
They'll calcify,
they'll like
put limescale and
stuff into it.
The water that's, like,
inside here that
you boil is,
like, the purest water.
It doesn't contain
anything that can, like,
precipitate and
destroy a boiler.
My buddy used to work
for Mel like Toledo,
and he solds instruments
that would monitor,
like, water quality
in the plant.
So you could do
something like that,
but there will be a cost,
and the cost will be that,
you know, this will look
like it's on a very
unhealthy an enjoyable
but unhealthy diet.
Yes, please.
It's like a non
ethical question.
Is there ever a reason to
not amin generator in
any of these cycles but
it seems like such an easy
I mean, it all depends.
So you're going to be able
to answer that question
by the end of the course
because you're
going to be able to
turn this into
efficiencies.
And if you know money
and how things cost,
you can turn that
into, like, you know,
several year ROI, and
then you go to
your boss and say,
Hey, here's the payback
period on this.
This is the time frame,
and they all have
a policy if it's
maybe like when I
worked two years,
if I could make a project
that showed that I
could make the money back
in less than two years,
we got to do that.
All right. Other
questions?
Okay, so we're doing
properties now.
So we have this? Water is
a pure substance.
So we have complete
information.
I know H three and
I know S three
specific enthropy and
specific entropy here.
Great. I To state
four to state four,
again, we did the entropy
control volume
analysis there.
We showed that for
adiabatic reversible
processes isentropic.
Steady flow means
we don't have
change in entropy in
the control volume.
The isentropic part
means we don't have
entropy generation
because it's
single inlet, single
outlet, right?
S in is S out.
What is the S in?
There was S three,
the out is that S four
is equal to S three.
The other piece of
information which
is typically going
to be given in
a ranking process
is the pressure.
P four, in this case,
it's 75 pa. What
determines this
pressure is
the temperature of
the cooling water.
So basically, you would
love this pressure
to be zero.
What sets this temperature
is you bring in
cooling water or air,
and you blow that over the
outside of these tubes,
and it brings it to
some temperature.
You have that temperature,
and you know that
this is going to be,
you want to bring
this down to
being a saturated vapor.
So with that
temperature and
knowing that it's
a saturated vapor,
it's going to set
the pressure, okay?
75 kPa, it's okay.
All right? That's on
the higher side
of a value.
So this temperature
here, if you look
at the saturation
temperature here,
my guess is that it's
over 30 Celsius there.
All right?
Okay. But the
point is that with
this, I have, right?
I could have
complete information
from this process.
It means that I
know my my H four.
I could also know T
four if I cared
about it, all right?
And to be consistent
with what I wrote before,
because it's isentropic,
I'll write h4s,
and let's say t4s.
Going along this to
state one to state
one. All right.
So this is a condenser,
this is a heat exchanger.
So it means that P one
is going to be equal
to P four, right?
We're not going to
have a pressure
drop across that device.
The one piece of
information that
is implicit,
I believe,
in most rankin
problems, and again,
this is what
differentiates
from a Braden analysis,
is that it's a condenser.
What comes out
of a condenser?
What is the purpose
Minus Vf over Vg
minus Vf is one.
We call it vapor
quality when
it's one, you're a vapor.
So if it's not
one, what should
you be when you're here
when you're a liquid?
If you're not one, you're
zero binary, okay?
So the quality at
state one is equal
to I'm going to
give everyone on
this side a zero.
That's what you're
going to get, okay?
So this is the condensed
phase here, right?
So you're a liquid.
Your vapor
quality is what?
Nah, zero. Okay.
It's good. This is what's
impl in the ranking.
It will not be mentioned
to you since you were in
this lecture and I
spent 5 minutes on it.
I expect you all
to know that.
I know you. I
know your names.
If I grade this and you
don't have it,
you're all done.
I'll learn his name later.
Allright? So you have
this P one and P four.
And from this,
you'll have H one,
and you will
have you'll have
H one and you will
have S one, okay?
If I hear more talking,
I'm going to call
on you and spend 5 minutes
on you, all
right? It's good.
So H one and S
one, you know,
and now we come
into the pump.
Now we have state two.
So in state two, again,
this is the ideal
case, right?
So, and the first thing
is you need to look
forward, right?
So with state
two connected to
state three of a
heat exchanger.
So since I know the
pressure at state three,
it means I know the
pressure at state two.
P two is equal to P
three, one, okay?
That's on one side
of the state.
On the other side
of the state, you
have a pump
that's operating
adiabatically and versibly.
When I do the
control volume
analysis with the entropy,
they're steady flow,
so there's no change in
entropy of the
control volume.
It's isotropic is
adiabatic and reversible,
means there's no
entropy generation.
S.in is S dot out.
Because it's steady flow,
dot in is M dot out,
which means that S two is
equal to S three, okay?
Or, I'm sorry, S two is
equal to S one, right?
Here, right? Because
it's two to one.
So S two is equal to
h is equal to S one,
which we had there.
And it means then we're
basically able
to get H two,
right, h2s out of that.
Okay? So all of that,
you would just
put these into Pi
color and you would
then get out
the enthalpies
that you need, right?
Right?
These are the enthalpies
that you would
need to determine
the efficiency,
which was the goal, right?
So let's just look.
Are we correct?
H4h 4h4s here, right?
H one, you have
H one here,
H three and h2s
are here and here.
Questions? Yes, please.
Finding H's.
So if I tell you
it's just ideal,
that's ideal, it's that.
What do you think
I would give you?
What additional
information would
I have to give you
if it was not isotropic?
What do you think
I would provide?
Next. E of what?
That's it. So basically,
we define what we call
isotropic efficiencies
of a turbine,
of a compressor,
of a pump.
So if it wasn't ideal,
I would say something
to the effect of,
you know, here's a turbine
that operates with
an isentropic efficiency
of 0.8, right?
And so if I told you that,
so let's say I have
my turbine and I have
this isentropic
efficiency of 0.8, right?
The isentropic
efficiency is
W dot actual divided
by W dot isotropic, right?
So for a steady flow
device, in our case,
that would look
something like
H three minus H
for a divided by H
three minus h4s.
I just went through
the exercise
of determining h4s.
This is 0.8.
H three is always
going to be given,
then you solve
for H four A,
and that's the
actual. Yes, please.
I thought that No.
W is not TDS.
No, that's a no.
The whole point of work
when we start off as
a basic analysis
is we treat
these as isotropic
devices.
What differentiates
work from
heat is entropy, okay?
I assume there
was just lots of
midterms this week
and we're all cooked.
Thank you. I'll be a
little nicer next time.
Sorry. Okay. All right.
Other questions?
Although they're
good questions.
Yes, please, in
the back. Name?
Elias.
I mean, I would say for
a rank in cycle,
you will learn.
You will know this
and it will become
second nature to
think about it.
I can't say right now if
I'm going to draw
it pictorially.
At the moment, I feel in
the world of large
language models,
everything can be
represented as text.
So maybe I'll
just say like,
Hey,
these are the components
like I have here.
I have a rank in cycle
consisting of a
pump, a boiler,
a turbine, and
a condenser,
and here's some
properties now
analyze the efficiency.
That's probably how I
would give you a problem.
My question is always
know, let's step
back a second.
A condenser is a subset
of a heat exchanger.
What do I say
literally every time
I say the word heat
exchanger in this class?
It's an isoberic device.
A heat exchanger is by
definition isoberic.
That should be
in your head.
I'm not going to
tell you that.
At the end of a condenser,
he, for example,
is never going
to forget that
the quality at the exit
of a condenser is zero,
that it's going to come
out as a condensed state.
I'm also never
going to forget it.
I think those are things,
but this comes
with practice and
looking and having that?
Other questions?
Yes, please.
Area of this graph.
So if I took the
temperature and I
multiplied it
by kilojoules
per kilogram there,
what are my units?
So what would that
be a total thing or
a specific thing?
Yeah. Other questions?
David? This is
combined with cycle.
Where was from
the, that's an
excellent question.
I feel like you read ahead
and are setting me up.
This is wonderful.
I'll answer it
in a second.
Other questions?
You're going in the
right direction though.
If not, okay. So this
is how it looked like.
So again, I've
represented all of what
I wrote here on this.
So there's the X one.
Here's a good reason
to read ahead.
Sometimes you'll
see the answers.
Okay. Right, so this
is how this looks
like on the
TS diagram with
those states.
Here's how it
would look like
on the PV diagram.
What you'll note
through all of
this is that we
stay below the
super critical or
the critical point
of water, okay?
Most modern power plants,
nuclear fossil
fuel based ones,
do not operate with this.
They go Boilers are now
made nowadays to be
able to withstand
much higher
pressures there.
And so this allows them,
when they do the heat
addition process,
to go into a super
critical regime.
Now, to remind you
about super critical,
super critical is I cannot
differentiate
between a liquid
and a vapor, okay?
They are one.
They're
indistinguishable, right?
Why is that?
Here, I'm a
saturated liquid.
Here I'm a
saturated vapor.
At this point, they
merge and they're
critical.
So the closer you get
to the critical point,
it becomes harder
and harder to tell
the difference until
you cannot, okay?
The very commonly used
supercritical fluid
is CO two to make
decaffeinated coffee.
Alright, maybe that's what
you guys are drinking
today, alright?
So this is what
you'd have.
So this is then the case.
What you'll note here
is when I have
three to four S,
I am falling
below the dome,
so that could be a
little bit problematic.
I'm above the temperature,
but I don't know
the pressure here.
So I'll show you
the PV diagram,
and you see this
process is above that.
Questions? Questions?
Why are they relevant?
Because you asked me,
why am I doing isentropic?
I'm doing isentropic
because it's ideal.
The way that we make
something actual
and not ideal for
work transfer
devices is we
talk about isotropic
efficiencies,
which is the reality
divided by the ideal for
a turbine and the exact
opposite vice versa
for a compressor.
It's an easy
way in ME 40 in
a sophomore level class to
take something that's
ideal and make it real.
Yes. That's what I said.
Okay, good. Other
questions? Okay.
Yes, we want to look
at efficiencies,
a modern fossil
steam power plant,
the thermal efficiency is
about 40%, which is
a pretty big value.
A nuclear plant is 34%,
and the reason why
it's lower is
that there are
safety reasons for
how high you can
let T three go
in the nuclear?
It's conservative
industry.
Okay, that's good.
To David's point about
combining cycles,
which I won't even
do in the next one.
Maybe it's a
lecture after that,
is that the exit of
the Brayton cycle has
very hot gases, right?
So we were talking
about using
regenerators to
recover some
of that and use it.
You could also just hook
it up and use it as
the Q in to what's
called the bottom cycle.
So you could go in with
that heat out of the
exhaust of a Brayton,
put that into a
heat exchanger
that would be, let's say,
the boiler of a rakin
and take that
lower grade heat
and still get
power, all right?
This is, um, something
that is done, okay?
What fluids would you use?
You could try
to use water,
but with water, right,
to make that work,
you need high temperatures
and all of that.
The heat that comes
out of the brain
and the exhaust may
not be warm enough.
So what you might
do is to select
a fluid that boils
easier, okay?
So fluids that
boil easier are,
um, refrigerants.
So refrigerants are there.
So R 134 A's
are an example.
Carbon dioxide
is another one.
Carbon dioxide is
a very commonly
used refrigerant.
A lots known about it.
There's a lot of
benefits to it,
but you could
use that to be
basically running
the bottom cycle.
Those are commonly
called organic ankin.
So organic ankin is
like, Okay, not water.
I'm going to use
a different fluid
that's more like
a refrigerant,
and I'll take care of the
lower grade heat with it.
The one thing I'll mention
here is that you can
also run CO two,
since I mentioned super
critical here for
Rankin and water,
You can take CO two and
also run it as a rankin.
And what's
interesting here
is for these cases,
while you would guess
that this would be
a vapor cycle because you
would expect some
condensation to occur,
the examples that I looked
up before I came
today actually
showed this running all in
the supercritical regime,
which resembles wet?
What cycle looks
like that?
So I have a fluid that I
cannot differentiate
from a gas there,
and I have no condensation
and no phase
change happening.
What does that
look like? David?
Is it a car? Not a carnal.
The temperatures
are not constant.
So what power cycle did we
just analyze before that
had no phase change?
Sorry, so the B
Brayton, right?
That might look like
Brayton, you had basically
the heat addition
and out with it there.
Okay? Yeah, and you
can read about it. It's
pretty interesting.
So where people
talk about gaining
efficiencies and
what they do,
this is one
area of the DOE
Department of Energy
that was looking.
You can read about
a ten megawatt power
plant that went with it,
okay? Where is this going?
Where is this going?
So that's one
example of, again,
where I took two cycles,
and I kind of put
them in series.
We talked about
regenerators before
with Braden.
We'll talk about that in
the context of Rankin.
Another way that
you could do
this is the following.
So another way to
boost efficiency in
a cycle is with
what's called reheat.
So what is it? It's
original rankin.
I got a boiler, a pump
a condenser,
and a turbine.
All I do is I
take the exit,
um, you know, fluid here
out of the turbine.
I run it again through
my boiler and then send it
back into a lower
pressure turbine
that's connected
in series, okay?
So next lecture and
the one after that
are going to be like
additional tricks
that we can use to
squeeze every bit of
energy out of
that Q and we
have to get into
work, okay?
With that, I'm
going to close it.
Thank you so much for
your participation,
especially yours, for
letting me have that.
I feel like that was
very good, okay?
Alright, have a good one.