Okay, so we're talking
about the second
law. Yes, please.
Module one is over.
No. This is the
second module, okay?
This is the second act
of our play, okay?
Or in our Tour de
France analysis, right?
Now we're entering
the Pyrenees.
We climb a bit, all right?
Yeah, so after today,
you're going to be
able to complete these
you should be able to
do the following, okay?
Okay, so the first thing
we're going to start
with is the following
question, okay?
Hopefully, following
your pre work
and previewing,
I know that you've read
it all and are on it,
so you're going
to ace it, okay?
So a statement, right?
Lord Calvin said
a transformation
whose only final
result is to
transform into work heat
extracted from a source,
which is at the
same temperature
throughout is
impossible, okay?
I'm drawing a diagram of
this because I like
pictures, okay?
So here I have a
heat reservoir
at temperature T,
Um, heat is being
transferred from
this reservoir into
a piston. Hold on.
It's not active yet
because I'm slow.
I have technical
problems today.
In this isothermal,
expanding ideal gas,
and some work is being
transferred out, okay?
So, give me a second.
Let me activate
the pole because my phone
is also misbehaving.
It doesn't make me
want to go onto Module
two, either. Let's see.
Go to activities, blah,
blah, blah. Fall 2025.
There's our polls,
six B and Calvin's
statement.
Okay, so that's
active there.
Um, And so look at
the poll and see
basically the questions.
And then what we're
going to do is then
kind of talk through
we're going to talk
through some
of that, okay?
Are there any
questions before we
get started in
this activity?
Wonderful. Let's go.
F. Do,
do. Which one do I want?
Maybe we want this one.
Okay, so there
was a bunch.
So there's several
versions of this.
If you read the
book, you know,
they kind of say
the same thing,
but in different thought
experiments, okay?
So different thought
experiments there.
So, the first thing
is that, yeah,
what we just said, so, you
know, is impossible.
Alternatively, right,
it's impossible
for any device that
operates on a cycle
to receive heat from
a single reservoir
and produce a net
amount of work, right?
So this whole part that
I have to basically
contract,
and in order to contract,
it will have to cool.
Right? I'll
basically have to
take some heat out
of that system,
cool it in order to
come back, all right?
I'll probably also have
to put a little bit of
work in to compress.
You probably would
agree with that.
I'll have to do that,
so I'll have to
put some work in,
and I'll have to take
some heat out, okay?
Now, the first law
doesn't Put any,
let's say, constraints
on this, right?
And here's basically
a thought experiment,
okay?
So let's say I
have some system
here, some control volume.
I have my single I
have my reservoir.
Remember, reservoir is
essentially a thing
a thermal reservoir
is a thing
where you can transfer
heat in and out of it,
and its temperature
doesn't change, right?
Earth is basically,
you know,
probably, for us, like
a reservoir, right?
You think about geothermal
and taking heat
out, right.
So you have a reservoir,
and you can transfer
some heat in, uh, to that.
You can transfer
some work out of it
and you can transfer
some work into
it, all right?
If I write the first law,
right, I could talk
about a workout,
a W in, and a Q in,
and I could make those
things balance, right?
So the first law is
not going to put any,
um, you know,
it may or may not put
any some, you know,
constraints, um,
constraints into it, okay?
But from the
second law, right,
as we just showed
basically in
that experiment,
in order to actually
do that as a cycle,
you would have to
take some heat
out of this in order to
make that in order to
make that work, okay?
And that's what this green
this Kelvin Pluck
statement says, okay?
It will become clearer
with time, okay?
All right. Yeah, then we
have a Clausius
postulate, okay?
So in Clausius, so
a transformation whose
only final result is to
transfer heat
from a body at
a given temperature
to a body at
a higher temperature
is impossible.
The way to think about
this experiment
is the following.
I have a control
volume here.
I have it in
diathermal, right?
So it's thermally
in contact with
a reservoir at a
high temperature
and also one at a
low temperature.
And my question is,
what direction does
heat flow here?
Loud. High to low,
yeah. Okay. Okay?
Things at high
concentration
tend to move to regions
of low concentration.
That's the second law.
That's how I understand
the second law.
You take a balloon, right?
It's compressed,
you pop it,
the air expands,
and it moves out,
you spray perfume
here, and it diffuses,
you make something
hot here
and it spreads, okay?
So that's essentially
what, you know,
the clauses
statement is that.
So if I have something
at a high temperature,
heat is going
to flow or be
transferred to
the regions where
it's then colder and
not the other way
around, okay?
Okay. Cool.
You can ask you
solve things like
why is time only
one direction.
Yeah, and you could think
about Clausius, okay?
Here's the first
chair of physics
at ETH where I used to be.
Um Yeah, exactly.
And so that's kind
of a simpler way
of of writing it, okay?
Cool. He flows by
conduction, blah,
blah, blah.
Do I have one
more? Hold on.
Do I have one more
drawing for you?
So rewriting.
Mm hm mm. Mm hm mm.
Yes, I think for this one,
we have a drawing, okay?
So this this statement
is a little bit
more tricky.
It was more tricky
for me when I was
trying to visualize it.
Um, I think that
the the way that
this statement
looks like is if we
drew a control
volume here,
and I said that, am
I saying that I
have a reservoir?
Yes, I'm saying that I
have a reservoir
that's maybe
cold and I have a
reservoir that's hot.
If I want to
spontaneously transfer
heat from the cold
into this like this,
this is not
possible, okay?
And this would be analogous
to the one that I
have to the one
that I have
written and
to the one that I
have written here.
So this version of, okay,
I have some system
here, whatever that is.
I don't have any work
transferred into it.
I cannot pump heat from
the low temperature.
So if TC is less than TH,
this is not allowed, okay?
For the same reason,
right, you know,
this is not
allowed because
heat would
basically flow in
the opposite direction
unless what?
You have to add
work, right?
And what's that device
usually called?
Compressor, right?
So in a heat
pump, basically,
this is your
compressor here,
and you'd have
some W, some W in.
And then, in this
case, actually,
this still wouldn't
be allowed.
What you'd end
up with is that
this is the QH,
because if you're
going to write this as
the first law
for, let's say,
a steady operating
condition here,
what enters it has to
be equal to what
goes out, right?
So QH then must
be equal to
W in plus QL, right?
So if I drew
this as, like,
a control volume,
it's under steady
conditions,
what leaves must
be equal to what's
entering, okay? All right.
Yeah. So and again,
in order to basically
extract heat from
the colder body and
move it to the
warmer body,
you have to put
some work, right?
You basically have to put
some work in, right?
And that's what's
shown here, right?
So this last statement
that we had here,
right, is I can't have
a system that
looks like this.
Again, heat,
essentially pumping
having heat move in
the exact opposite
direction
as we would
normally expect
without doing some
work in, all right?
And that's the Clausius
statement, okay?
Questions about
second law?
Sure. David, right?
Yes. Okay. It's
a violation
of Kevin Clark because.
So you can never
have a heat engine
operating on a cycle that
has 100% thermal
efficiency.
So I can never have an
engine that
looks like this.
So I can't take heat
from one reservoir,
put it into an engine,
and only get work network
out of it, right?
I will have to right?
I will basically have
to take some heat, right?
I'll basically have
to take some heat
out of that there, okay?
All right. Other
questions?
And this one, I mean,
at the end of it,
it's a more complicated
way of writing it,
but this one makes,
like, perfect sense,
right? This is
more intuitive.
This would basically be
a more intuitive thing
because heat doesn't
spontaneously
flow from regions
that are cold to
regions that
are hot, okay?
As you might
want sometimes
in a room, okay? Cool.
Yeah, so then this
so the reason
why this is important
is because for
a long time,
there was a bunch of
snake oil salesmen
out there who
were trying to,
like, come up with devices
that could beat
thermo, right?
The only reason why
we have really the
first and the
second law is
because no one's produced,
right, a machine that
says that it
doesn't work, okay?
You know, these
are postulates.
And believe me,
there have been some
very smart
people who have,
like, looked at that
and said, you know,
I'm going to be able to
beat it for
obvious reasons,
if you can beat these
laws, you could get,
right, fantastically
wealthy, all right?
Um, Ava machine.
So these kinds of
machines that
violate these laws,
they call them
perpetual mobile
or perpetual
motion machines.
And they can be
stated as, like,
either a perpetual
motion machine
of the first kind or
of the second kind.
A perpetual
motion machine of
the first kind means it
violates the
first law, okay?
It means that I
have more energy
leaving my control volume,
right, my system, that I
have energy
entering, right?
And you can't create
energy, right?
It can only be
transformed, right?
So those ones are
pretty straightforward
to analyze.
For the second kind, it's
a violation of the
second law, okay?
And then usually
in those cases,
it would be right?
Maybe a system like that.
So I have 100%
conversion of
work from heat on a cycle,
but you got to look at it.
You got to think
more about it.
It's not maybe as
straightforward,
okay? If you want
to see an example.
So the one with my
students, you know,
my doctoral students,
when I would talk
to them in this,
those would be like one
example, all right?
So you have your
pump, right?
You move a fluid. Let's
say it's like water.
I transfer heat into that.
So through like a boiler.
I run that through
a turbine.
I get network out, and
then I run it
all again, okay?
And this doesn't work,
okay? It doesn't
work, right?
For the same reason that
we mentioned before,
think about the piston,
you could have
the heat in,
you could get
the work out,
but you need to
return back to
the initial state, okay?
And you cannot
return back to
the initial state
without cooling, right?
You basically need to cool
off the steam here.
You got to condense
it down to
a liquid because
out of this,
it's still a vapor, right?
So, out of here,
you'd have a vapor,
and that vapor would
go into a pump.
You don't put vapor
through pumps.
No, no, no, all right?
And then, right,
it would basically
go back in and be that.
This is not something
that could operate.
And in Chapter ten,
Or in week ten, we'll get
into what are called
rank in cycles.
We'll get into the systems
and what they actually
should look like to
operate correctly, okay?
Um, Yes, okay?
That's one thing.
The second thing
is that when
we deal with
the second law,
we're going to talk
a lot about
reversible, okay?
Reversible,
right? So what's
reversible mean? It
means that, right?
I do something so
slowly that I don't
really have any
friction, right?
So it's like I
take a spring
and I compress
it really slow,
and then I let it
go and it comes
back to exactly where
I started, right?
The reason why
we're obsessed
with this or why
we'll use it
is it's going
to help us to
understand theoretical
limits, right?
So we're going to be able
to understand
and say, like,
is this perpetual
motion or not, right?
Is this something
that, uh,
um, you know, can
happen physically.
One, and then two tells
you things about,
like, what optimum
could be, right?
It's kind of like
a glass half full,
but you look at it
and you say, okay,
assuming these kind
of idealities,
is this like a
good system, okay?
And we're going to talk
about reversible,
all right?
Just to remind you what
that would look like,
right in this
video, right?
So we have essentially
the same initial states.
You do something
reversibly
versus something
irreversibly,
and here you can compress
a lot more, right?
I can do more PDV
work transfer in,
in the case when I
do it reversibly
compared to where it's
irreversible, right?
And what's happening in
an irreversible
case on the right,
physically, Yeah.
And so basically you
move them quickly.
You create some,
like, vortices,
right, some eddies, the
fluid moves, right?
So you give it
some kinetic energy
or movement there,
and then it
dissipates viscously.
Basically, you
warm it, right?
Instead of, like,
all of that work
going in and
compressing it,
it's like in the
spring example,
you heat up the spring.
You move too
quickly, and you
have some heating
there, okay?
And so that's why you see
the temperature
here is higher.
So when you do
that irreversibly,
it's a higher
temperature than
than the other
case, all right?
Yes, okay?
And again, we talked,
you know, a
little bit, you
know, about
efficiency before.
But again, when we
assume these idealities,
we're going to be
able to set, like,
an absolute upper limit
of efficiency
for the system,
and this is called
second law,
second law efficiency,
it allows you to rank
and say what's better.
And again, kind of
like a North Star,
it guides you. All right?
Yeah, so friction,
mixing, blah, blah, blah,
all the fun stuff
is what's irreversible,
all right?
Okay, so we did
perpetual emotion.
We talked about
the second law.
I want to get into
the most ideal, like,
the most ideal
cycle that sets
the absolute upper limit
of efficiency is
the Carnal, right?
So remember Carnal
Sadi Carino,
he was a French guy.
Old man worked, you
know, for Napoleon.
And he was obsessed with
making steam engines
more efficient, okay?
Um, And I'll take
you through essentially
what his cycle is,
and then we can talk
about the finding.
But in a car no, you
have four stages, okay?
So you have four stages.
The first stage is what
we already looked at
the heat in and the
expansion, right?
So I take heat from some
energy source at TH,
and let's say I transfer
it into the system.
This could be a
piston cylinder,
but I transfer
heat in, and I
undergo what's called
isothermal expansion.
So that's the first
thing that we looked at.
The second stage is now
I take that cylinder,
and instead of
transferring
heat in isothermally,
I suddenly
insulate it, okay?
It's not a
practical cycle,
but it's a thought
experiment, okay?
And I insulate it,
and then I allow it
to expand
adiabatically, okay?
So I have isothermal
expansion,
then I have
adiabatic expansion.
And during the
adiabatic expansion,
what do you think
happens to temperature?
If I let gas expand,
what happens to
the temperature?
All right. So you're
going to expect
basically an
adiabatic expansion.
Your temperature
is going to
go, you know, down.
And then at that stage,
you're going to
put this cylinder.
You're going to take
the insulation off.
You're going
to set it onto
a colder reservoir.
You're going to
transfer heat out
QL that's transferred out,
and then you're going to
do an adiabatic
compression.
So then you're basically
going to go in.
You're going to compress
this thing and then
basically bring it
back to the initial
state that you had there.
So this whole
part where we had
the heat sink and
the heat out,
that's a key aspect of
getting it back
there, all right?
Another key attribute
of the carne,
is it doesn't matter about
the substance, right?
It's independent
of the substance.
All that you care about is
the temperature of
the hot reservoir
and the temperature of
the cold reservoir.
And these two
things together set
the efficiency, right?
And all systems, okay,
if you want to make
any thermal engine
more efficient,
you essentially maximize
the temperature
that you get heat from,
and you minimize
the temperature
that you transfer
the heat to.
But really, the key
thing is you know,
transferring heat
from something
that's very,
very hot, okay?
That's another thing
the first law
didn't tell you.
The first law
just said that
conservation of
energy, right?
So, um, you know,
work and heat
are essentially,
you know, equivalent.
The second law
basically says
that energy has
a quality to it,
okay, especially with
heat, all right?
The warmer, you know,
that something is that
you transfer heat from,
the better the
quality is, the
more useful it
is, all right?
Okay.
Yeah, if you want to then
put that onto a cycle.
So if you want to then
basically see what
that would look
like in a cycle,
a PV diagram.
So here would
be one to two.
So the black lines are
your isotherms, right?
So I'm transferring
heat in one to two.
I'm also doing
expansion PV work.
Adiabatic expansion,
isothermal compression,
adiabatic
compression, right?
And the network then
is the area that's
shaded there and
the heat transfer
processes are shown.
You can also do
that on unpols
if you want to launch
that notebook,
you can also see then what
this process
looks like, okay?
Cool. So I put
some of you to
sleep. Yes, please.
Question? So if you
were a efficiency.
But it's not a
cycle, right?
Because you
don't basically
come back to the
initial state.
If you want to get back
to where you started,
and this is what
we'll work through
to basically
get back where you
started and run a cycle,
if you put heat
in, you're going
to have to take
heat out, okay?
And for the ones
we've looked at here,
we're going to also be
putting some work in.
So there's going to
be like heat in,
work out, heat out,
work in, right?
And those four
things that I
mentioned there are going
to form the basis and
of a lot of
the cycles we're
going to look at.
Okay? Yes, please.
What does a graph look
like when it's more
efficient versus
less efficient?
What does it look
like when it's more
efficient versus
less efficient?
So how to answer that.
Um, I'm avoiding
saying a word.
I have to avoid a
property to get it.
I will say for now,
that really, you know,
if I have a very high
temperature source and
a relatively low
temperature sink
that I'm
transferring from,
this is essentially
going to be
what, you know, what
matters the most.
The rest of these
things are going
to be little details
that are there,
but to a leading order,
that's what it is.
And that's what
you think about.
If you look, for
example, um,
You know, what
sets essentially,
like the limits of
efficiencies on
our engines now is
that metal melts,
right? Like, you
could go higher.
You do combustion, right?
You could do, you know,
nuclear, you concentrate
solar, right?
But what sets, like
the limit then of
the efficiencies
of these things
is that at some point,
you know, steel stainless
steel melts, right?
That's in there, the
turbines go away,
even like some
combustion ones, right?
Think about aircraft
and stuff, too.
Yeah, you'd love
to go hotter,
but materials that's why
we have this beautiful
building, you know,
material scientists who
do really good work
to try to make these
things survive it.
Yes, please.
So 100% efficiency.
Is not possible.
Full stop.
What's the highest
efficiency? Of what?
Of an engine. So if you
want to talk about
efficiencies of,
like, a modern
power plant,
steam electric
those things are north of
40 to 50%, right,
efficient.
What did they start
with? 1%, right?
Like, what, in
his day when he
was doing steam engines,
these things were, like,
less than a
percent efficient,
and then with time,
they've gotten
much better.
It also depends on what
you call efficiency.
So on this campus,
we used to do
co generation.
So it's co generation.
I put heat in.
I run, you know, so I
do combustion, right?
I run a a turbine, I
generate electricity.
I have that heat
that comes out.
That heat that comes
out, if it comes out at
a high enough temperature,
can be useful, right?
You can then do district
heating, right?
And so in those cases,
depending on how one
defines efficiencies,
those things might
be north of 80%,
90%, okay?
Because then
the heat, it's
not wasted, it's
used, okay?
And we want to
know what, like,
the biggest problem is
we have today is we
have a ton of
waste heat out of
a data center,
and we just, like, reject
it to, like,
the atmosphere.
And they call it
free cooling.
And there's nothing
free about that.
That's, like, insane.
Yes. Okay. Other
questions?
All right. So here's
what I want to do.
So basically, let's look.
So let's get into a little
bit of perpetual motion.
I mean, bear with
me for this.
I appreciate you guys
staying with me today,
but we have one of
these carno cycle.
Remember, we're
transferring heat
in from something at
constant temperature,
and then we're
rejecting it to
something that's also
at a constant temperature,
but but it's lower.
Let me launch the poll and
then can discuss
with this.
Blah, blah, blah.
Here. Okay. There we go.
Um All right, so you
want to be stingy, okay?
Just like I showed
you with the
other machine,
the perpetual motion, and
you want to
decrease QL, okay?
Instead of compressing
isothermally from
state three to four,
you decided to do it
adiabatically, okay?
Right? So you're
at state three,
and instead of
going to four,
you do adiabatic
compression.
So the first question is
what state do
you end up at?
And two, what do
you expect to
happen to Wt out, okay?
Really appreciate your
support in the class.
Look through this.
And if you get this,
you understand the
second law, and,
you know, the rest
of this course
is going to be
very easy for you.
Okay? If you have
questions, I'm circulating.
D do, did do. Okay.
Um Yeah,
so this is what's called
the fully
reversible cycle.
You know, you can
basically you can
reverse this thing.
And if you run
it in reverse,
instead of it being
a thermal engine,
it is a heat pump, okay?
So you can run a Karno to
produce, you know, power,
but you can also run
a Karno to pump heat.
It's just that
one is clockwise,
and the heat pump is
counterclockwise, right,
in terms of the way
the directions look.
And with that, I'm
going to close it.
Thank you so much,
Dave, for your
participation,
me giving you
two questions.
I love that. Also the
answers in the debate.
If you have any
questions, I'm up here.
Thank you.