All right, I got 210.
So today, we're going to
get into entropy
analysis, right?
So till now we've
done entropy,
and now today
we're going to use
it for analysis, right.
We're starting to
check off a bunch of
these major learning
objectives.
Yeah, so today, you'll be
able to analyze
a compressor.
So we'll talk about a
compressor and ways
to make it more
effective involving
inter cooling.
And then we'll start with
a general entropy
balance and
apply this to a
heat exchanger.
Okay, so before that,
to understand if
you understand
this property, okay?
So, you're all here.
So yes, you're the
few in the product.
So in this problem,
what you're
given is a
reversible process.
So let's say a steady
flow reversible process
that's going from states
one to two to three.
You have a plot here of
temperature in
degrees Celsius
versus specific entropy
on the horizontal axis.
And the question is,
in going 1-2 to three,
what is the total
heat transfer
for this reversible
process?
Okay? 2 minutes.
We take a quick
check on you,
and then if you pass,
I will proceed, and then
if not, we will see.
Any questions?
Great. It's a good
intimate crowd today.
Thank you. I'll circulate.
Let's see what
their correctness.
I never even get to
this part of it.
Yeah, there you go. Okay.
Now, suddenly, 44%.
Awesome. I'm happy.
I can go on.
Say it again. Sorry.
Okay.
Okay. So before I get
into the whole entropy
analysis and that,
I just want to take
a step back and
then remind
ourselves of
what we've been
analyzing, right?
So, essentially, we've
had two types of systems,
one which we called
as a closed system,
right, piston cylinders.
No mass in or out.
The only way we can
exchange energy
is through heater
work, okay?
Good. We had a
second system
where we could where
it was open, right?
We call these control
volumes, okay?
You know, the book
calls these
control volumes.
I would call it kind
of an you know,
it's an open system.
You can bring
heat and work in,
but you can also
bring in mass, right?
So in bringing mass in,
mass can also bring
energy into it, okay?
So that's really the two
differences with it.
When we analyze this one,
we tended to talk
about, like,
a delta U is equal
to something, right?
And here, we talked about,
like, rate
notation, right?
So we'd say,
like, the rate of
change of work
in, you know,
w.in, W dot out
there, okay?
We speak about
the work, right,
the type of
work, you know,
work transfer useful work
that can be transferred
out of the system.
In the case of a
piston, right,
that was PDV, right?
So we have
pressure, right?
We'll be integrating PDV,
and that would get us
to some useful work.
In the case of
the open system,
so things like a
turbine or, like,
the pinwheel example,
right there,
it's VDP, okay, right?
Here, the volume changes,
and here it
does not, okay?
And the way that this one
produces then work
is because you
have big pressure
differences that
are across those
devices, right?
So PDV and VDP there Okay.
Great. What I'd like to
do now is then this,
remember I said at
the beginning,
we're going to,
you know, see about
ways that we can design
compressor systems to
be more efficient.
And I'm going to show
you this example here.
So in this example,
you're doing
two stages of compression.
And in between
the two stages,
you do what's called
intercooling, okay?
You basically
cool it, right?
What's the logic
behind doing this?
If I take a gas and
I compress it there,
even if I do it
isotropically,
it's going to get
very hot, okay?
You're going to get it's
going to get pretty hot.
And then if I go
again and I try
to compress now
that very hot gas,
you can imagine that maybe
that might be more
difficult to do, okay?
So you put all
that work in,
you put a lot of
energy in, okay?
You get it to a
high pressure.
You take heat out without
basically changing
the pressure,
and then you go
on and compress.
And the purpose of
this example is
to illustrate that by
doing this cooling stage,
actually you can
reduce the amount of,
let's say, electricity you
would need to
run this, right?
And this is used, right?
This is a system
that's actually
used, right?
What I'm showing
you on the right is
essentially the solution
to what we have.
So where is this
going right
before I get
deeply into it?
The blue line. So
we start here,
right? So this is air.
We're starting off at
100 PA in 27 degrees
Celsius, right?
So it's like, you
know, room temperature
conditions.
In the blue stage, right?
And the dashed
black line that I
have here is the isobar.
So this is the line
of constant pressure
on this TS diagram.
If I just did
a single stage
of compression, all right?
I could do that,
so I could go
from this state
up to
the higher pressure
that's totally valid.
Or we could do what I'm
showing here where I
go up to some you know,
I compress up to
some pressure, okay?
I cool it, and
then I basically
do the same thing.
I basically compress
again and I get
onto the same
cobar, right?
What you can
anticipate from
this heat transfer process
is what changes
from here to here?
What do you see?
Like what's
the first thing
that's different for
you on that plot from
the right to
the left there?
Okay. Every value
is a lower.
It's entropy lower, right?
And so what does it mean
if I go from here to here?
So if I have an entropy
value that's here,
and then I go to it here,
what does that mean?
Or let me say
it another way.
I told you before
about a relationship
between entropy
and heat, okay?
So am I putting heat
into this or am I
taking heat out of it,
if I'm decreasing entropy.
You're taking
heat out, okay?
So that's the key
thing. Now I'm
going to give
you math, right?
But just remember
this is where
we're at. All right.
Do do do do.
Okay. All right,
so our substance
here, right?
So the substance
we're working with
in this case,
we have air here.
The mass flow
rate that we're
told in this problem is
what I'm telling you
is in the problem,
the MDOT here is
equal to 0.15
kilograms/second.
We have our initial state.
So if we talk about
state one, All right.
State one, we
have a P one,
which is 100 PA.
We have a T one,
which is then
equal to 27
degrees Celsius.
And what it means is
that if we use Pi CLR,
I'd be able to
know enthalpy
one and entropy one
from this, right?
So I have complete
information by
having this there.
We're going to assume.
So let's make
some assumptions.
So some assumptions
we're going to make.
Assumptions. All right.
We're going to assume
that this is right,
so this is a steady flow.
Device, the compressors
are reversible
plus adiabatic,
which means
Isotropic, okay?
Right? So this implies
that they're isentropic.
Neglect, right?
We neglect Delta KE,
you know, and Delta PE.
Cool. For State two,
so if we analyze into
State two for this, we,
um We are told
that the pressure
at state two,
let me see how
I'm looking here.
This is better.
The pressure at
state two is equal to
some ratio times the
pressure at state one.
And this ratio R here,
we're told is 2.5, okay?
Later on, this is not
going to be uncommon.
We're going to,
like, a lot of
the problems are
not going to tell
you what pressure two is.
They're going to say
things like ratio,
compression ratio,
and later here.
So here we just
have a ratio of
R of 2.5, right?
Um Because these
operate isotropically,
what we can say is that
S two specific entropy
S two is equal
to S one, right?
And from this,
then we know H
two and we know
and we know S two.
All right. And State
three, State three.
What do we know
about State three?
State three, we know let
me back up a second
here really quick.
So we know H two,
we know S two, and,
of course, from
this, we know P two.
All right. All right.
Um,
Right?
This is a heat exchanger.
So what you're
doing here is
basically a
heat exchanger.
And in this class, when we
deal with heat
exchanger devices,
we assume we don't have
pressure drops
across them.
So what it means
is that P three
is equal to P two,
and we know T
three, right?
T three is given us
27 degrees Celsius.
So it means now we
know enthal P three,
and we know entra
P three there.
For state four, Okay,
we're told that P
four is equal to
that same ratio
times P three.
So we know that.
And because
this is a reversible
and adiabatic,
we're going to say that S
four is equal to
little S three,
and it means that
we'll know H three.
And if we wanted, we could
compute or I'm sorry,
H four and T four,
let's say, if we wanted
to know that, right?
But we have complete
information
then it's state four.
Mm hmm, hmm. Okay.
So we've oriented
ourselves.
Now what we can get into
is is the analysis.
So again, here we
have let's draw this.
So I have here, right?
I have an inlet.
I have here,
let's say this is
the heat exchanger like
this into a second
stage of compression.
Okay. Here. And then
this is out, right?
I have aw.in for that.
This is our state one,
our state two, our state
three, and our state four.
You can draw some
control volumes, right?
I would say this is
the control volume
of compressor one.
We can do a control volume
of the heat exchanger,
and then we can do
a control volume
of the second
compressor. All right.
So let's call this
maybe CV one,
CV two and CV three
there, all right?
Okay, so let's say the
w.in then of
control volume
one is equal
to, all right?
That's the M dot, right?
This is basically M dot
times the enthalpy at
state two minus the
enthalpy at state
one, all right?
I'm not going to
go through and,
like, simplify, right.
You know,
this is what I know
from the problem.
We have a Q dot.
Out that's happening 2-3.
So then we have a Q dot
out for control
volume two,
and that's again
equal to the M dot.
And here, right, H
two is going to have
a higher enthalpy
than H three,
so this is going to
be H two minus H
three for the out term.
And then for the w.in,
so w.in for control
volume, let's say three.
This is going to be
dot times H three,
because it's a
higher enthalpy
minus H, nope,
that's wrong.
H4h4 minus H three there.
All right. And
so the total,
then the total work then.
So the question that
we were asked is,
assuming the compression
process to be isotropic,
determine the power input
to the compressor for
the mass flow rate
that we gave.
And then we'll do the
same analysis then
for the case when we don't
when we have just
basically a
single compressor
going from state one
to state four, right?
So for this one, though,
w.in, is going to
be equal to w.in for
control volume one.
+w.in for control
volume three, okay?
And the value that I have,
so again, how do we
compute this, right?
We determine H one, H two,
H three and H four.
The M dot was given as
0.15 kilograms/second.
So if you substitute
in those values,
I have aw.in kilowatts of
27.1 of W dot N, right?
Okay. Now, we can
analyze this as a as
a single stage two.
So if we do a single
stage, right?
So what we're doing
here is, let's see.
This is my
compressor here,
here's my inlet,
here's my outlet.
W.in. He's state one.
And we can call
this one as,
like, two prime, okay?
T prime. All right.
Do to do. We know
state one, right?
So state one was
again given to us.
So we know this already.
So state one,
and from this we know H
one and we know S one.
That doesn't change
in the system.
For state two prime,
state let's say
two prime here.
What's the
pressure relative
to what we had in
the first problem.
Say it again.
That's right.
Exactly. So
it's out there.
It's on this.
So we can write the 625 PA
or if I want to
make it relative
to what I had for
the other one,
that would be at at
state four, right?
From state four of what we
had before, but yes, here,
625 PA. All right.
And what else do we assume
here? You're on a roll.
S two prime. You're
a numerical guy.
I like that. Yeah, sure.
That's the right
one, or we would
say it's one here, right?
So it's one on this.
And from here, then
you would know
your enthalpy two
prime, right?
And then if you
go in, then w.in
for this system is
going to be equal to
the same dot that
we had before,
and it's going
to be then H two
prime minus H one.
And if you substitute
numbers in there,
I get 331.1 kilowatts
for a single stage
without intercooling,
okay?
This is a bigger number
than this, okay?
It's easy to
cool something.
Sometimes cooling is
for free, all right?
And so this may make sense
then in a system
to go into
a single stage
of compression,
cool the cast off, send
it back into
another compressor.
And what you'll see
is the work
required there is
less than the case
of a single stage.
Even if this is isotropic
as a single stage,
it's still more work to do
the single stage
compression here than to do
this, cool this, okay?
Does that make
sense? Are there
questions about this
analysis? Yes, please.
What's the
difference between P
two and P two prime.
So P two prime here.
So P two is like in
this problem, right?
This is like halfway to
the final pressure of the
625 we want to
get to, right?
So P two here is like
an intermediate
pressure on
the way to P four
in this system.
P two primed here
is like I do this
in one shot, right?
I start off at
atmospheric pressure,
and I compress all the way
to P two prime here.
And where we want
to go is 625 PA.
So here, it's
like I go from
here to here in one go.
And so the P two
prime relative to
the first problem is it's
equal to P four, okay?
Other questions?
Yes. Louder.
Sounds like a good
homework problem.
So if we reverse it,
if we reverse it,
actually, it sounds like
a good quiz problem.
If we reverse it, will
it be better, okay?
So I think your
problem statement
is if I were
to so I go
with something that's
at very high pressure.
So let's say to
keep it analogous.
So I go with high
pressure through
a turbine, okay?
All right.
And then I come back down,
and I do the same
thing with my turbine.
Here's my W dot
out from it.
And you have this
heat exchanger.
You have a heat
exchanger, which is here.
So four, three,
two, one. Okay?
If you were trying to
get so I guess
the question is,
what's the goal?
So what is the goal of
a process like this?
What is this?
It's a turbine. What
does a turbine do?
Workout. It's useful.
You know, it creates work.
What do you think is
going to happen if I put
a heat exchanger and I
cool off the gas 3-2 here?
What do you think is
going to happen to
the performance of
this second turbine?
So let's think simpler.
And let's open
up to the crowd.
What is the formula that I
just showed you a couple
of slides before for work?
Work is equal to the
integral of what here?
Okay, one at one.
Or one all at once.
Like go bears.
Yes, please. No.
VDP PDV is expansion
work, right?
This is a constant
volume, right?
This is constant volume.
Okay. So to get work
out of something
that's constant volume,
it's VDP for steady
flow, right?
So you have V
DP there, okay?
So this is the thing
I want to have
in your mind.
So now I go from
state three,
and I cool it down
to state two.
What is going to happen
to the workout of
that turbine if I
cool down from State
three to State two?
Phone a friend.
Please. It's
going to go down.
Why? But I don't
have temperature
in this formula.
I liked it. I liked
where you were going.
Anyone want to pick up
the baton in front of you?
No, no, pause. Sorry.
You're decreasing
pressure.
So if you basically
take heat out here,
if I do a Q out here,
then the P two is going
to go down, okay?
Which means like pinwheel,
right, it's less pressure.
You're going to have
less pressure to
push on that device,
and you're going to get
less workout, okay?
So if you ran
that in reverse,
you'd get fired, okay?
However, let's think
the other way.
What would you
actually do?
So if I gave you
that system there,
what is an intelligent
thing you could do?
A turbine. Say it again.
You can use it to
stop a turbine.
Stop a turbine.
You could do.
Sure. You're also
out of a job.
Add heat. That's it.
So basically, you
can add heat.
You can do a Q in here,
and that's done
later, right?
So we'll call this reheat.
So sometimes this will
be called reheat.
Or let's think about this.
Maybe you decide
you want to take
the exhaust gases out
of this and
something like that.
That's called
regeneration.
And we're going to get
into this later, okay?
So you're going
to do things to
extract, okay? All right.
So it was a good idea.
Like all things, you know,
we started off a
little bit kind
of as a nice question,
but there is something
to it. Yes, please?
Okay. So how would
the two stage with
the heat extender in
the middle of it
be different than
a single stage where
it loses heat
during the process?
So, you want to
do the cooling.
Basically, you
want to cool
the compressor while you
do it. It's possible.
The point of that is
that then I can't come
up to the whiteboard
here and do it
in a very elegant way
like I've done, right?
So I take it and
I break it down.
I can do one
stop isotropic,
right, where I don't deal
with the heat additions,
and I can do
it reversibly,
and then the next
one where I'm taking
heat out while it happens.
We have cycles that are
coming where we're
going to do that,
but it's not today, okay?
But it is a fair
question, all right?
Yes, please.
Temperature So
this is I believe you guys
are saying the
same thing, right?
So he's basically saying,
I will take the heat
out of it to keep it
cool while I'm operating,
is what I got.
Or did I misunderstand?
I'm looking at the graph
instead of just
going straight up.
Is that would you
say that that's
a similar thought to
what you had or no?
So what he's basically
saying is while
I'm doing this,
I'm also cooling.
So while I'm putting
the work in,
I'm basically
taking the heat
out while it
happens, okay?
All right. But as you can
imagine in this
analysis, right?
Like, I want to be
able to say that
this thing operates
reversibly,
okay? So at optimum.
To be able to use my
entropy being constant,
I have to treat that
adiabatically, right?
So it needs to be
an adiabatic process
to get to get to that.
I Right.
And then we go down.
I think what
you're saying is
essentially to keep it
flat in this analysis,
it would be like
an infinite series
of compressors
in a row with,
like, little bits
a little bits
of heat taken out, okay?
And we're going
to do this.
We're basically
going to get into
cycles and
analysis like that
later that build on
these two thoughts.
These are two very
nice thoughts,
actually we have, okay?
All right. Other
questions?
Other nice
thoughts. This side
of the room is
crushing it.
You guys, you just
saving for later.
Okay, that's good.
All right. All right.
So if there's not, then
what I'm going to do,
I'll is that
recording on that?
Let me erase and then we
can dive into some
entropy analysis.
All right. Okay,
entropy balance.
Like, why would
we do this?
So, the reason why
we're going to get into
this is because sometimes
entropy is easier,
all right?
And okay.
So we end the
first law, right?
The first law
basically says, like,
heat and work are
the same, right?
They're equivalent.
Delta U
is Q minus W, right?
The second law tells
you that they are
not, all right?
There's all
kinds of energy.
It's very weird.
We don't fully
understand it.
Um, But
entropy is something
we do understand,
one, and two, we can use
it to kind of make
these things
equivalent, right?
When we're dealing with
work in heat interactions,
we're going to be
able to draw the same
control volumes
that we did
before and only deal
with entropy there, right?
It's a property.
That's a nice thing.
So we can talk about
the fluid streams.
We've got a nice
formula for heat,
and we say that for work
transfer processes
that are reversible,
there is no change
in entropy, right?
So from the beginning,
it seems like
we're on a more
firm firm basis, right?
Yeah, so it's It
doesn't exist in
various forms.
It's equally confusing
to all, right?
It's a nice thing, right?
And the way we're going
to do the balance,
the only
difference between
this and what
we had before,
we'll start off
the same, right?
So we're going to have
a change in the entropy
of some control
volume that we draw.
That's equal to the
amount we bring in, okay,
total entropy
entering minus
the total that leaves.
And then we have
one other term
which is generated, right?
What's an example of
entropy generation?
Kai? Something that
generates heat.
Could be. Friction, right?
So you can have
something that's
happened and
it's friction,
maybe, you know,
the compressor
and stuff before.
That's exactly it, right?
So it is something that
can be generated, right?
So that's really the
only additional thing
conceptually to
this balance
compared to what we had
from the energy before,
is that it can be
generated within
the control volume.
Alright? And you remember
before when I said, Okay,
whether or not to
know if something's
a work transfer process
or a heat
transfer process,
what did I say to you
before was like the rule?
How did you know the
difference? Temperature.
If there was a difference
in temperature,
right,
it was heat transfer,
and if there wasn't,
then it was work transfer.
Here, we'll give
you another one.
If you have an
energy interaction
accompanied by
entropy transfer,
that's going to
be heat transfer.
If you have an
energy interaction
that's not accompanied
by entropy transfer,
it's work, right?
So again, think about
that work interaction
before, the
turbine, Iropic?
I do this, and I have
no change in entropy.
Work, okay? I
do this thing,
and I have that
massive line.
Remember that line
before, which was here,
right? So then I
have this one.
Heat.
Heat work.
Okay. Bless you.
All right.
Cool.
Um, yeah, so the
mechanisms, again,
if we come back to
that smaller
control volume
where I'm not
bringing any mass in,
you're going to
be transferring
in entropy here
with heat, right?
So I have some Q, right?
You know, if it's a
constant temperature,
so if I'm transferring
into or out of
a reservoir,
thermal reservoir,
you know,
you're going to be
able to write that.
If it's not, then you
need to be able to relate
changes in heat to
temperature, right?
We did that before
with things
like with sensible
heating, right?
What was, like,
one formula we had
for relating
heat heat transfer
to temperature?
MCP Delta T, right?
So we basically had
something like
that, you know,
for the solids and
for the liquids,
that's a common way
to deal with that.
As we also saw from
before when we
did it in class,
I think some people had
just taken a guess
and said, Okay,
what if I just do
the heat divided by
the temperature and it
turned off that was off.
It was only off by like
10% for the purposes
of that, you know,
analysis, okay?
So this is the
way that entropy
can be transferred
into a closed system.
If it's an open
system, right,
in addition to
that mechanism,
a fluid, right?
So I can have a fluid and
the fluid can carry
entropy in, right?
So again, in the original
energy analysis,
right, I could bring
energy in by work.
I could bring it by heat,
and I could bring it
in by mass, all right?
In entropy, I cannot
bring it in by work, okay?
I'm bringing
it in by heat,
and I am bringing it in by
mass that can
be brought in.
Okay. And because it's
a property, it's
convenient, right?
I can just say
I have this M
dot fluid stream in.
I know the state of it,
I know the entropy.
So I have, you know,
M dot as in, okay?
Cool. Yes, so then
you do some
balances, right?
So here's an example,
then, right?
We have a single
stream in,
single stream
out. All right.
So you want to look
at, let's say,
the change in the entropy,
that control volume.
I can do the heat in.
I have the
entropy by mass,
and of course, I can
also have
generation, okay?
Um what's a way
that I can have generation
inside of this?
We'll do this with
a heat exchanger.
But anything that happens,
right, like, let's say,
irreversibly inside of
that container could
be generation.
We said friction,
heat transfer.
It could also be
mixing, right?
So if you think about
mixing as a
process, right,
you can have
changes in entropy
from from mixing.
Okay?
Yeah. So if you get
into the steady state,
so this is non ate form,
again, just like we did
before in ate form.
A lot of times in
these analysis here,
we'll do it, you
know, for a second.
But, so the rate of change
of um And so we'll
see the rate
of change of entropy
in my control
volume dt is equal
to.in minus dot out plus
dot gen, all right?
If we assume it's
a steady process, this
is going to go away.
And so what you'll have
is that dot gen is
equal to dot out minus.in.
And this is going to be
a very common formula
for us, right,
that we're going
to use to then
understand this
generation, all right?
Alright, I got 7 minutes.
I think I can do it.
Alright. I'll leave
that one there.
So in this problem,
we're looking
at a heat exchanger.
Heat exchangers are
very important.
And this is I think
it's mimicking a
shower, if I remember.
Singles are some
funny examples.
So here we're bringing
in cold water
into this heat
exchanger at
this temperature
and conditions,
and it's exiting.
Now we're bringing
hot water
in from this side,
and it's exiting here.
We know, right,
the Delta Ts here.
So, um, Presumably
because we know,
let's say,
the phase of this
water that's here,
probably we could if
we assumed a
pressure of this,
let's say, like
1 atmosphere,
I'd be able to
know the enthalpy
in and the enthalpy out.
Or, and this is
what we'll also do.
We can rely on the
fact that changes in
enthalpy for sensible
heating DH is CPET.
We can also try
this on for size.
And in this
example, you get to
compare values
you get from
the property
tables or from
Picor against what
you could have from,
um, from from
this analysis.
Alright, and the take home
message out of this
is because I know
the inlet and I
know the outlet of
this in those states and
end of the mass florid,
I'm going to know the
heat leaving, okay?
The key insight
is the heat
leaving or the heat
entering into
the cold stream.
For this heat exchanger,
a lot of times
the heat exchangs
they're very insulated,
so there's no
heat transfer in
or out of them
on the outside.
But internally,
the heat that
goes into the
cold water must
come from the
hot water, okay?
And so from that,
you're going to be
able to determine,
then the rest of
the information basically
the exit state here
because you know
the mass flow
rate of that, okay?
Let's do it. Alright.
So I am not going to well,
I guess what I'll
redraw is I'll redraw
the control volumes there.
And so we can answer
the first question.
So the first question is
the rate of heat transfer.
This is pretty trivial.
So what we'll do there
is we'll just
take the water.
So I have this
water stream here,
which is going in and out.
Okay? I'm going to
draw my control
volume around that.
So I'll draw that
control volume around
the cold water streams
of the blue one up there.
I'm going to call
this is State one,
and I'm going to call this
is state two, okay?
I have the MDOT.
Let's call it
MDOT cold here,
which is also, known.
And for this
control volume,
all we can say is that
there's going to
be maybe like
aq.in that is
happening, okay?
So it's a steady flow,
no work interaction.
And so this q.in is
going to be equal to
the dot code times
the enthalpy at state two
minus the enthalpy at
state one, all right?
And we can
approximate this
as saying because it
doesn't change phase,
we can say dot code is
CP two minus
one, all right?
If we do it this way
or let's say this.
If I do it this way to
the MDOT cold is what
0.95 kilograms/second.
What's the specific
heat of water?
4.18 kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin, right?
And our Delta T is what?
It's 80 70, 70 degrees
C minus ten degrees
C. All right. And
you'll get a number.
The number that I
have for this is 238.
238.3 kilowatts, okay.
If on the other hand,
you want to give
it a go with something
like Pi killer,
you know, this
is, you know,
water that's coming
in from the house.
You could take a
guess and say, Okay,
maybe this P one here
is maybe like 100 kPa,
you know, something
like an atmosphere.
It's a heat exchanger,
so P two is
equal to P one.
And from that, you could
do a substitution.
You could figure out what
those enthalpies are
from that state.
And the number
that you'll get
is 238.5 kilowatts, okay?
So single phase water
and bringing heat
in dot Cp delta
T. Cp Delta T,
not too shabby, not
too shabby, and
very fast, okay?
Someone even knew that
off the top of their head.
They knew the C, they
knew the Delta T,
and you got a value
that's good for almost
to the fourth
decimal, all right?
Fourth a significant
figure. All right?
Okay. So that's the
heat transferred in.
So this is Q dot N.
That's wonderful.
All right.
To do this analysis,
though, right?
So to be able to get to
the entropy, though.
So for the cute item,
this is perfectly
acceptable.
But if I want to
determine things
like entropy here,
I will have to
declare the
temperature, right?
So I knew the
temperature was a value.
I knew that I'll
assume a pressure,
and out of this, I'll
get to an S one.
We also got to an
H one this way.
And for the case
here, right,
so the T two was
also a given.
If I have that pressure,
I can also get to an S.
I can also get
to an S two.
All right. All right,
so now we can deal
with the other stream,
which is basically
the hot water.
So here's the hot water.
Okay.
Here's my control volume
for the hot water.
Let's say this is
state three here.
This is state four here.
I've got an M dot hot
that's coming in.
I'm given a temperature
of 85 degrees Celsius,
and I'm given the M dot.
And we know that
there's a Q dot
out from it that's
then heating the
water, right?
So Q dot out
is going to be
equal to M dot hot times
H three minus H four.
Q dot out is
equal to q.in,
which is what
we had before.
So that's the
238238, kilowatts.
The dot hot is a given.
H three, we could get.
So if I say 85
degrees C, again,
let's just hazard
a guess and call
it like 100 kPa.
With that information,
so with P three
known and with
T three known,
I'm going to be
able to know what
I know what H three
is an S three.
So I know H three,
I know the M dot,
I know the Q dot,
and now I know H,
but I know H four, okay?
And the point is for
state four, All right,
so for state four, if I
know H four that's
there, and again,
if I say P four is
equal to P three,
I'm going to be
able to say that I
know what S four is, okay?
And the take home message,
did I get rid of it?
I got rid of it.
The take home message
from this, though,
is that essentially
the dot gen that
I wrote before is
going to be dot cold.
Times S two
minus one plus m
dot hot times S four
minus S three, okay?
With that, I'll
close there.
We'll get more into
this and more practice,
you know, with some time,
but at least as
a starter into
some entropy
analysis, okay?