PROFESSOR: Okay so first
law, let's talk about this
before we dive into
the second law.
So what we found from
the first law was
it was impossible to make a
machine that could make energy
right, that could generate--
that could basically
create energy.
We talked about transformations.
We said we can't have a machine
that just creates energy.
Energy always is.
It just goes through
transformations.
The thing about the
first law, though,
is it doesn't put any
constraints on this energy
transformation from
one end to the other.
So this example that
I give you here, let's
say this experiment
that Joule did, right.
Joule took a paddle, and he
spun this paddle in water.
That paddle hit the water,
caused the water to move.
That water then dissipated
this energy viscously.
It became heat.
And then he was measuring that
with a with a thermometer.
We thought, okay, we
could do that in reverse.
Why don't I just take the heat,
pump it or transfer it into the
into the water, and it should
cause the paddle to spin.
Does that work?
Based on your experience?
Hell no, right.
So that does not work.
And the second law is we
need another law then.
So because the first law doesn't
put any stop sign for that.
Exactly.
So as we know, so as we know
from this fact of this example
here with the paddle
or from the example of,
let's say I have
a resistor, right.
I pass electricity through that.
It makes heat.
If I transfer heat
into that resistor,
I do not get
electricity out of it.
So we know from
experience there are
definite limitations into
the transformation of heat
into work.
And that is what
motivated, right,
the development of the second
laws to explain that and then,
ultimately, use it
for developments.
And so for a long time, people
tried to do this stuff, though.
People tried to make
these machines that could
create energy on their own.
If you were able to do what I
just described before, you'd
be able to take a
machine, literally
extract heat out of the
surroundings, cooling it,
and then directly
creating it into work
because we're on earth here, and
we have heat everywhere, right?
So there's thermal energy
contained in here, in the soil,
and the atmosphere.
You have, like, an
unlimited reservoir of heat.
It is also the challenge
of our entire lives, right,
is the fact that we
have too much of it.
And so what you would end up if
you were to create such a device
is you could design
something that
would do what's called
perpetual motion
or perpetuum mobile, all right.
So it's a perpetual
motion machine.
And people like devoted a
lot of their times and lives,
like, the alchemists trying
to make gold from what lead
or whatever it was.
They were the equivalent
of the alchemists
in thermodynamics who were
working on perpetual motion.
And the second law firmly
rules these out, okay.
So if you're an engineer
and you come across
and someone sends you some
email, it gives you a phone call
and says I got this great
thing, you only pay,
10 kilojoules of energy
of this and you're
going to get like
20 kilojoules out,
you're going to,
first of all say,
hey, that's like a violation
of the first law, okay.
And the second thing
is you're going
to say it definitely also
violates the second law
there as well.
So you use this to sniff out
interphrase bullshit, right?
You're going to use this as
your BS meter there, right.
All right.
And this was the cover of
Popular Magazine in apparently
in the 1920s there.
So like I said, a lot of
people worked for a long time.
They tried to do it.
They don't work.
But if you do make
one and they do work,
you will get filthy rich.
But again, I don't
necessarily advise
investing your life in that.
Another key concept when we're
talking about the second law
and understanding
it and what it means
is to talk about what's called
the thermal energy reservoir.
In a nutshell, it's
something that's
big, okay, with respect to the
thing that's transferring heat
to and from it.
Examples sort of
in everyday life
would be something
like an ocean.
So if you do atmospheric
modeling or simulations,
let's say you're
transferring heat
maybe over the course
of a day, maybe
from that into the into the
ocean or maybe it's you,
you're by there and transferring
some heat to and from it,
the temperature of the
body doesn't really
change because you are--
well, whatever.
The thing transferring
is probably
very small with
respect to the ocean
because that's a
very big entity.
And that's the point.
You transfer energy
to or from it,
but the temperature of the
reservoir doesn't change.
We'll get to why we need
that in a in a second.
Okay, so as I said, a lot of--
well, the first lot
and the second law,
a lot of these things,
we did experiments.
We observed what
happens, and we try
to come up with
rules that are trying
to rationalize what we observe.
In thermal. we call
those postulates.
You postulate this.
So the first law was a postulate
on the conservation of energy,
and that is like
pretty straightforward.
That's like accounting.
The second law is not exactly
as straightforward as that.
So I'm going to give you two
statements about the second law.
I'll read them.
I'll read them kind of slowly.
So the first one is from
Lord Kelvin, so again,
a very famous, famous physicist.
So a transformation
whose only final result
is to transform into work--
dramatic effect-- heat
extracted from a source,
which is at the same temperature
throughout is impossible.
All right, you're going to
read that, and you'll say,
what the heck does that mean?
We're going to do an example
in a second to make it firm.
But the thing is that
the key words here--
first key word I want
to point out here
is only final result. So
the only final result of,
let's say, this
transformation is
you're taking this heat from
some source, so a single source
temperature uniform throughout
at the same temperature,
and you're going to convert
this directly into--
directly into heat.
So keep this in mind.
This also doesn't come from me.
I have to like think
about this a lot.
Like I think about this so much
that sometimes I dream about it,
and then it freaks my wife
out, all right, and yeah,
because it's deep stuff.
And the evidence to
support this statement
is people have tried to do this.
So as I said before,
with this example
of the of Joule's machine
of the heat into--
directly into, let's
say, the paddle
and trying to get
work directly out.
It doesn't work.
There's a lot of other-- if
you can go on to Wikipedia,
it's amazing how many devices
that they've tried to construct.
And when a device, let's
say, satisfies the first law,
as I said, energy
conservation but does not
satisfy this statement,
we call that a perpetuum
mobile of the second kind.
So second means the second law.
If something wasn't-- was a
machine that violated the first
law, we'd would call it
perpetuum mobile of the first
kind.
I'll give you a second
statement on the second law.
So the second statement
is a transformation
whose only final result is
to transfer heat from a body
at a given temperature
to a body at a higher
temperature is impossible.
This you already did.
Who was here for
that experiment?
We did molecular dynamics
simulations in class,
and we looked at the direction
that heat transferred.
You may have been here.
Maybe you don't remember it.
I've given you a
lot of information.
But you did look at it.
You had a reservoir
at one temperature.
You had another one at another.
You released the
barrier, and you
looked at how the
mean temperature
spatially was varying.
This is something that's
more intuitive to me.
So this statement
on the second law
is like things at high
temperature tend to spread,
right?
So I have a hot pan at home
that's really hot, okay.
I take it off the stove, and
I set it on an insulating mat
there.
And what will
happen is over time,
that thermal energy
will dissipate
to the environment, conduction,
convection, radiation, right.
It's going to go away.
So that's an example of
things tend to spread.
If you take a balloon, right--
I take a balloon, high
pressure, right, of gas in it.
I pop it.
That's enjoyable.
But what you have
there is that the gas
tends to expand, so
another example of it.
A third one, I mean, examples
are given here like perfume,
right?
So you put something here.
You spray a bit of it.
It tends to diffuse.
Food dye in water,
it tends to diffuse.
So this is something
where you probably
have preexisting
knowledge, right, of this.
And this is a postulate
from Rudolf Clausius.
So Rudolf Clausius was the first
chair of physics at ETH Zurich.
So that's where I was before.
My building that I was on
was called Clausius Strasse,
which means Clausius Street.
And yeah, he was there,
basically, in the 1850s,
and he took the work of Sadi
Carnot and put it like on a firm
basis.
So he took the work of Sadi,
which was already very good
but was using what was called
Caloric Theory of heat,
and Clausius put it on a
more, basically, firm basis.
There he has a very
interesting history.
And if you want to learn more
about it, you can read it there.
Okay, so you have some
preexisting experience
on this statement.
I've given you this
other statement there.
And here's what I'd like
to do now, all right.
So to, kind of,
make this concrete,
especially the first statement,
which is a bit less intuitive,
so I'm giving you this.
I'm giving you
Kelvin's statement.
I'm putting this term in bold
here, and this is the scenario.
So the scenario is you have
a thermal energy reservoir.
So remember, big thing at
some temperature, temperature
won't change if I transfer heat.
So I take that.
I transfer some heat into--
excuse me-- this piston.
So this piston here can expand
so that the piston rod can move.
So the substance that's
in there is an ideal gas.
The ideal gas is
expanding because of this.
And we assume that the
gas is then isothermal.
Why?
Because you have it in contact
with the energy reservoir,
all right.
So that's the prompt.
Just give me a second.
All right, and so
the first question
that you're going
to ask is that--
I want you to answer with this.
You can open it
up on your phones.
But the first question is, does
the internal energy of the gas
change during this process?
So if I take this thing, it's
at a constant temperature,
and I transfer heat.
Does the internal energy change
for this isothermal process?
The second one is using
the first law applied
to this control
volume, is the work
performed by the expanding
gas equal to the heat that it
absorbs?
So is the boundary
work, the PDV work
that happens here equal to
the heat that's transferred.
And then what I want
you to do with those two
pieces of information, which
hopefully are straightforward,
is answer is this
a contradiction
of the Kelvin postulate,
which is here, okay?