Alright, I got 210. I'm
going to get started.
So today, we're continuing
with our second law.
So we're going to cover
some aspects and
refrigeration,
some power plants, and
then get into more
into the Karno
Karno cycle,
which we started
last time, okay?
Yeah, so, This is
how the arnocycle
looks like.
Recall, we have
heat transferred in
a system from high
temperature isothermally.
At the same time, we
have a work transfer
out process.
Then you have an adiabatic
expansion process
which drops our temperature
from high to low.
We have heat
transferred out
of the system to a low
temperature reservoir,
TL And then at
the same time,
we're compressing,
and then we have
adiabatic compression,
which takes us from
the low temperature
to the high
temperature, right?
But the key attribute
of this is that one,
that we operate
between these
two temperatures
and that all of
the work transfer
processes
are reversible,
reversible, okay?
And that's going
to be the basis
of next week when we
introduce our next
character entropy,
all right? You
can reverse it.
So I mentioned this
also at the end
of the last time
is that if you run
it in reverse, okay,
So the thermal
engines go clockwise,
the heat pumps go
counterclockwise.
What you're going
to do then is
you're just going
to pump heat from
the low temperature
reservoir and put it
into the high
temperature, right?
So on an application
on a cold winter day,
right, that would be
your house, okay?
Or on a hot day, right?
That's the inside of
your fridge, okay?
But also, remember,
an attribute of
the cycle is that the
network that we
transfer out,
so W net out is equal
to the net heat
we transfer in.
And the reason for that is
that we end up where
we start, right?
And if we end up
where we start,
that's a property, okay?
It's a property.
So it means that,
from the first law, right?
So if my property is
my internal
energy throughout
that whole thing,
from the first law,
we know that the if
the change in the
internal energy
at this point
is then zero,
right, the heat
that we put
in must be equal to
the work that we
take out, right?
Because the first
law is Delta U
is basically a Q
minus W, okay?
Good, super.
Alright, let's talk
about power plants.
All right.
So what is a
typical thermoelectric
power plant look like?
This is still, like I
said, a majority of
most energy electricity is
produced in this way.
So what you have here to
start with between
States one,
let's say States one
and State's two is you
have a pump, okay?
And with this pump, you're
putting some work
transferred in.
Allright? This then enters
into what's called
a boiler, okay?
So you have a boiler here.
All right. All right.
This is your cue,
basically your q.in,
which is which is here
out of this boiler.
Okay. This thing goes
into into a turbine.
Okay. So this basically is
your turbine in, okay?
And from here,
right, we have
basically our W dot out.
And then out of
the end of this
turbine, okay,
this thing goes into
another heat exchanger,
which we term as a
condenser, okay?
And then here's where
you have your Q
dot out.
And this whole thing,
right, starts again.
So I have states one,
which is here,
State two here,
State three here,
and then State four,
which is here. Any
clarifications?
Cool.
Oh, it gets better,
man. Don't worry.
Alright. So this is
what we're talking
about here.
And so in this problem, so
this is a problem
from six.
I believe I have 617.
The question is, you know,
we'd like to
determine determine
what's called
the efficiency
the thermal efficiency
of its efficiency.
So eta, is the
Greek letter Ea.
I put H to indicate that
it's a thermal engine,
and I'd like to know
the net power
output, okay?
So mathematically, right,
that's basically
w.net out, okay,
which is by definition,
equal to W dot
out minus w.in.
All right? We're given
some information.
So the information
that we're
given here is that
for our q.in,
we're told that it's
transferred in
at a rate of
280 gigajoules per hour.
Mm hmm. We're told
that we have a
Q dot out here,
which is equal to 165.
Gigajoules per hour.
We're also told that
there's some losses.
So for example, you know,
as I'm transferring,
you know,
let's say, hot steam
into the turbine,
I could have thermal
losses that happen here,
and that's to the tune of
eight gigajoules per
hour of losses, okay?
This we don't know.
We don't know how
much work is in.
So what do we do?
Assume steady. Sure.
We can do that.
So we have a steady
do we assume, right?
So we assume, right,
that we're
operating under,
let's say, a steady
state condition.
So, this whole
thing is going.
So each of the devices are
steady flow
devices, right?
So, write a pump,
a heat exchanger,
a turbine, another
heat exchanger
in a in a loop, okay?
More specifically, what do
you do if you want to
determine let's start
with this one, right?
Because this is
essentially a bit easier.
What piece of information
that I give you about
cycles and network
with respect to heat?
Okay. All right, so
we have here, right,
our q.net in, right,
is equal to our
w.net out, right?
And that's a feature
of a cycle, okay?
That's a feature
of a cycle, right?
If you want to know what
this basically
looked like,
try to draw this
from memory.
But this type of cycle
here looks something
like this.
Okay, like that,
and the point
is, it's a cycle.
And so then the area
contained within
that curve is
the net workout,
and it must be
from the first law
equal to the net heat in.
How can we define
the net heat
in based on this?
What would you do?
Okay, so we've drawn
control volumes for each
individual elements,
right?
You can also draw
control volume for
the entire power
plant, right?
So if I draw a
control volume
for the entire basically,
maybe I'll draw
like, you know,
a box around it,
so I have this.
So my flows are, right?
I have a Q dot.
In, right? I'll
have a Q dot out,
which I know,
and then I have
a Q dot loss, okay?
Basically, let's
say, like a Q dot,
you know, loss, which
is also there, okay?
So then from this, right,
what we can say
is that our
q.net in is equal to
what comes in, right,
q.in minus the
sum of Q dot
out plus Q dot loss, okay?
Our q.in is what?
It's 280 gigajoules
per hour.
Q dot out is 165
gigajoules per hour,
and the Q dot loss is
eight gigajoules
per hour. Mmm.
So if I do that,
I have 107.
I have 107 gigajoules
per hour is then
my is my q.net.
I, okay, which by
definition here is also
equal to my
w.net out, okay?
So that C.
And now we can talk
about efficiencies,
okay? So
efficiencies here.
So to the first
part, so for,
um, For the efficiencies,
and in general,
when you're thinking about
defining figures of merit,
you take the ratio of
the thing you desire,
and you divide it by
the thing that
you pay, okay?
So, like, you know,
you know, okay.
That's all I'm going
to say. So, all right,
so basically the
definition of this,
so the thing
that we want is
the net power
output, right?
So this basically is
defined as W net,
um, divided by Q in.
I I wrote it in rate
notation, right?
If this is a steady
system and it's closed,
right,
the M dots that
would be in here
would go away.
It could also just
be little W net and
little Q in. All right?
You'll sometimes see
this written as,
um, All right, no, this
is basically fine.
You can also write
this because w.net is
equal to q.net, right?
I could also write q dot.
This is net out q.net
in divided by q.in, right?
That's another way that
you can do that, right?
And so if we substitute
in our numbers, so
what do I have?
I have 107, right?
So I have here 107
gigajoules per hour.
And then what's my q.in?
My Q dot N is
280 80 gigajoules per
hour. What is it?
Like, yeah, 38.
It's basically
38% efficiency.
38 me write that
better, right?
38%, okay?
And this is where we're
going now, right?
So everything we did
in part five, right,
was to talk about
these individual
elements, right,
with the heat
exchangers, turbines,
compressors, and
all of that.
And to make power cycles
and heat pumps
and all of that,
we string all
of these things
into series. We
close the loop.
We call it a cycle,
and we're interested
in things like that,
the work in,
the networking,
the net heat
out, like that.
This is a very easy
problem, right?
problem because all I did
at the end of it is I kind
of lumped all those
elements together,
and then I just said,
Look, I know my q.in,
I know my Q dot out,
I know my Q dot loss.
But actually, a lot of
what we're going
to be doing
is determining these
properties at state two,
three, four,
and one. Okay?
So the enthalpies,
multiply those by dots,
and then you get
things like q.in,
W dot out, and so
on and so forth.
Okay? All right.
And the reason why
I can't give that
to you next is to do this,
I need to give you,
again, this other property
to be able to
analyze, okay?
Clear? Great. Grace, do,
do, do. All right.
Maybe a good
segue, though,
before we dive into some
refrigeration is to
talk for a second about
what is the maximum
efficiency.
So I said before that
the Karnea cycle
sets the absolute
maximum efficiency
that's attainable.
I just told you
that. And what
we can do is we
can actually
define what
that efficiency
would be and what
it depends on.
Alright? So a
little bit of math.
19th century.
Alright. Good it.
This one sucks.
This one better.
Okay, that's better.
All right. Okay, so
we drew with Carne.
Maybe I can just
blank this out.
Okay. All right,
we drew with Karno
last time right?
So I have here one
to two, let's say.
So this is he
transferred out in
compression, two to three.
I have some adiabatic
compression,
three to four
isothermal expansion,
and then four to one
adiabatic expansion,
right?
So these are work
transferred in processes,
and these are work
transferred out.
Along this line, this is
an isotherm where
T is equal to TH,
and along this isotherm,
we have T equals to TC.
So I'm going to call
it for um, cold, okay?
So TH is my hot,
and then TC is my cold.
The book, a lot
of times I'll
write this also
sometimes as TL.
So L for low or
C, um, for cold.
We only have one
word for hot,
so we have H, all right?
So that's our cycle, okay?
Um, T, do, do,
do, do, do, do.
All right.
And in this cycle, okay,
when we transfer, right,
so the heat that's
transferred
here is in from right,
so we have Q
we have, like,
a a Q in here
at TH, right?
And we have basically
a Q out here,
which is then
transferred then into
the cold right into the
cold, side, all right?
So let's focus for a
second on and again,
while we transfer
this heat in,
right, we have the work
transfer process out.
While we transfer
the heat out,
we have the work
transfer in.
And these two things
are equal, right?
Remember,
we did that example
with the piston.
I put that amount
of heat in.
And, of course,
because it's
isothermal, right,
the same amount of work
had to be transferred
out, right?
So let's make some
assumptions about this.
We're going to deal
with an ideal gas.
We don't need to, but we
will because it's
instructive.
We'll deal with
an ideal gas.
And let's say that
we're working
the work transfer
work transfer
is only a boundary
work, okay?
And boundary work is what?
PdV. All right?
You're going
to ace the quiz.
All right.
PdV. Okay? All right,
PdV PDV work there,
which is our boundary,
our boundary
work. All right.
So let's focus
on one, two.
So and I can write
W. You know,
one, two is equal to.
You can also write this
as like a little M.
W one, two, where this has
units of joules
per kilogram,
so I can have
it like that.
And then this is equal to
my M times the
integral from
state one to two of PD V,
where V is then
little V, um, right?
If we're dealing with
an ideal gas, right?
So we have PV.
P little V is equal to Rt.
So this is the
specific gas constant.
This would depend
on your substance
in the end of the washout.
But for now, we
can write this
as just, you know,
some ideal gas that has a
constant R. If we
substitute this into here,
right, what we're
going to have is P
is equal to RT
divided by V,
and that's going
to go into here.
So then my, um, And if
I write it just as
little W one, two.
So if I just
focus on this,
this is going to
be equal to then,
the integral
of one to two,
R T divided by
V dV, right?
And this is
going to produce
a natural log, right?
It's basically going to
produce a natural log.
And so what I'm
going to have
is why is it a
natural log?
Because R is a
constant and T is
a constant because this is
an isothermal process.
So I could take those out,
and I have R T,
natural log of
little V two
divided by little V
one, all right? Cool.
All right. And
the temperature.
The point is that
didn't declare
the temperature.
What is the
temperature that I'm
transfring heat
out here at?
So it's an isothermal
or transfer process.
What's the temperature
of one to two?
TC, right? So
this is TC here.
If this is a
compression process
is V two going to
be greater than or
less than V one?
So what is the sign
of the natural log
here if V two is
less than V one?
It's negative, okay?
So then this W one,
two would be a
negative, okay?
So if I wanted to call
this as, for example,
W, you know,
let's say W in,
let's say one, two, right?
This would be equal
to the negative of
RTC natural log of V
two divided by V one,
okay, just to
be consistent.
So here I didn't
say anything
about in and out.
The fact that
I'm writing in
here now and applying
it to one, two,
I have to put the
negative sign because of
the fact that
that'll be negative.
Okay, that's good. TC.
All right, it's
isothermal.
So isothermal one to two.
So if we look back
to our Delta E of
the control volume
is equal to E
in minus E out, right?
This can then be Delta U
if we neglect Kineticut
potential energies,
right?
This would then be Wn plus
Qn minus W out
plus Q out, okay?
So it's isothermal.
What does that mean about
the internal
energy here for
an ideal gas?
It's constant.
It's unchanged, right?
So because it's
isothermal for
this process of one,
two, this is constant.
Do we have work in?
Yes. Do we have Q in?
Yes? No, right?
Do we have W
out? No, right?
But we do have Q
out. And the point
from this exercise of one,
two is that Q out, right?
One, two is then
equal to W in, right?
One, two, okay? So we
can write this on
a per mass basis.
I can divide
both sides by M,
and I can say little
Q out, right?
One, two is equal to
little W in one,
two, right?
And so what does
it mean for this?
It means that Q out One,
two is equal to
the negative of
RTC natural log of
V two divided
by V one, okay?
And that's an
important first step.
So we wrote our first real
formula with this, okay?
So we can do the
same thing for
the W out, right?
So the W out.
Right here, we can look
at the three to four.
So W out out three,
four, little W,
and it is then equal
to ideal gas constant,
high temperature of the
reservoir and natural log,
little V four
divided by V three.
The sign of this is
correct because the
specific volume
at state four
will be larger,
right, than that
at state three.
So that looks that all
looks fine, right?
We know that W out three,
four must be
equal to Q in at
34 because the other
two legs that we have
analyze are
idiabatic processes,
or you can go through
the same thing that
I just said now,
which is that
it's isothermal,
and you can follow
that whole step
and arrive at that
same conclusion.
All right. So our
thermal efficiency
here is equal to what?
So what do we desire?
Okay, we desire
work. All right.
I'll carry the load
today, all right?
So we carry the
W net and Q in.
And W net is also equal
to Q net, right, right?
Which is basically Q in
minus Q divided by
Q in, all right?
We're getting
close. All right.
We have formulas, right?
So we have a formula
for our cue out.
We have a formula for
our Q in, all right?
And so I guess I can
say it this way.
If we were to do
a sum of all the
cue you know,
these are just two
legs, because one,
four and two, three
are adiabatic,
So let's say like this,
our Q in is equal to
our what we call
this Q in three,
four, because
this, like I said,
two, three, and four,
one are diabatic.
Our Q out is equal to
what we had there,
which was our Q out
one, two, okay?
And so if we substitute
those formulas in,
what we would have
then for our Q and
three Q and 34 is
R T H natural log
of V four divided by
V three minus our Q,
which is where RTC,
RTC, natural log.
I think I have V
natural log of.
So this is the
minus, right?
So let me get this right.
Okay, so this is
minus a minus, right?
So I have negative
R, TC natural log,
of V two divided by V one,
and then again,
divided by the Q,
which is your R TH,
natural log V four
divided by V three, okay?
And so the challenge
right now is we
need to deal we'd like to
have V two and V one to be
like the V four
and the V three.
And so for this,
what we can
recall is that this is,
right, it's four to
one and two to three
are adiabatic
processes, okay?
So if I look at PV
to the gamma equal
to C, right?
This is what we
proved before
for an adiabatic process.
This is adiabatic,
adiabatic,
you know, expansion or
adiabatic compression.
And so what we so
that's one thing.
To be able to do this,
we've got to make sort
of a slight
transformation.
So I can write if
I go PV like this,
is V to the Gamma
minus one is equal
to C, right?
So basically, I pulled
a specific volume
out of this.
Now I have Gamma
to the minus one.
Idel gas equation.
This is nothing
but Rt N times
Gamma minus one
equals to C.
Since R is a constant,
TV Gamma minus one
is equal to C
divided by R,
or we could call this
as like C one, okay?
All right. Um. And now
we'll apply this to these
two legs here, all right?
Uh. All right.
So the first one,
I have T cold V two,
Gamma minus one,
two, right?
So that'll bring me then
to three, State three,
which is TH V three,
Gamma minus one,
and then we can do
the same thing the
other way, right?
I can write TC at
V one Gamma minus
one, which is here.
And then that must be
H and V four, right?
TH and V four,
Gamma minus one.
All right. We're
almost there.
We're almost able to now
relate because now if
I divide these two things,
so if I divide
this, right,
the TCs are gone,
the Hs are gone.
And so what you'll
have then is V
two divided by V
one to the Gamma
minus one is
then equal to V
three divided by V
four to the Gamma
minus one, okay?
And the Gamma minus
ones can go away.
And so what you'll have
then is now what we saw,
which is V two
divided by V
one is V three
divided by V four.
Okay.
So, now with this,
we can come back
to this term here.
So V two divided by V
one is hold on a second.
This is the negative.
Okay, so this is
an important part
that I have to deal
with here before I
do the substitution
Alright,
suppose I can do
the substitution.
So the V two divided
by the V one,
this is equal to V
three divided by V
four, all right?
And that's almost
how we wanted it,
although we'd like V
four divided by V three.
We'll bring this
back to center
stage here and move
this out.
All right.
So I have here a
negative, right?
A negative of a
natural log does what?
Right? I can invert it.
Anything that's here, I
can put to the power.
So then v3v4 to the
negative one is
then V four divided
by V three, okay?
So this goes away, right?
And then this is V
four divided by
V three, R gone.
Natural log of V
four divided by V
three, gone, gone, gone.
TH minus TC divided by
H or how it's more
commonly written is
one minus c divided by H.
So if you want to make
a very efficient device
for producing power,
what do you do?
Name and what do you do?
That's it. That's it.
That's it. Okay?
And this temperature
is Kelvin, right?
This is an absolute scale.
This only works
in Kelvin, right?
If you starting 0
Celsius in there,
then you're going to get
some some weird numbers.
But, yeah, that's
exactly it.
So when you think about
a cycle or you look at it,
you know, they're
essentially,
you know, you want to
be having heat transferred
in from something that's
at high temperature,
all right?
And the lower
the temperature
that you transfer
the heat in from,
the lower the efficiency
will be, okay?
This is a way of
saying, right,
that heat has a quality
to it, all right?
You can rank it. You can
basically say if it
has a value, okay?
So we talk about
low grade heat.
Low grade heat is like,
I don't know,
waste heat out of
a building, right?
It's heat that's
being transferred
from something
that's at a relatively
low temperature,
and we don't use it, okay?
But if you start taking
heat off of things
that are at higher
temperatures, all right?
In a process,
you can start
to make use of
these things, okay?
I think there was a
question in front.
Yeah.
Name. Arturo. So the
negative so this comes
back to here, okay?
And even further,
which is to this,
if I want to
talk about work
in from state one to
state two, all right?
And because it's an in,
I'm declaring the value.
So what I need to
produce here needs to be
a positive value
because I'm
writing in, okay?
For that to
happen, I have to
look and see my
volume at state two.
This is a
compression process.
So V two is going to
be less than V one.
The natural log of that
ratio is negative.
So to make this a positive
quantity and to be
a work in process,
I have to put a
negative sign.
One, two, The work
because this is an
isothermal process
and it's an ideal gas,
because it's isothermal,
the internal
energy doesn't
change. That's
what we said here.
So the work in
there must be equal
to the heat out.
So then you have
the heat out.
And so that's the origin
of the first
negative sign.
And that's what
went into here.
So then the Q in
minus the Q out.
And we just took
that negative
sign, and we flipped,
what would have been the V
three divided
by the V four,
then became V four
divided by V three,
and then all
the canceling,
and then you had
to put that, okay?
The other thing that
I will tell you,
Saadi Kara, he did.
This is beautiful.
You look at all of that
and you think, like,
that's actually
quite a statement.
So there's two things
that are interesting
to this.
The first is
that he did it
with not
understanding heat.
He did this at a time when
he thought heat
was a substance.
Like, it was called
caloric theory,
and later on it
was shown that
it's not, right?
It's basically not had
a lot of weird
ideas back then.
Um, but, you know,
his math and his thinking
was so consistent that
he still produced a result
that actually could stand.
But you don't see
anything about a
substance here.
Of course, in
this derivation,
we did it for
an ideal gas,
but you can get in and
show that this statement,
this doesn't depend on
the substance involved.
The efficiency a thermal
engine only depends.
The maximum efficiency
of a thermal engine only
depends on the difference
between the temperatures
of the heat in and
the heat out, okay?
So if you take no
other formula out of
this class, This
is it, okay?
Seriously. I look back
at my notes from,
like, before
coming in today.
I looked, you know,
I'm not going to
say how long ago,
but I looked at
it and I thought,
I did remember that.
Okay. All right.
Cool. So if there's no
questions about that,
I think we have
enough time to do.
This is kind of an easy
that's kind of
an easy one.
I'd prefer to
flex the legs.
Well, maybe we
should do easy.
Okay. Maybe maybe
we'll do that
one. All right.
But as usual, all those
ones you can launch
and see and go through.
Some might be
interesting and helpful
for future homeworks
there, okay?
Do do do. All right.
This feels like more of
a permanent marker here.
That's not.
Oh, man, do, do, do.
All right. That's good.
Cool. Alright, so
in this problem,
what we're looking at is
a refrigeration cycle just
to remind you what that
looks like, right?
So you have a
work transfer
that happens to
the compressor.
You take a
refrigerant. One of
the most common
is R 134 A.
You take that from
a low pressure,
you compress it
to a high one.
You force it to
condense, okay?
So you go from like
a rate of vapor.
You condense down
into a liquid,
you transfer heat out.
You put that through
an expansion valve,
what we call
throttling process,
a big temperature drop.
This causes you
then to produce
like a mixture of
liquid and vapor.
And then you evaporate
all the rest of
the basically all the rest
of the liquid there and
do the cooling, okay?
But the key part of this
is you have a heat out,
a heat in, and a
work in there.
And what we'd like to
determine are the Q dot
L's and the dot's
and the MDT, okay?
And usually in
these systems,
the way that
they're rated is
based on the Q
dot L, okay?
And they usually set
is things like
tons, right?
So how many tons of
ice could you produce,
like in an hour are there?
So that's kind
of a standard
way that these
are looked at.
Okay?
All right. So for the
thermal engines, right?
We said that All right.
And this is not a
thermal engine,
but just to remind
you, right?
The thermal engine was the
desirable thing
on top, right,
O W net out divided
by our Q in, okay?
That's how we
rank performance.
For refrigerators,
heat pumps, and
all of that,
we talk about a COP,
a coefficient of
performance, right?
So what's the
desirable thing
in a refrigerator?
Besides the beverages
being cold.
Yes. So that's it, right?
So the desirable thing
there is, right?
You want, like, a lot
of Q dot L, all right?
And what do you pay?
Work in. That's it.
Okay? So basically, you
have you have this.
If this was a heat pump,
so this is a refrigerator?
This is a refrigerator.
All right. If it
was a heat pump,
what would you write
in the numerator?
So remember, the whole
point of a heat pump is
that you want to warm
something up, right?
Cody. So that's it,
right? This is not
rocket science.
We will get the
No today, though, right?
So w.in there, right?
So that's refrigerator.
And, this would be
heat pump, right?
All right, so we're
interested in this one.
So we're interested
in the refrigerator.
So our desirable is the
Q dot L and the w.in.
As we were told,
the w.in we
know is 600 watts.
COP is equal to a
terrible value of 1.2.
1.2 is like That's
not a good number,
but it's a number
for this problem.
And so from this
formula of the COP,
so if I know write my
w.in and I know
my COP, from this
formula, right?
I can write Q dot
L is equal to
w.in times my C COP.
So again, 600 watts
times 1.2, okay?
And we have that as
a Q dot L, right?
So we now know one thing,
we know Q dot L. All
right. All right.
So as I mentioned, right,
in these cycles, to
determine things like,
to determine things
like, for example,
the mass transfer we're
going to get
into because I
know the Q dot L and
I want to get dot,
I'm going to need
to figure out,
like, what these
states are,
essentially what the
enthalpy is of this.
So if we look at
the evaporator.
So let me make sure I
have this is state one.
State one's 100.
Yeah. So let's look at
this evaporator here.
So this is my All right.
My evaporator
is nothing but,
right, like a
heat exchanger.
So I have some
MDOT entering.
I have some MDOT
that's leaving, right?
It's a steady flow
device. Okay.
Let's call this as
maybe state one.
I didn't number it.
Yeah. State one is
maybe entering.
State two is exiting,
and we have some
heat that's
being transferred
in Q dot L,
which we know from there.
And what we want
to figure out
next is the mass flow
rate, all right?
Sure, yeah, mass flow
rate. All right.
So to do that, we
write our conservation
of energy. Alright?
So we say, right,
that DE CV.
So this is my
control volume CV.
Dt is equal to e.in
minus e dot out.
We can also write our
conservation of mass,
dmCv dt is equal to my
m.in minus my m
dot out, right?
We assume steady
flow conditions,
so these go away.
And so what we'll have
then is write m.in
is equal to M dot out
is equal to m dot.
And in this case, right,
this also implies
that e.in is
equal to e dot out, right?
I can expand this.
So the ways that
energy can be
transferred in,
I can have aw.in,
aq.in, and then I
can have an m.in,
which I'm just going
to call as dot.
And I'm going to times
one plus velocity one
squared divided by
two plus g one,
and then that's going
to be equal to W dot
out plus Q dot
out plus dot out.
Again is dot times
H two plus velocity
two squared divided by
two plus GZ two, right?
We're going to
neglect, right,
kinetic and potential
energy effects, right?
So those are gone. Do we
have work transfer
into a heat exchanger?
No, workout. I'll
give you this one.
No. What about heat in?
What do we call
it? Q dot L. Okay.
What about heat
out? No, right?
So essentially, then
our Q dot L, right?
So this Q dot L
is equal to m
dot times H two
minus rh one.
Again, we would like
to find this dot.
We know Q dot L. We need
to figure out two and one.
Right? So for state
one state one,
what do we know
about state one?
So state one is entering
the evaporator.
What's the
pressure? 100 kp,
and our quality X
one is equal to two.
With Pi kiloor in tables,
you can look this up
and get to your H
one value for state two.
So I'd say Pi kiloor
H one equals a value.
Um and state two,
what do I know?
I know, again, the
pressure P one is
equal P two is equal
to P one because
it's a heat
exchanger, right?
Heat exchanges are
isobaric, right?
We don't have
pressure drops.
In this class,
we don't have
pressure drops across
heat exchangers.
And we know the
temperature,
the temperature is
given T two is equal to
negative 26 degrees
Celsius, right?
And it's fair to ask
yourself what's
going to be
the state of the
vapor there?
I mean, in this case,
we could look
it up and see,
but it's most likely
either a saturated
vapor or
potentially a
superheated vapor.
There, right?
But the point is
that presumably
from these two pieces
of information,
we then also know
H two, again,
from Pi color, right?
So with those two
things no, right?
We can substitute
into this formula,
and we'll
rearrange, right?
So dot is equal to
Q dot L divided
by H two minus
H one, right?
And what's my value?
The value that
I have for my MDOT
is 0.004 1
kilogram/second.
Yeah, that's like
a small fridge.
That's like your
fridge at home
is probably that size.
Okay. The final part then,
so we know Q dot
L, we know dot.
And now we can figure
out Q dot H, right?
And the way that
we can figure out
Q dot H is to draw,
again, a control volume
around the entire device.
So let's say this
is my whole,
you know, my whole
device here.
Okay, it looks like
this. Horribly drawn.
Right at the Q dot
H. All right,
which is out.
I have a Q dot L,
which is here,
and I have aw.in.
If I go in, I draw
my control volume. You
know, I don't know.
Let's say I draw
it like this
around the entire system.
You can look at
this and say,
you know, write the
first law here.
So if we say for the
first law is that,
um, Oh, my gosh.
What we're going to
end up with here
is that the change,
right, in the energy
of the system has
to be zero in its
steady state, right?
So the energy that I
transfer in must be
equal to the energy
that's transferred
out, right?
So Q dot H is what's
leaving and what's
entering is
then my w.in plus
my Q dot L, right?
And the w.in was
a given, right?
So that's 600
watts, the Q dot L,
um, We just determined,
which was over there,
that was, like,
the first thing that we
did plus that number.
And so what I
have at the end
of this is one, three,
two, zero watts is then
the Q dot H. Okay?
Yeah. And I
think one of the
things I always like,
wrap your head around
with this is that
you are able, right?
So the whole point of
the COP here is
that you're able to
transfer move more heat
than the work you
put in, okay?
It seems like a
violation of the
first law, right?
So I put like one unit of
electricity in, and
I'm able to pump,
let's say, in this case,
1.2 units of heat from
the cold reservoir.
I The way to know
that it's not
a violation is
to first just
look at the
first law, okay?
So everything, you know,
about that is possible.
I'm able to,
you know, move,
absorb more q dot L
here for an
amount of w.in.
For this to work, though,
the sum of those two
components in has
to equal the heat that
leaves, all right?
And that's why,
again, the back of
a fridge is very
warm and all of
that because
you have a lot
of heat to reject.
But there's many scenarios
where this makes a lot
of sense, you know?
So if you think about
electrification,
you want to electrify
so this again,
this is on the
refrigeration side,
but if you want
to run that
as like a heat pump,
So again, you can look
at that as an example.
So here's an example of
that. Water heater, right?
So you could take, like,
a resistor, take
electricity,
heat the water
directly, right?
That's first law,
though, right?
So I put electricity in,
I transfer work in.
All of that then becomes
heat for warming
this device.
But that's one
to one, right?
The point with the
heat pump, though,
is I can take one
unit of work in,
and I can move
in several units
of heat into the
water heater.
And that's the
whole reason
why heat pump technologies
are very competitive
is because they just,
like, I mean, it's
a no brainer.
You don't even need
to know thermo.
You do need to
know thermo,
but you don't really
need to understand thermo
to get the fact that for
the same dollar
that I pay,
I can have three units
of the same quality
of heat, right?
You're just
going to install
that capital costs
and other things
notwithstanding,
alright? Cool.
It's Friday.
I feel like I rain
you through a lot.
So I'm basically
going to close it.
I'm going to
close it here.
If you have any
questions, for
example, not
about the quiz.
I'm just kidding.
Maybe quiz, too.
Feel free to come up.
Otherwise, have
a great weekend,
everyone. Oh.