Okay, I got 210, so
I will get started.
So what I have
here, right,
is this example we left
off with last time,
where we took
a hot piece of
iron and dropped it
into a cold bath.
What we know from
this process
is that it's an adiabatic
adiabatic basically from
the overall
system, all right?
It's a no work exchange
because it's
incompressible
between CV one and
CV two in the
surroundings.
We represent that
by saying, right,
that the change in
the internal energy
of this combined system
is no heat, no
work, right?
So that's zero, okay?
Um, We know the
initial states, right?
We know the rock
to start with,
you know, the
water, right?
And so what we're
looking for
is the final temperature
that's there, right?
So what we did is, at
the end of the
last lecture,
right, the change in
the internal energy
of control volume one,
which I'm representing
with pink
here is the mass
of the iron,
the specific heat of
the iron times the
final temperature,
which we don't know minus
the initial
temperature, okay?
And we're going to
come up with a similar
expression for the water.
We're going to substitute
both those
formulas together,
and then we're going to
solve for T two, okay?
Um, Yes.
Okay. So for the
water baths,
and now we're basically
dealing with CV two.
So for control volume
to the water bath,
we know from
incompressible fluids that
the specific heat Cp is
equal to CV is
equal to C, right?
So it's it's a constant.
And so changes in
internal energy.
Random writing
little U here,
so jules per
kilogram is equal
to CV which is
a function of temperature
times dt, right?
This is just a
definition that we have.
If we integrate
through here and if we
treat the specific heat
as being constant over the
temperature range
that we're studying,
which is basically
valid for
most of the problems,
right, that we
work with, right?
We can pull that out of
the integral, right?
And we'll call
it dt, right?
And so in this case,
if we have that, you know,
Delta U, it is then equal
to, approximate
symbol, approximate.
So basically approximately
equal to some CV.
Let's call it,
you know, for
the now maybe average.
And then we can
times that by T
two minus T one, right?
And we did this
for the rock.
What I said is
in the tables.
So if you go to the
tables and you look
up what you have
for the iron.
So, not the rock,
the iron, right,
is there's 11 value
of CP, right?
Basically, one value of
the specific heat
that's there.
For water, you have
other ones, right, zero,
25, 50, 75 and 100.
My recommendation,
especially when
getting started in these
problems and working
on it for now
is just to pick
the value that's at
room temperature unless
you're told
otherwise, right?
So all I'm going to
say is that basically this
is for the case of
water, right, CV,
at T equals to
25 degrees C,
which because of
that, it's CP,
and there it's what, 4.1,
4.18 kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin.
All right? I mean, it's
very detailed,
but, you know,
I want to be explicit
with this, all right?
Is that clear
for all or no?
Great. Um Yeah.
And so then right
if we want to
turn this into
the right Delta U,
which is what we want.
Right? So the
big Delta U of
CV two is then
equal to the mass
of the water.
So mh2o times CV,
h2o times T two, the
final temperature,
which we don't know
minus the initial
temperature,
t1h 20, right?
Okay, so if I call this
as if I call this is,
let's call it
equation one, right?
If I call this basically
as equation two,
and if I call this
as equation three,
I combine two and three.
If I combine two
and three into one,
what we're going
to have is
the mass of the iron.
So M of F,
CV of F. I'm writing F
as the um uh the
symbol for iron,
T two minus T one,
comma F E, and then
that's going to be plus
this formula here.
So that's going to
be plus h2o, CV,
h2o times T two,
the final
temperature minus
the initial
temperature T one,
H two oh, and that's
all equal to zero.
All right. Maybe a kid.
And all you do is
you basically
rearrange them.
So if we rearrange
four and we
solve for T two,
what we're going
to have then is T
two is equal
to the mass of the iron CV
of the iron T one of
the iron plus the
mass of water h2o.
CV, h2o, and t1h 20,
and all that's essentially
divided by the CVs.
Then we're going
to have M of iron,
CV of iron plus
the mass of h2o,
and then the CV
of h2o, okay?
Yeah, and if I substitute
the value, right?
So we're given the
masses are given
in the problem.
The initial
temperatures are,
let's see, given in the
problem in Celsius.
That's perfectly fine here
because we're going
to expect a value
that's going to be
intermediate 80-25, right?
So you could see maybe
these initial factors
as kind of like
waiting factors for
which ones are going
to um end up at.
So we know the mass,
the CVs, we know
the mass, we know
the temperatures.
The CVs I just showed you,
CVs are CPs for
these cases.
So that's your water,
and that's your iron.
So you substitute that
in, and then it's
the same here.
You have the M's and
the C's with it.
If you substitute
those values,
what I have is a T
two that is 58 Oh,
I'm sorry, Geez,
I'm reading wrong.
25.6 degrees Celsius as
my final
temperature, okay?
And I can analyze this
and say Gee whiz,
that's not a huge
temperature increase.
That's like 0.6.
Calvin, but what you
have to recognize is
that the drawing here
is obviously not to scale.
There's an order of
magnitude more water
there by mass than
there is essentially
of iron.
That's that's half
a ton of water
and only 50 kilogram
then of iron?
Yes, please. When you
put the C for iron
at eight degrees.
You don't get so
in this case,
in this class, there
is no such thing.
Right? So there
is this value.
That's what's
in the table.
If you wanted to be
that sophisticated,
you could go up
and look at it.
What I would tell
you, though, and
this is what I
introduced earlier,
is if you want
to look up like
specific heats and how
they depend upon
temperature,
let's call this roughly
like I don't know,
100 Kelvin that's here.
You'll see kind of
a big drop off,
and then kind of,
you know, you do it.
So basically, by some
critical temperature,
you've already
activated most of
the modes of energy
storage in the material.
And so when you go
to really high ones,
you don't see that
much of a gain, right?
So water's a nice example.
So 25-100, you go
from 4.18 to 4.22.
So that's less
than 1% change
in the specific
heat, okay?
But if you get to,
like, temperature
differences that
are maybe like 1,000
Kelvin, right,
then maybe that tiny
amount that you have
there becomes relevant
for your calculations.
Okay? But fair question.
Other questions?
How might you do
this differently?
You had a very good
point last lecture,
if you cared to share.
Yeah.
Yes. Exactly.
So instead of writing
our conservation of
energy equation
in this way,
or we could write
it in this way.
The way you could
look at it is that
the change in the
internal energy of
the water has to equal
the change in
internal energy
of the iron, right?
Which is to say
that the heat
that I transfer
into the water
has to be equal
to the heat that
leaves that's transferred
out of the iron, right?
And for me, that's
a more intuitive
way to do it,
especially later on when
we get into heat
exchangers.
That's a much more
intuitive way,
but I'm just
following, you know,
basically, I'm following
the book here.
And also this framework of
kind of this
additive approach
into changes
internal energy
for control volumes
is a good one, right?
So the GSI, I
think Cassidy
worked through a
problem with a room
and a radiator and a fan,
and there it's very
helpful to visualize,
break it down into
the different parts.
Analyze, right from
your initial to
your final states and
then just start
adding things up.
And just like in
that problem,
I'm pretty sure it was
an adiabatic no work
transfer process
at the end of
it with the goal
basically to fight
T two, all right?
Wonderful. Okay,
so if there are
no other questions,
Okay.
Great. So today,
essentially,
we're going to go
through some
conservation principles,
and then at the end,
we're going to finish
with turbines,
right? There's
a bit of math.
You know, we're
going over a very
important is a very
important stage,
right, in the class
when we get into
what are called
steady flow devices.
But this is
rockets, nozzles,
diffusers, turbines.
Basically, everything
that goes fast
is and how we produce
the energy is based on
this analysis, all right?
Okay, so we've
done conservation.
Of energy. That's
the first principle.
In your courses
and later on,
you basically have
two other ones that
you'll deal with
conservation of
mass and conservation
of energy we've done.
Mass, now we're
going to do.
The last one is momentum.
When you take
M one oh six,
you're going to de a lot
with conservation of
mass and conservation
of momentum.
In this class, we only
do conservation of
energy and conservation
of mass with it.
Okay, what I want
you to look at here,
what I'm defining
essentially here is, again,
one of my, um, uh,
control volumes.
So I have, let's say,
um, you know,
I don't know,
I define some type of,
uh, uh, you know,
wonky looking,
um, you know,
basically control
volume here, right?
This is the interface
and basically maybe
at this interface,
Um, right?
I have a vector which
is normal, right?
So I have a vector
that's normal
at that point,
right, which I can define.
That's possible. Have
you ever read Gauss,
you know, beautiful
stuff from him.
If I take any
surface, right?
I can take a point.
I can define the
curvature at that point,
and I can define
a vector that's
normal away from it, okay?
We have that.
So this is basically
like let's say
a normal vector, one, two,
let's say at this point,
I have the following,
you know, velocity, right?
So let's say that I
have a fluid velocity,
V, I'll denote it
as a vector with
the arrow over it, okay?
The first step in all of
this, would be right?
To essentially, right,
to do the analysis
at this point,
what we actually
need to know
is the velocity,
right, of, let's say,
this fluid in
the normal direction
to this, right?
So, essentially, we do
a projection, right,
of this velocity
here into um,
onto the normal direction,
right, which we
can then call as,
let's say, V bar,
N, N denoting,
uh, the normal.
And I'm putting an
arrow above this,
at least for the
moment so I don't
confuse you with volume.
Again, I have
26 characters,
a couple of Greek letters,
but that's where we're
we're at, right?
And I represent
this, you know,
here in the plot again.
If you want to go through,
you can run through
that code and
see it, right?
Okay, that's the mathy
part of it, right?
In reality, the
way that we
deal with this is we don't
draw boundaries
in a weird way
where we need to
do math, right?
We're engineers.
We're efficient.
Okay? If you want
torture yourself,
you can get down the
road there, right?
So in this case, what I'm
showing you is a
classic problem,
and a classic problem
of a pipe flow, okay?
And I'm going to draw
the boundary such as
this velocity that I see
here matches Vn, right?
So basically, I'm
going to draw
this in this
way, all right?
How do I do that?
The first thing
to know is to
describe for you what
a velocity looks
like in a pipe flow.
There's a fascinating
history to
this Poisll was
looking at this,
like flow in your blood
in your veins and,
like, how that goes.
And it turns out, right,
there's two
important well,
basically,
there's, like, one
very important
thing in fluids.
Thermo, we draw a
boundary in fluids,
there's no slip
at the wall.
There is no slip, okay?
So Here, I have no
slip. Okay, one.
I have some flow that
I'm bringing in.
I have no slip there.
What it basically means is
that I'm going
to assume that
I'm going to end
up with a maximum
velocity at the middle,
and probably to a
good approximation,
actually maybe
analytically correct,
you're going
to end up with
a parabolic flow
profile, right?
So again, this is
All right, maximum,
the way we represent
these velocities at
these different points
is we draw arrows
that look like
this, all right?
Okay. But this
is my right?
This is my boundary.
And I've drawn
this, right?
It turns out
maybe I'm a bit
lucky in the way that
I've drawn it here,
it turns out that all
those velocity vectors,
the magnitude or
the direction of
those velocity
vectors also
lies on the normal, right?
The plane that's normal or
the line that's normal
to that plane, okay?
Again, if you
want to plot it,
you can see it
see it there.
Okay. Um great. All right?
Ooh. All right.
Where should I go
with this, right?
So maybe it's better if I
keep up before I get
into this, right?
So we can talk
about so this is
like velocities,
but actually what
we care about is
not necessarily
velocity all the time.
We care a lot about
mass flow rates, okay?
So we can take this and
this velocity, and
by knowing, right,
the density of
the fluid or
specific volume
of the fluid,
I can turn this into
mass fluorides.
That's a conserved
principle.
There is no conservation
of volume, okay?
You get into that.
You think about
a compressor.
I have a low
specific volume
going into a compressor,
a high one,
leaving it Like,
if you go with
conservation of volume,
you're out of job.
Okay? All right.
So we can write a
differential of
the mass flow rate,
generally, right?
Delta, again, I'm going to
go with inexact
differentials.
Delta M dot, M dot,
meaning that, you know,
like the Newton
notation, right?
So dm dt is equal
to M dot, right?
So this is what
Leibnitz, that's
Neton, right?
So we're going with
Newton notation
here in M dot is
equal to the inverse
of specific volume.
The magnitude of the
velocity normal, right?
So basically, the
normal velocity
and the cross
sectional the
differential then of
the cross sectional area
that's that's there.
And again, we
chose this plane
intelligently so
that, you know,
this matches that
and we don't
have to do any
kind of cosines
or projections. All right.
If we go with
that formula that I
had there, right?
So what I can say is that
the magnitude then of
this normal
velocity is then
equal to some V max, okay?
So value that's here.
It doesn't really concern
us for this class.
And then this would be
one minus little R, right?
Divided by big R, right?
So this would be,
right, big R,
and then little R is
just a coordinate, right?
In the pipe, okay?
So when I have,
R equals little R
equals zero,
write a maximum,
when I have little
R equal to big R,
this is zero,
and that's how
you produce that profile.
All right. So if we
do a substitution
into this and we
integrate, okay?
So if I go write
an integral and DM
dot, all right?
So I'm going to
basically be doing
a double integral because
it's an area of
specific volume,
the magnitude of
the normal velocity
R the DR or P,
right, is like this
is polar
coordinates, right?
I could like wrote, you
know, look into the
um if I had basically
looking down the pipe,
this is my R, right?
This would be
your Phi, right?
So you assume it's
an axymmetric,
you know, problem, okay?
So we don't have
any sort of
dependence on the
P that's in here.
So these integral limits
will be like zero to
two Pi and then
zero to R, right?
So basically zero to R,
and then zero to two Pi in
terms of of the
radian, right?
Okay. So the
first one, right,
the first integral because
we don't have
any Phi in here,
this is going to be
two Pi minus zero.
So you'll end up
with a two Pi.
And then the other one
is that, um, right?
We're going to
end up here.
Well, let's just
write it out.
Basically, you're
going to have here
an m.in this case,
right, which is going
to then be equal to
two Pi V max, right?
V max is a constant.
So we should basically
substitute this
formula into here,
and we integrate
into two Pi.
So you have two Pi V max
divided by
specific volume.
There's an integral
zero to R of R
minus R squared
divided by R,
okay, and D R, right?
You can go through and you
integrate again with this,
and what you're
going to end
up with is an M dot
that's equal to
Pi times V max,
right, your
maximum velocity R
squared divided by
three times the
specific volume, okay?
Cool. All right, um do.
Yeah, in a pipe, so
basically in a pipe,
we know that AC,
so the cross sectional
area is going
to be equal to
Pi R is equal
to Pi squared.
And so if with
this knowledge,
so I go with Pi R squared,
I can rewrite then
my dot as being
equal to a row.
So, let's go with this.
Let's go with AC.
Pi squared V max,
and then this is
divided by three V.
Again, because this is
going to come up and
sometimes you might see it
in a fluids context,
right, the density
is equal to
the inverse of
specific volume.
And so what this will
look like then is
times AC times V max
divided by basically
divided by three, okay?
Um, at the end of this,
this will all make
sense why we
bother, right?
It turns out this V
max divided by three.
You can do the math
and go through
with the definition of
the average velocity,
but it turns out
this is basically
going to be
the average velocity
in the pipe, right?
And so this is
by definition,
equal to one
over AC, right?
So the integral over
the cross sectional
area, right?
The normal vector,
the magnitude of
the normal vector
to the plane there.
And then this is dC.
I'll spare you, but
if you go through my
notes there and see,
what you would see at
the end of this
is that the
max or that the
average velocity is
basically going to
be equal to V max
divided by three there,
okay? So, who cares?
The who cares
is that, again,
when we think about
control volumes
and we draw them,
we draw them
intelligently.
When they cross through
something like
a pipe, right?
This should be done,
right, essentially
perpendicular to the flow,
right, that you have
there. That's one.
The second thing is
that for most
of this course,
I think probably
the entirety,
we're going to give
you velocity values,
and these are going
to indicate averages.
So if you see a
pipe that says
100 meters a
second, you know,
into a nozzle there,
it means that it's
the average velocity
into the nozzle, okay?
And I'm telling
you with math
and knowledge and physics,
you could go back and
show that, right?
If I had detailed
knowledge about
the flow profile and
what's there, I could,
you know, come up
with this average,
and that's ME one oh six,
not this class, okay?
All right. Any
comments about that?
All right. Cool.
All right.
So there we go. So again,
average velocities are
what we care about,
and we draw control
volumes intelligently.
The conservation of mass
principle is written
like this, right?
So we have a
control volume.
The net change in the mass
in the control volume is
equal to how much
enters it minus how
much it leaves it.
That's the same thing
that we did, right?
This is accounting fluid
mechanics accounting,
right? It's
written like this.
So in non rate form in
minus M out is Delta MCV.
We will, again,
a lot of this,
we'll be writing
it in rate form.
We're going to talk
about dot ins minus
M dot outs are
equal to dm, cv dt.
I'm noting here the
units in this case,
again, in Leibniz and
in Newton notation.
All right. Okay. Yes.
You can take
everything that
I've written
and done here,
I did it for a pipe flow,
but you could go
and do it for,
and develop an
MDOT formula
for something that's
leaving or entering.
That would end up
being something
that's on the
right hand side,
and that would be equal
to the rate of change
of what's actually
inside of the control
volume, okay?
So I'm going to
spare you know,
having to go through that.
But again, this is
nothing but, uh, right?
Essentially, this
formula that I'm writing
here and done
more generally.
And here, row in
this case is, again,
the density, V here,
dv here does not
have a vector.
This is indicating
the volume, right?
So essentially the density
the rate of change
of the density
times the change in the
volume is then equal
to the change in
the mass in the
control volume.
Okay.
All right. Another
thing that's
going to come up
a lot is you're
going to have things
sometimes cases
where multiple streams
are coming into a
control volume and maybe
leaving as one or
vice versa, okay?
This is called a
mixing chamber.
You know, we're
going to have
systems that we do it.
What do you need
to know is that
when these are
steady processes,
so again, what was
the formula that we
had here, right?
We said that dm
CV dt is equal to
dm in dt minus
dM out dt, okay?
Um a steady process in
this case does not mean
that all of them
go away, okay?
That technically is a
steady process, right?
But the system is
dead, okay, right?
If nothing's coming
in, nothing's
leaving, obviously
nothing's changing.
Steady in this
case here means
that this term
is out, okay?
So it's like I have
the same amount leaving
as I have entering, okay?
That's what's
steady for, right?
So, MD basically MDOT
in is equal to
your MDT out.
All right. And that's
what's shown here,
right, in this
case, right?
So I have some 2
kilograms/second
in, 3 kilograms/second in.
What must be leaving under
steady conditions, right,
is then that
two plus three
must be equal to the
five, all right?
And, I mean, turbines,
diffusers, nozzles, again,
a lot of what
we're going to
analyze are going to have,
I would say 90%
of what we analyze
is going to be this.
There's very few cases.
They are important cases,
but there's a few
cases where you have,
like what we call unsteady
flow where essentially,
let's say you
have more leaving
than you have
entering, okay?
I won't make the accounting
joke about that,
alright?
Fine. So that's
one part of it.
The second thing
is that there is
no, as I mentioned before,
there is no
conservation of
volume, uh,
principle, okay?
And the case that
I give here,
like I mentioned before,
is this air
compressor case.
I have 2
kilograms/second in,
2 kilograms/second
out, right?
So that's steady according
to my definition.
But because the density
in here or the
specific volume here
is much higher than the
specific volume here,
the denser phase, you're
going to end up with
a lower volumetric
flow rate
leaving than what
enters, okay?
So M dots,
conservation of mass,
conservation
of energy, not
conservation of
volume, right?
Yeah. And you can play
fast with the rules.
If you do something
that's incompressible,
let's say like
water, go ahead.
How does this make
sense to play you?
I don't understand
the question.
Say it again.
Because you said the air
leaving the system faster
than it's entering it.
So I'm saying the mass is
entering at the same rate
that it's leaving, right?
The mass. So just
follow with me.
So let's say we
accept that.
You also accept that
when you compress
something,
is the density
higher or lower?
Is the specific volume
Lower. Specific volume
times the mass flow rate,
the product of that is
the volumetric flow rate.
So it is lower.
The big compressor
industry
has been lying
to you, alright?
Okay. Other comments
about this?
Okay, so that's sweet.
You got EE one
oh six your setup to
succeed on, alright?
Alright.
So, now we're going
to use this, alright?
So I'm going to
go through Oh,
boy, I don't like that.
Why is that cut
off like that?
Okay. Um Okay.
Apologies. I'm
not sure why
my Can I do this
in two present?
Of course not. Okay, so
here there
were basically we're
talking about,
you know, one inlet,
one outlet here.
What I would like
to go through in
this example is to go
into multiple
streams, okay?
And at the end of this,
I'm going to show you why
you care about enthalpy,
why you're going
to use enthalpy
for all analysis of
all steady flow
devices and
not changes in
internal energy
like we've done, right?
So enthalpy is where
we're going with this,
like a very meaningful
use of enthalpy, right?
Um, So let's say I have
a control volume
here that I
draw with my dashed lines,
and I have these
dots that are in,
and so N number
of M dots in
and K number of dots out.
Eganga means inlet,
Aus Ganga means
exit, apologies.
So we have M dot.
Our general mass
balance is going to be
the rate of change of mass
in the control volume.
Ms of T is going to be
equal to the sum of
those dots in minus
the sum of the M dots out?
When we have a
steady balance,
the rate that
the mass enters
is equal to the rate
that it leaves.
Okay, so that's what
the mass, right?
Now we can go and do the
energy balance, all right?
The thing is that fluids
also carry energy.
Remember before we do
a control volume,
and I said,
In this control volume,
when I don't have
mass exchange,
what are the ways I can
transfer energy
in and out?
Louder. I'm like,
getting I don't know.
Maybe there's, like,
a thing in my ear.
Okay. How can I
transfer energy in and
out of control volume?
Work Or heat. That's it.
Okay?
What I'm telling you
is when you have
an open system,
you can also carry
energy in with
mass, right?
Mass, if I move it really
quick carries kinetic
energy, right?
There can be
kinetic energy.
Mass that I bring from
very high, right?
There's potential energy
that could be
brought into it,
and a fluid also
contains internal
energy, right?
It's mass, okay?
So, um, the
rate of change.
So let's say the difference
in the energy in
this control volume at
some future time
minus now is
equal to the net
heat we transfer
in minus the network
we transfer out plus
an additional term,
which is the mass
the change in
the mass that
enters with its
little energy.
I'll get into
that in a second,
minus the change in
mass times the
energy content
that it has leaving, okay?
So we have basically
two new terms,
and it has to do with
the flow energy there,
okay? What is little E?
So little E, right?
We already did
this in the first,
right in the first
parts of the lecture.
We said, Look,
when we deal
with systems here, right?
We don't want to
talk about all
the kinds of
energy, right?
You know, you
have magnetic,
right, you got all
kinds of stuff.
For in thermal,
we just said,
like, look, we want
to deal, right?
So changes, right? We had,
like, changes in,
um, you know,
Delta E CV, right,
is equal to E in
minus the E out.
And the way that we
said that energy
could change in the
control volume,
right, was this Delta
U plus the Delta KE,
plus the, um, uh,
Delta P. We said,
these are the three
types of energy changes
we're interested in
in this class, okay?
And we said, Look,
with the internal energy
for pure substances,
it depends on,
like, temperature
and pressure,
pressure and
specific volume,
they say two things.
Okay? This depends on how
high you are and
how fast you are.
You know, are you
using bolt or,
you know, a
skydiver, right?
Um, Okay,
it's no different with
the fluids, right?
A fluid can possess
internal energy, right?
It can be hot, it
can be cold, right?
It can possess
kinetic energy.
It can have a speed
to it, a velocity,
nozzles, very
important nozzles,
right, rockets
and all of that.
And it can possess
potential energy, right?
If it's very high, think
pump hydro, right?
Switzerland where
I was before,
the country's blessed with
mountains and all of this,
but also a lot of
mountain lakes.
And so they used
to store a ton
of energy with hydro,
pump it up, bring
it back down.
It's a beautiful way
to store energy.
So those are like the
three ways, again,
in this class that we're
going to talk about
the energy of a
flowing fluid, okay?
That's literally, right?
And again, because
it's a little letter,
it indicates
that it's energy
per mass, right?
Okay, so you can
go from this form
that I have here.
So if we divide basically
both sides here
by Delta T,
so some small time,
increment, right?
We can turn each
of these things
into a rate form, right?
So the change in
the energy of
the control volume
can be E dot, right?
The the change in
heat transfer can
be Q dot, right,
w dot, and so on
and so forth,
including also, the
mass flow rates, right?
And so that's what
we write here.
So basically, this
form of the formula is
the conservation of energy
for control volume,
where I can bring
heat in or out,
work in or out, or a
fluid in or out, okay?
So here, okay?
So the Q dot, right?
This could be
essentially like
heat loss through
a housing.
But the W dot, I
want to pause for
a second because this is
a little bit
complicated, all right?
This W dot, right?
When we were dealing with
these systems
and the pistons,
what were ways that we
were dealing with work?
Let's say, what
were types of
work transfer
processes that
we could do with,
like, a piston cylinder?
Name and what?
Yes. Okay. That's
wonderful.
What's another type
of work interaction?
Yeah. That's also PDV.
So I can do that and that.
That's good.
Okay. Yes, please,
Force distance.
Force distance of
similar to him.
Yes, please.
Name. Ryan electric work.
Yes, right? I can
transfer electrically.
That was the other
way we did it, okay?
What I'm telling you here
is that when you
bring a fluid in,
right, you may have to
displace a fluid
out, okay?
That makes sense.
Kind of like a
plunger effect,
a piston, a little bit
like the boundary
work before.
You may have to push it.
And that is
called flow work.
And you don't give a shit
as an engineer
about flow work.
That's a penalty
for you, okay?
So you want to
get flow work
out of this W dot, okay?
If you want a job with GE,
I saw Nviden front,
you want to go
work for GE.
This w dot cannot be
w dot of everything.
You want to get flow
work out of it.
And I'm going
to show you how
to get rid of that, okay?
Um, so let's imagine
this experiment, okay?
So again, let's
say we have
this bladder looking
control volume,
all right? All right?
So you got let's
say a fictitious,
an imaginary
piston, and it has
some cross sectional area
to it, A, all right?
The fluid at
this point has
a density or the inverse
specific volume,
and it has a
pressure, all right?
And let's say that there's
one stream that
it can leave.
And now we push that
piston a little bit.
So we do that
displacement.
So what was
mentioned before,
we displaced that
piston a little bit.
So some of delta little S,
so that's a distance
that it's moved.
The cross sectional area
times that Delta
S is a Delta V,
a volume change, okay?
P dv, right, in
a sense, right?
So the work you
have there is
that pressure there times
that displacement
in volume.
And we can write
it as rate form.
It can be w dot is
the pressure times
the cross sectional area
times the velocity.
And again, just
because I've
got too many Vs
that are here,
I'm going to go with
the German one vindiki
W. We do W for velocity.
PAW there is then
the rate of flow work
that's being
transferred in, right?
And then we do
it to the exit.
We're going to have a
density of the exit,
a pressure at the exit,
a surface that's a
cross sectional area.
We have an area
at the exit,
and then we can expand it.
We can expand that
some distance.
Again, that delta S times
that cross sectional area
becomes a displacement
volume, pdv.
That's the work or
we can have the
rate of it.
PA times the velocity
that the fluid moves.
So flow work, okay?
So the total work, so that
W dot that I showed you
before in the
conservation of energy,
right, that consists
of useful work.
All right, what
we would call
shaft work or what we
formerly just called,
like boundary work.
You know, basically,
that's useful work
plus the rate of
flow work leaving
the system minus
the rate of
flow work that's entering
into that, okay?
And the formula
that's the best way I
have the total rate
of work transferred
out of the system
is equal to
the useful work plus
the dot specific volume of
the fluid stream leaving
minus M dot PV of
the one entering.
And the thing you
should see with this
is that we have
a P, right?
So the pressure times
the specific volume
that's there, right?
And if you
remember enthalpy,
what's enthalpy?
It's H. Yes. Thank
you. Like my kids.
Yeah. So they're right
in the funniest ways.
Okay, U plus PV,
right? P there.
And so, essentially what
we're going to do
is we're going to
take that flow
work portion.
We're going to
combine it with
the internal energy
of that flow stream,
and we're going to
form enthalpy there.
So the enthalpy, right?
The whole point of
the enthalpy is you're
basically taking
flow work out of the
total work term.
So all that's left is
useful work, okay?
That's what I'm
doing here, right?
So this is kind of
a mess, but right,
the rate of
change of energy
in the system is
the rate that we
transfer heat in minus
the rate of work
leaving, right?
That is shaft
work, flow work
leaving, flow
work entering,
plus the sum of
the mass entering times
the energy stream there,
minus the mass leaving
times its energy
stream, okay?
And if you put
this whole term
into the W dot,
and I take the PV terms,
and I combine
them here, right?
So now I've got rate of
change of energy and
my control volume is he
leaving work shaft work,
useful work
transferred out
plus all of
that U plus PV,
which is enthalpy,
kinetic energy
and potential
energy, okay?
So we take, right,
the flow work out
of the total work,
and then we form enthalpy
in the fluid
stream, right?
And that's a
more natural way
to introduce
enthalpy, right?
This is actually
the way you should
introduce enthalpy
is actually through
this analysis,
because it has a lot
of utility, right,
much more than the
other one, okay?
Um, Yes.
So if you want to
compare and contrast,
so here's the
conservation of
energy when we do
the enthalpy form.
So we have the
useful work,
right? Notation with that.
If you go with
the notation of
internal energy
in the flow term,
this w dot is the
overall work, okay?
So, um, you know,
so I can show
an example because I
got a bit of time.
I'll show you an
example of how it is.
So let's think about
a turbine, right?
So I have a turbine, um,
And we can apply
this conservation of
mass and which we
introduced today and
the conservation
of energy principle
for an open system,
which we have
today, alright?
Okay. All right.
So what does it look
like a turbine?
You have a star
and a rotter
A rotter rotates,
a star stays.
You start off with a
very compressed region.
So the smallest part of
the turbine is where
you're most compressed,
and then it expands.
So at some schools,
that's like a question
they ask on the final.
They take you the
show a turbine
and they say, what's
the front and the back?
And then some
people don't know.
So you start off
very, very compressed
and you leave it's
the opposite of
a compressor.
A compressor, you
would start off
highly expanded and
you get smaller.
So we have the inlet,
we have the outlet.
And what we're
interested in
the turbine is the rate
of work that's
transferred out,
and that we call
shaft work,
spinning the
shaft that spins,
there's a force
associated with that.
It can move through
a distance.
A lot of times you're
just spinning right
a generator producing
electricity from this,
but shaft work is what
you want to know.
P in kinetic energies are
trivially kind of small
compared to the changes in
enthalpy that happen here.
So Delta KE and Delta P
are usually pretty small.
And then these things
are usually insulated,
so we don't have
heat transfer.
If it's poorly insulated,
you may have heat
transfer out,
but then you're
losing money, right?
So the way to
analyze this is you
write your conservation
of mass, right?
Steady, um, under
steady conditions.
So the rate that
mass enters
equals the mass
that leaves.
And then for the
conservation
of energy, the same thing.
There's no change in
the energy to
control volume.
It's adiabatic.
There's no kinetic or
potential energy terms.
And so all the w dot
S is is dot, right,
because that's equal to
the inlet and the outlet,
times the enthalpy at
the entrance minus the
enthalpy at the exit.
Like, that's it.
Like, it's so simple.
You just get
these two states.
All I need to know is the
enthalpy and the MDT,
and you can say
things like, that's
a ten megawatt
turbine, okay? G.
That must be the states
that you need to
make that work.
Yes, please. Name?
Andy. Fluid.
The thing is,
it has. It can
come in with a velocity.
It's going to leave
with a velocity.
But when you go in
and you actually
calculate in joules
how much that it is,
it's not really
comparable to
the difference in
the enthalpies
that are there.
The square of
that velocity,
if you now compare
that with the
difference in
the enthalpies
in these kinds
of problems,
it's not there.
One place where it can
happen is when you
get into nozzles.
So in nozzles, that's
the whole point, right?
The whole point of
a nozzle is that
I take a lot of
enthropy to start and
I convert all of it,
all of it into velocity.
So you can design
systems where
you make that,
or you could design
a system where
you want to,
you know, take all of
the enthropy
and convert it
into potential energy.
Like, these can be done.
Yeah. Okay. But you
could double check.
You could go in and put
some velocities in.
Maybe that's homework, you
know, next time,
come and tell me.
Okay? Other questions
about this until now?
Okay.
Um Yes.
So here you could go
through and do it.
So this would be
some numbers.
You know, for Andy,
he could go in
and put 10
meters/second here,
100 meters/second
here and say how
different the
work would be.
But if we neglect
kinetic and potential
energy and we assume
it's adiabatic,
that's going to
be the formula
for the shaft work.
And so all you need to
determine is H
one and H two.
So that whole part
about Pi killre,
why do we care at all
about states, right?
You know, I put in
the two conditions
that I know.
The other two
conditions that
I know, dot
notation, right?
I basically get the
enthalpy out of it.
So here we have a
superheated steam,
so high pressure, 6
megapascals, 400 degrees.
See a good quality
steam coming in.
Um, we're leaving as a,
a saturated liquid
vapor condition,
so 90% of vapor
and much lower
pressure, okay?
Um, And that's
good, right?
We have a huge
difference between
60 bar to 0.2 bars,
you know, that's going
to produce a lot of
work out of the system.
But by knowing here
the pressure and
the quality,
you have complete
information
of the system, right?
You're going to be able to
determine the enthalpy by
the book tables or
Pi color there.
That's how it's
represented on
a TV diagram, right?
So superheated out here.
We're showing the isobar,
and then we end
up under the dome
here with the
saturated vapor. Okay.
I just some
numbers with this.
So if I have a bit
of time, I do.
Um, So the numbers
that I have,
maybe am I going
to be able to
just show this or is it
going to look wonky?
Okay, now it looks good.
I don't know
why. All right.
Okay, so we have
here, right,
for State one
State one Right?
So we know P one is
equal to our 60 bar,
T one is equal to
400 degrees C.
With this, because it's in
the superheated
region, right?
I'm going to be able to
determine everything
including my enthalpy,
my H one, right?
For my state two,
Let's see if we
can turn H one,
and we can determine also
the specific
internal energy
U one, right?
For state two, of P two
is equal to 0.2 bar,
and the quality of the
vapor is equal to 0.9.
Again, from this,
I can know H two,
and I can also know
U two there, okay?
And we set the dot shaft,
so the useful work
was equal to
the mass flowy,
which is also given
as 4,600 kilograms
an hour.
All right, that's
going to be equal to H
one minus H two.
If we do the substitution,
what you're going
to end up with
is a let me look at this.
This is like that.
That's a big value.
So what I'm going to end
up with here is one, zero,
28, 102 8 megawatts.
Basically, at
this case, that's
that's a massive
power plant.
It's like a gigawatt
of power plants.
No, I'm sorry. Hold
on. Wait a second.
I've multiplied
it in 10,000.
If I put this in,
what you're going to
end up with is
a 1.03 megawatt
power plant.
That's more
reasonable? Yes.
Okay. So now the thing is,
if now we want to
compute the total
work, right?
The total work.
So this is the
correct one, right?
This is basically
what you want.
But you can go
right with the
w.net out to the w
dot total, right?
That would be.u1
minus U two,
okay, specific volume or
internal energy, specific
internal energy.
And if you substitute
and you have that,
you're going to
end up with 0.841.
Let's see, megawatt,
okay? And that's wrong.
And that's not, like,
a little bit wrong.
That's, like, wrong
by, like, a mile.
I you know, there.
So 1.0 megawatts versus
0.84 with it, okay?
And so that's
why, you know,
we go through we
extract the flow work
out of the work term.
We put that then
into the U plus PV.
We form enthalpy.
And so, with all
of these systems,
the rate of work
transferred out,
transferred in,
the rate of heat out,
the rate of heat
in is all going to
become dot
enthalpies, okay?
So life gets simpler
in a sense, with
this, all right?
Okay, so you all
did great today.
That's everything you can
do after the lecture.
I'm going to close
here. So if any of you
have any questions,
please feel free
to come up.
Thank you.