PROFESSOR: I'm also
quite curious what
this is going to look like on
the recorded video in the night
here.
So now-- so all right.
So that was-- we talked
about reservoirs.
We talked about this single
expansion of a piston doing work
with an ideal gas there.
That was not inconsistent
with Kelvin's statements
since we didn't just
have heat into work.
We also had a change in the
volume from state 1 to state 2.
But now we're going
to start to connect
some of these more
thought experiments
with real concrete systems.
And the first type
that's very important
are what are called
heat engines.
So what is a heat engine?
So it's an engine which is here.
We draw it as a ball.
I'll show a real example
in the next slide here.
But you have an engine here.
On one side of it, you have
a high temperature source.
So that's a high temperature
source at some, let's say, TH.
And you have a low
temperature sink
which is at some temperature--
usually, it's denoted TL.
So you have some heat that
you're transferring in,
some work--
the net work that's
transferred out.
And in order to make this work,
to make this thing actually
work, you need to actually
transfer heat out of the system.
So just like I said before, we
thought about this experiment.
We transfer heat in.
You get some work.
But if you want to keep doing
that over and over again,
you're going to have
to have a cooling step
to bring it back to its
initial state to start over.
It's not intuitive.
I understand that.
I've had my PhD
students also ask
me, Tom, why don't we do this?
We can just put heat in.
Yeah, of course, fine.
But also, you have
to take heat out.
So you have that.
So you have the heat in, the
heat out, and the work out.
So it receives this heat from
a high temperature source.
It's converting it usually
into something like shaft work.
So this is like a model
for a power plant.
So that thing that you're
spinning is a shaft.
That shaft is connected
to a generator.
That generator
makes electricity.
And that's why we have
lights on in this room--
well, some lights
on in this room.
[CHUCKLES]
And then you got to reject
the remaining amount of heat.
Where do we reject that to?
We reject it to the environment.
So that-- I don't know--
I don't know--
I don't recall in
California seeing it a lot.
I grew up in the Midwest.
I grew up in Illinois.
Illinois was known for, among
other things, the Manhattan
Project.
We did nuclear.
Of course, they did a
lot of that stuff here.
But there's a lot of
nuclear power plants.
So we had a lot of
these cooling towers,
so these big gray things
where sometimes it
looks like a bunch of
smoke is coming out of it.
That's not smoke.
That's water vapor that's
condensed into droplets,
and it's clouds.
And that's where
you're rejecting heat.
You can also reject
heat into rivers.
It can be done into oceans.
And all of that is used to
cool steam that's coming out
of the back end of a turbine.
And again, these things
all operate on a cycle.
That's the key insight.
So what does it look like?
So again, the-- for now--
we're in a transition
to more sustainability
and weaning ourselves off of it.
But the reality, even in
where I was in Europe,
50% of all electricity there
was still generated in 2017
with a coal-fired power plant,
which looks exactly like this.
You take water.
You compress it with
a pump that goes
into what's called a boiler.
You take something.
It can be sunlight, it can
be coal, it can be whatever.
You burn it, or you
concentrate that heat.
You boil the water,
so that water
gets to a really high
temperature and a high pressure.
So you vaporize it, get
it to high temperature
and high pressure.
You send that into a turbine.
So first, it goes into
this really narrow part.
And then, as it passes through,
it causes these fans to spin.
It expands, transfers
work out to the generator.
Now you have, out of the back
end of there, still steam,
usually at a lower pressure
and maybe a lower temperature.
And then you condense that.
You condense that into what's
called a surface condenser.
So imagine this is
like a bunch of pipes.
So you have like 1,000 pipes
all next to each other.
On the inside of them, you
take water out of a river.
You send it through the pipe.
Then you put it back into
the river or into it.
On the outside of
those pipes, you
condense the steam
which is coming out
of the back end of that turbine.
So then your liquid here is
a liquid, saturated liquid,
and then you send it
back into the pump there.
Maybe it's interesting to know
that process of actually cooling
that condenser.
Does anyone want to hazard a
guess how much water we take out
of the ground every
year, as a percentage
of all the water that we
take out of the ground,
to actually cool surface
condensers in the US?
STUDENT: 60%.
PROFESSOR: Say it
[INDISCERNIBLE] one more time.
STUDENT: 60.
PROFESSOR: 60.
STUDENT: Someone said 20.
PROFESSOR: Someone said 20.
So if we took the average
of it, it's not far off.
50% of all the
flipping groundwater
we take out in a year
goes through something
that looks like this and
basically back into the ground.
At the end of It,
that's not consumption.
It's out of the ground, and
then it's back into the ground.
That's fine.
70% of all the water
that we consume in a year
actually goes into agriculture.
California feeds the world,
so a lot of [INDISCERNIBLE].
But it's interesting to know
because these things come
into conflict.
This is called the
water-energy nexus.
So we have energy.
Who needs water at some point?
We have water which
we need for drinking.
Sometimes it's called
water-energy-food nexus.
But all these things
come together.
And really, it's that device.
It's the surface condenser.
And yeah, that's literally
my entire line of research,
is looking at doing this
stuff, understanding it better
and how we do it
more efficiently.
Anyway, so we have
these four components.
Within this control volume-- so
if I'm not talking about river
water coming in and
cooling the condenser,
if I'm not talking about how
the fuel comes into heat--
I just have heat in.
I have heat out.
I have work in
for my compressor.
I have work out for my turbine.
We can treat that
as a closed system.
Because at this scale,
that water is not leaving,
assuming no leaks, whatever.
And closed systems
undergoing a cycle--
remember, we started in one
state, another, another,
another.
Just like being on
a track, you need
to get back where you
started at the beginning.
So with the first
law, then we have--
we'll have no change,
then, in that cycle.
So what you have to say
is that the work out
is equal to the heat in
minus, then, the heat out.
And so-- again, the point
is that this heat out-- we
need to do it.
You need to transfer it out.
And it represents a wasted heat,
but we would love to use it.
But it's just not at that high
temperature like we had before.
So you're getting an insight
that energy also has a quality.
It's not just conserved,
but it also has a quality.
And it's also never zero.
So the point is that the net
work that we can transfer out
is always less than the
heat that we transfer in.
And with these
terms now defined,
we can talk about
actual efficiency.
We can talk about an
actual, honest to God,
proper efficiency,
which is here--
and we write with
the Greek letter eta,
eta, which is the ratio
of the network output,
so the shaft work here, divided
by the total heat input.
So that's W net out
divided by Q in.
So we can rewrite that
diagram that I showed before.
So again, now we have that
high temperature reservoir
at a temperature TH.
So that-- the point
of the reservoir
is that TH won't change even
if I transfer heat out of it.
We have-- and we call
the heat transfer QH.
We then have the heat
rejected, so that's
QL, rejected to the low
temperature reservoir at TL.
And then we have
the W net out here.
Because I'm drawing
arrows, so because I'm
indicating arrows and directions
of where things are going,
we are treating these
things as magnitudes.
A vector is something that
has magnitude and direction.
I've given you the direction.
So these are just--
again, these are not vectors.
But in an analogy
with a vector, you
have a magnitude and direction.
I'm giving you the direction of
heat transfer and work transfer,
so these quantities are
treated as positive.
So rewriting it,
W net out is then
the Q from the high
temperature minus the Q
from the low
temperature reservoir.
And if we divide
both sides by QH--
the definition of eta was the
work out divided by the heat in,
so that's there.
And that's equal to 1 minus the
heat transferred to the lower
reservoir divided by
the heat transferred
from the high
temperature reservoir.
And some actual values--
so after like 120 years of
research into the diesel
engine-- that was one of the
first rationally designed
engines--
those things are close
to 40% efficiency,
so that's like
chemical-- basically,
your chemical energy,
in that sense,
is kind of like
your energy input,
and you have the work output.
The normal automobile
engine, close to 25%.
And these large, really
large steam power plants,
because they are really
highly optimized,
they can get up to 60% But the
take-home message from that
is like, 100 and
whatever years and lots
of money and investment,
and that's your number.
So you still lose
like 40% of this,
and that's necessary in
order to do the cycle.
To be able to do the
cycle and to keep going.
It's a necessary evil there.
And it may be interesting
to think about, there,
what was actually the first
steam engines looked like.
So if you want to think about
what engineering progress looked
like, you can look up
what that value was,
and maybe that helps you to
appreciate what 60 actually
looks like.
So making that more
concrete-- so again,
here, you can't run these
cycles without heat rejection,
so you've got a reservoir at
100 degrees C. Transfer it in.
You do some PV work out.
You have to bring that back
down to the initial stage.
In order to do that, you
have to transfer some heat
to the reservoir.
And again, that's boundary work.
But it's straightforward to
imagine if that was a shaft work
example too.
Coming back to sort of
an environmental context
of where we reject all
this heat to-- so this
is what's called
a sankey diagram.
So this is a diagram where--
they're really weird to read,
but they're left to right.
So you go left to right,
and the width of that stream
there indicates
more of something.
So here, you have, left
to right, fresh water
at the source, so that
could be groundwater,
river water, whatever.
And you have salt
water at the source,
so that can be like
the ocean, the sea.
And then you can
look where it goes.
So this comes out.
Most of it goes to some user.
Quite a lot of it is heading
towards the agricultural sector,
the public.
But you see here,
the number that's
even bigger than the than
the agricultural consumption
is that the majority
of the water
is passing through a
thermoelectric power plant,
so that means like
steam power plant,
like the things that you see.
And of course, we're not
consuming that, in a sense.
You take it, it passes
through the surface condenser,
and then it goes
back into the ground
or into the river, where
then perhaps it might
be used in agriculture.
So that's the
discharge part of it.
And then here in
agriculture, that's
actually consumed
because plants undergo
what's called transpiration.
They lose water vapor.
They evaporate it or use
it in growth as well.
But that part about
the discharge--
that water is no longer
at the same temperature
that it came in with.
So that water is warmer.
You're putting that back
into an environment,
and that also has consequences.
So if you start to
heat up river water--
just being-- for
us at home, it's
not as pleasant to probably
stay in an environment that's
too warm, and these things can
have damage and impact from it.
And it's not at some tiny scale.
It's at a scale of all of our
water that we use, or most of it
is at some point doing
something like that.
I hope you're sufficiently
motivated about steam power
plants in the dark here.
So then other-- so other systems
where we look at this analysis
with the reservoir there for
what's called refrigerators
and heat pumps, the
latter of which is how--
the current US plan
for decarbonizing
our heating-- residential and
commercial heating sectors
is this.
You take-- in a nutshell,
you take electricity.
You run a compressor or a pump.
You take some fluid.
It's called a refrigerant.
You bring it to a high pressure
and a high temperature.
You reject that heat.
So you reject that-- or
you transfer heat there
at that high temperature
into some surroundings.
If it's in your--
you have what are called--
what are they called?
Air heat pumps,
[INDISCERNIBLE] air heat pumps,
where you're more
or less rejecting,
let's say, heat into
the environment.
Then we go through
that expansion valve.
Remember that throttling
valve I talked before,
where we have a sudden
expansion, and then,
therefore, trading off PV
for an internal energy.
So this gets really cold, and
then you can cool some process.
That's how it looks like in
an air conditioning system.
That's more or less how
your refrigerator is.
So that would be your home.
That would be the outside.
What's interesting about
these systems for, let's say,
using them is when we
use them in reverse.
So if you run them in reverse,
you can actually take--
you can transfer heat, let's
say from a cold outside--
this is going to sound weird.
But you can transfer
heat from the outside
when it's cold into the
inside of your home.
And what's really
cool about this
is that when you're
transferring heat like that,
1 unit of electricity
consumed here in work
might equal 3 units of heat
transferred from the environment
into your home, and vice versa.
And that's really key.
That tells you exactly why you
would not do Joule heating,
like a resistor.
So if I had electricity
and I had a Joule resistor,
I could heat the air in
my home or the water.
That makes sense, right?
That makes sense,
and I would do it.
But this is a way where
you can take energy that--
you can take and
transfer thermal energy
from the environment outside
and get more bang for your buck.
And the bang is like a
factor 3, so this isn't
like some 60% thing, 45% thing.
This is like-- we're talking
factors of difference there.
And we'll go more
into that there.
But again, you sort of set up
the problem in the same way.
You have some
thermal reservoirs.
You treat this, then, a
as a closed system there,
and we do some analysis.
And there, we won't
talk about efficiency,
because efficiency of 300%
doesn't make any sense.
We call that coefficient
of performance.
Bringing it home, here, I'm just
going to give you some examples.
So the other thing about
the second law-- again,
about this temperature
differences that we were saying
about the tendency
of things to flow--
so again, this is this
video with the balloons.
So you have something at
high pressure and there,
and you release it, and it--
they move.
Believe it or not, this
video was made at MIT.
I find it hilarious
that an MIT professor
is making videos like that.
So great.
And they're nice videos.
You can learn a lot from
this-- from these links there.
This is that food dye example,
for those of you who have never
played with food coloring.
I do this on the regular.
So you put it in there, and then
you can watch it diffuse there.
And then there's the thermal
example where here, they
take a pan, they
put a really cool--
it's called thermochromic
liquid crystals.
These are things that change
color depending on the heat.
So you see here it's really hot.
And then you put it out
and you let it cool,
and you see it change
color, and you transfer.
So again, talking about things
that happen spontaneously--
so if it's something
that can happen,
it's something that's going
to be following the first
and the second laws
of thermodynamics.