I've got you ten, so
let's get started.
Welcome to ME 40.
If you're not in this
class, you can leave.
If you're not in
the class, you're
welcome to learn today
about thermodynamics.
Of course theme. So what
do we talk about
in thermo?
Energy, right? So
timely ones today,
we talk about the
conversion of it.
So you think about
photovoltaics, right?
This is, like, the most
fastly growing area
of energy systems.
Um, we think about
systems that are
consuming lots of
energy at the moment.
Think about data centers,
right, large language
models, right?
The third part of it is
because this is
intermittent,
we think a lot about
how we store energy.
So because of the fact
that we receive it,
we need to store
this and figure
out how to use this.
So this is basically
the theme of
our course, our team.
So, um, Cassie McCormick
is the head GSI.
I'm joined also by GSI
Jessica Woo here
and our reader,
Dear Baldwa, very
capable team.
These two are a member
of my research group,
and I've already
worked with Dear as
a reader last semester
for Emy winning 46,
so energy conversion
principles.
The point is, I think
you're in good hands.
You have a
motivated group,
a little about myself.
So I've been
teaching thermo
for the better
part of 11 years.
So I was overseas
for about ten years.
I taught at Ate Ha.
It's where Einstein
was a student,
a famously very
bad student.
So if you want to learn
anything about him,
you don't go
to Zurich, you
have to go to the
Capitol Bern.
You read a
little bit about
him and his stories,
there's two things
that are great.
Um, was about his
friendships, series
of friendships.
The first is he had
a friend who kind of
helped him get through
his courses because he
was bored to death.
They were teaching
the old physics.
He wanted to learn
about the newest kind
of friend gave him
notes and helped
him around.
Maybe helpful for
some of you here.
And the second thing
is that friend also
got him his first job
out of school, right?
So he got him a job
at the patent office.
And for those
who don't know,
that's where we
went to write on
basically his most
famous famous works
were there is his,
uh, apartments there,
but a coffee
shop in Burns,
you ever find yourself
there, it's very
beautiful walking
you kind of see.
And then when
you look from
that apartment
and you walk,
you can see what's
called a Glockenspiel,
basically a big clock.
And so you can get
this idea of walking
towards and away
from the clock
and maybe some
insight into what
he was thinking
about in a daily.
So not our tower,
but a big kind
of like a tower,
but a much bigger
clock on it.
See you Jess.
Learning objectives
for the course, right?
So we're going to talk
a lot about laws,
primarily the first
and second law there.
You're going to be able
to say this. So you
go to a party, talk
to some friends.
You say, this is
the first and
the second law. This is
how I think about it.
You're going to do some
simple single
answer problems.
I with first law,
first and second law,
and then we get into this.
So a lot of this is
sort of foundational.
Hopefully,
you stay with me
because after that,
you'll see the
utility of it.
You need much
bigger systems
and like the ones I
was talking about,
you know, before,
perpetual mobile.
So basically cycles
that violate, you know,
first and second law, and
then really get into
thermodynamic data.
So in this class, you
might have heard
about like tables.
I think you should
love fans there.
Okay, so that missed.
But the point is that
old school was that
you had a book.
Mostly why people
hate this kind
of class is that they
had to sit there,
look at this end of
the book appendix and
figure out things.
Here, we use Python,
right? We use module.
So I encourage
you from today,
if you don't feel
comfortable in Python,
which you should
because it's
a prerect to
this, learn this.
So we have homework
problems and stuff.
It's not
sophisticated Python.
I was raised on Fortran.
Does anyone know
Fortran is?
One, two. Okay, so
my hardcore
ones out there.
So everything
runs on Portrait.
You just don't know
it. But, you know,
I also taught myself
Python, right?
So if I can do it with
no class, surely,
you all are capable.
Our homework.
So some house scheme,
our homework's done
through a website
called Prairie Learn.
This is a fantastic
homework suite.
It's also how
we'll run all
of our assessments.
So the way that
you practice
on your homework
is going to be
exactly how you did
practice for assessments.
So if you haven't
already go and
enroll at this website,
look for ME 40.
I The way to see
the course in terms
of organization is
that we have
three modules.
First law, second law,
applications. That's it.
Okay? If this is like
the Tour de France,
these are flat stages.
You think, okay, I
did good in this.
I feel good.
This is the Pyrenees.
This is the Alps. This
is like pain, right?
This is, I'm not
going to lie to you.
This is like, you
know, this hurts.
If you can survive
that part of it,
from this point
on, everything is
basically very
straightforward, okay,
with the exception of
maybe chemical reactions
for mechanical
engineers myself,
chemistry I'm deeply
uncomfortable with.
But yeah, basically,
up until that point,
it's pretty
straight forward.
So it's kind of like
flat, a big mountain,
and maybe not
exactly downhill,
but maybe a bit
flatter there.
In the B courses, right?
So within each module,
we have pages.
On those pages, right,
we have to do
before lecture,
to do by the end
of the module,
and to read for that week.
And I can't emphasize
enough staying with
that analogy of the Tour
de France and cycling.
This is a class that is
very easy to
get behind on.
It's easy to
stay on track.
You just be disciplined,
you read, you do what
I tell you, you'll
be on track.
But if you don't, you
will fall behind,
and it is very difficult
to catch back up, okay?
So the main thing is,
like, for this week,
I want you to read
Chapter one. Read it.
Today, you go and
you read, and,
you know, you
basically get
ahead and it's do it.
The homework in each of
the modules is
released now.
So the first five
homework are there.
I encourage you to, like,
get through
that, especially
homeworks one,
two, and three.
Learn the Python
module for determining
properties.
Get comfortable with this.
It will serve you very
well when it comes time
to homeworks
four and five,
and especially
Quiz one, okay?
Okay.
Um, I record, so
I like openness,
so I already have
all the videos from
last year there.
I'll record all of
these and post them.
If we ever do discussions,
I don't record
discussions.
I think recording
and a discussion
tends to kind of
stifle it a bit.
So in my opinion,
don't I don't
record that, okay?
So if you want discussion,
be here, okay?
If you don't want to be
here, you're an adult.
You spent your money,
spent your parents money,
whatever, like, you want
to come or not, that's
up to you, okay?
You're an adult
and decide that.
What I will tell
you is sometimes
the visual audio
doesn't work, okay?
That camera, for example,
is turned like 40 degrees
too far to the left.
So today, I have
to keep the board
exactly here.
Sometimes the
batteries were not and
I'm replacing batteries.
It's not personal.
I'm not trying to,
like, you know,
create, you know,
some withholding
system like that.
Sometimes things
just don't work,
and I'm sorry for that.
And so I can't
upload them.
Okay, are there
any questions
about that before
I dive in?
One Mississippi to
Mississippi. Okay.
Cool. So, challenges
in decarbonizing.
So this article posted.
This is from
two years ago.
New York Times went
through and was
looking into sort of
the solution at
that time and
how we were dealing
with emissions.
And the way that you could
describe that is roughly,
we're just going
to plug it all in.
We're basically just
going to plug in
almost, you know,
everything.
So at that time,
that's now
four years ago, You know,
you typically
would distribute
things by sector.
So transportation is by
far the largest of it.
Industry, the
second, residential,
and then commercial.
If you look into
the transportation
part of it,
a lot of it's just
passengers, right?
In the United States,
who drive
everywhere, right?
I grew up in the Midwest.
It's not uncommon to do
5 hours just use why not?
You can just do that,
uh um, you know, there,
but also into
heavy duty trucks,
trains, right?
We have basically the best
freight rail in the world,
you know, here
for that, right?
You have other ones
that, if you look into
the industry,
chemicals, right?
These are things
that require high
process temperature,
process heat.
So things that are in
the news a lot now are
rare minerals, right?
Metals, right?
Copper is at the
highest price that
it's ever been in
history, right?
All of these
things require
refining and a
lot of energy,
a lot of a lot of um,
heat, steel, right?
These require a
lot of energy into
it to do it.
On the residential side,
the dominating thing is
space heat space
heating, right?
Berkeley in California
in general,
we're kind of blessed
with a lot of warmth,
but a good chunk
of the US and
the world is
not with that.
And so, you know,
big consumption
in natural gas,
um, They're also
into cooking.
And then the
commercial side,
it's kind of a
mix there largely
reflects what you
would see probably
on the residential side.
Some nomenclature
into this.
If you look at
the literature
and you read and
especially about energy
in a large scales,
you'll see things
like quad.
So a quad is 1
quadrillion British
thermal units.
I'm not going to tell
you what a BTU is.
I'm against it, but
it exists. You
can look it up.
The point is
that one BTU is
1055 joules there, right?
The joules and
Newton meter, okay?
So, how much of
that currently of
that makeup came from
electricity then,
right in transportation
in 2021,
very little was
electric in spite of
what you see and
you read, right?
A lot of it was still
a couple of years ago
just with gasoline.
On the chemical side, as
I mentioned, you
know, in the US,
you look also to
countries like
Germany and that,
where they have big
process industries.
A lot of that
is natural gas
and heating and
coal with it.
In space heating, right,
it's a larger size
of it is electric,
and that has to
do with the fact,
and what we'll go
over into this course
for what's called
heat pumps, right?
So the heat pump,
the beautiful thing
about a heat pump,
is that if I put in one
unit of electricity,
I can move three units
of heat with it, okay?
So that just makes
economic sense, right?
Like, by definition,
that's a very
efficient way to do
it versus a classical way
that I put one unit of,
let's say chemical
energy and I burn it,
I get one unit of
heat out of that.
You know, that's a
losing game for it.
So that's why
something like that
looks like it's
already developed.
Also because, again,
if I go back
to my Midwest,
a lot of buildings there
for historical reasons,
already have central
air conditioning.
So they already have
air conditioning systems.
A heat pump is nothing
but an air
conditioning system
run in reverse, okay?
So think about an air
conditioner, right?
I take heat in
the building and I
pump it out, right?
A heat pump is they
take heat from
the outside and I
pump it in there.
So infrastructure, and
we already have a lot
of solutions for
how to do that.
Okay? If you look at
20:50, and again,
this was a couple
of years ago in
the projections with it,
things were always getting
constantly more and
more efficient.
So you would
expect that the
overall consumption to
decrease And if you
look at the
different sectors,
things like space
heating, further adoption
into heat pumps,
better insulation in
buildings gets you there.
You think about
transportation,
passenger vehicles,
you know,
Teslas, right,
General Motors
doing a lot of
what they do
into their Chevy bolts.
The equinox, you'll
see around here, like,
a lot of those
vehicles are already
right electrified, so
that's straightforward.
But then you'll see
other things, right?
Notable one here
is aviation.
Does anyone know why we
are not going
to be able to
electrify like a
Boeing or an airbus?
The battery is
what? Heavy.
They're too heavy.
Fuel is also
kind of heavy.
Name and answer.
Kai.
Yes. Darn.
That's a specific
technical proposal,
maybe something you would
do right in deep space,
but wasn't working.
Other ideas?
I need a name
and then loud.
I need the
intensity higher.
The density of
energy dens of.
I think it's coming
to it. One more.
Battery charges.
Yeah. Yeah.
So charge times.
So if you think
about a cell phone
in charging,
how many years
can you go on
a cell phone before you
have to replace
your battery?
Five. That's
amazing. Okay.
So I'm probably at like
two into it, right?
So it's about 1,000
cycles, right?
You can basically do
about 1,000 cycles lithium
ion roughly there
before it's gone.
If you took planes and
you wanted to do that,
first of all, they'd be
massive batteries, right?
You can install
one and two,
you'd have to throw them
out every six months.
Like, gone, right?
So that's a very right?
So basically, that is
not there's other
ones that'll work.
You go to Alaska,
you want to go
into Cessna,
electrify that there.
Like there's
cases, but it's
not going to flying here,
Europe, here,
Australia, you know,
Asia and stuff.
Like, that's just
not current and
future looking at trends
with this, that's
not going to cut it.
And so the thing
is, like, how
does one do that?
Where I was before, people
who looked at
this seriously
were constructing
massive solar fields.
Like, in my old
building, we had
a big I mean,
it looked like an
old satellite dish.
The big ones, they
are a big old dish,
concentrated all the
sunlight into an area.
You fed it water, you fed
it CO two and
into a catalyst,
and you produce
methane out of it,
and basically they
produce fuel.
So like Swiss, that's
a big airlines
Switzerland,
and they're basically
we're buying from
a company Sin Helion and
stuff that we're looking
into this as a technology.
But pretty much, it's
like liquid fuel,
and you got to
figure out, like,
how you're going
to do that in
a sustainable way
because electrons,
you know, for that
reason and the
heavy reason and
the fact that
the batteries don't last
is not going to cut it.
The long haul trucking,
heavy duty stuff,
that's also
an area that's quite
difficult, right?
So that's just
an area where,
again, for the
same reason,
with batteries, you know,
semi trucks here drive
1 million miles, right?
Like, that's just,
like, not hard for
them to do several million
miles and with it.
And so for the
same reason there,
you have to think
about, like,
what's going to be a
potential replacement,
you know, there
into petroleum.
And on the
industrial side,
sort of the same
thing, like, how do
you get to these
high temperatures?
There's some
fantastic startups
in the area that look,
for example, and
Torres is one of them.
They take, um, Yeah.
I'm also not a
rich person.
I have no boards or
connection to any
of these companies.
So, like, basically, they
take photons, right?
So they take,
like, sunlight,
they produce electricity,
and what they
do is they just
heat up graphite.
They just heat up, like,
blocks of, you know,
I mean, almost
like coal, right?
They heat that
up really hot,
and those things can store
a lot of themal energy,
and then they basically
then circulate a
or fluid over that and
then use that there.
So that's kind
of like thermal
batteries and what's
done with it.
So the chemicals,
the aviation,
you know, in general,
like, shipping and stuff,
these are like three of
the most difficult to
decarbonize areas.
Yeah. Okay. I could
go on and on with it.
So that's one
factor, right?
And that's like looking
for a couple of years.
One thing that was, like,
unanticipated, right,
from a couple of years ago
and looking into it had
everything to do with
demand for compute, right?
So what I'm showing
you on this plot is
essentially a measure
of calculations, right?
Let's say
calculations that are
done by a computer
against year, right?
And this dashed line is
like frontier
compute models.
So, you know, chat,
Gemini, right?
So it's
sort of the most common
ones that are there.
The third thing
that's done is
showing The number of
graphical processing
units, GPUs,
these are basically
special kind
of processors that
are good for, like,
linear algebra and
machine learning
and the amount of power
that they draw, okay?
So like one GPU draws
about 700 watts, okay?
So what's a hairdryer?
Anyone know what
a hairdryer is?
I used to have really
long hair. I know this.
So it's about 1,000 watts.
So you can draw
the w about 1,200
watts from the wall there.
So, one GPU is basically
like a hairdryer
that's there.
So these models a
couple of years ago,
you had 10,000 of
those, all right?
Present day, those ones
now have 300,000 to them.
You look at like Elon,
what they have
in Tennessee,
Colossus, that's
about 100,000 GPUs.
They're looking at
a couple hundred
thousand and 1 million
in the near future.
So 25000-500 megawatts.
You look to like 2030.
So let's say we
follow this frontier
compute growth
trend there,
you're going to be
having a single
data center
that's drawing 10
gigawatts, okay?
So you don't have to
know what a gigawatt is.
I can tell you it's
as a very big number.
Okay. The second plot that
I'll show you is annual.
US Data Center energy use
in terawatt hours, okay?
So terawatt is
a big also a big a
pretty big number.
Basically, we use
about 14 globally,
something around like
ten to 20 terawatts.
It's pretty much what the
global capacity
for energy use.
And that's against
years, all right?
And so for a
number of years,
though, right,
things were very,
very flat, an inflection
point at about 20:20.
And again, you
know, various
sort of
projections, right?
This purple region is
sort of that mid level
of data centers.
Here is like the
ten gigawatt,
you know, level, okay?
This dot here, just to
give you reference as
to what this would mean,
was in 2021,
California's total
electricity generation.
So in a couple of years,
all of the
electricity that we
consume for data
centers will
exceed essentially
California's generation.
And it's the biggest
state, right?
Even like mid level
estimates, you know, okay?
Not the most conservative,
but mid level
ones that are that
are there, okay?
Um, Yeah.
And so just for reference,
then that's
like, you know,
4,000 terawatt
hours is what
the total US
consumption was.
So that number is then
about 10%, right?
So it is about 10%.
There are scenarios
where people
look and they
say about 10%,
right, which
would be up here.
At the extreme end.
10% of all electricity
consumption in
the United States
by 2030 is
going to be a Data
Center, right?
So, okay. And the
reason is this, right?
So that only happens
because there is
such a demand for compute
from anyone, okay?
So those are sort
of the two tails of
electricity that I see.
If you care about things
like this in the spring,
I'll be teaching
with my colleague,
Professor Zodi a
class essentially on
data center modeling and
energy management
system modeling.
So we'll go a
lot further into
sort of the specifics
of this and
the language and
what goes on.
In terms of,
like, careers,
there's roughly
about 3,000
jobs in this
country that need
somebody who
knows thermal and
really good
modeling for it.
So I think mechanical
engineering is
a very timely,
like, smart thing. Do.
A was also very good,
but I mean, there's
nothing that's,
like, in the news
more than that.
Okay? So there's that
the energy conversion,
decarbonizing, and
storage, okay?
So, but before
we get to that,
we got to learn to walk,
maybe to crawl, alright?
Um, Okay, so we're,
you know, really,
thermodynamics is
essentially about
starting with
drawing boundaries.
So we talked
really just about,
like, you know,
a box, okay?
Into this box, we
put, like, heat.
The box usually
has some mass.
We can put some
work into it.
We can basically take
some work out of it.
The boundary that we look
at here This can
basically grow.
This can shrink. It should
just sort of
contain whatever
else was had into it.
The other thing with
all of this is,
right, this is heat
in, this is workout.
Those are like processes.
A lot of times, if
we define sort of the
mass of this thing,
we'll talk about
properties
like temperature
and pressure,
and with that,
we'll be able
to say a lot of
things about it.
So this pretty much
talks about the state.
So let's begin with
our first one,
and I just want to make
sure that I can see.
Um, So as a beginning
point here,
we can talk about work.
So some basic
physics, right?
So our differential of
work here, let's say,
in a scenario like
that, it's going to,
let's say, if we have
a force that
we're applying.
Here's my dry eraser.
Okay, so let's say,
You know, maybe this
is like a piston.
So what's a piston?
A piston is
essentially like a
cylinder, right?
And at the other end,
anyone who's ever, like,
filled up a bike
before, you
know, a bike tire, right?
You go up and down, and
you compress the air.
So you have here,
like, a piston.
And this piston
could move,
you know, some
distance, let's say,
you know, you know, DS,
and maybe there's a force,
right,
that's being applied
that moves it up, right?
So this work
transferred is
nothing but that
force times
that distance, you
know, move, okay?
So that's sort of the
first thing that we
have as a definition
is that. Um, right?
The second thing
that I had
mentioned is that we're
largely concerned in order
to understand
these processes,
we're largely concerned
with what's called states.
To know a state, we
talk about properties.
So things like
temperature,
pressure, and
specific volume are
three of the most,
let's say,
important three of
the most important ones
that are that are there.
Okay, to define
a process here.
So let's say this is
at something
like state one.
If I were to look
at this, and I let
that piston head expand to
a higher, you know,
position inside here,
I can talk again
about a temperature,
a pressure, a
specific volume,
and that's a state two.
And pretty much the
whole class is about,
you know, stringing
together, like,
really defining
figuring out
the properties that we
know about the problem,
defining them the state,
and then from that moving
to another state,
all right?
And the outputs of
that are things like
work or heat, okay?
Cool. Let's move.
This is also the cleanest
I've ever seen the white
boards in this room.
They're not going
to look this good
again for the rest
of the semester.
All right. Okay.
Okay, so let's
now consider
instead of our piston,
though,
let's consider another
experiment, right?
So in this experiment,
let's say we have,
you know, a ground
here, okay?
We have a weight.
Let's say that
the weight has
a mass Omega.
Let's say that this
weight is attached to Oh,
man, I'm so bad
at drawing.
Right, attached to
a pulley, okay?
Okay. Basically,
it's attached
to, like, a pulley,
and maybe this
pulley has some kind
of crank and
we can use to,
um, All right,
textual pulley, should
look like that.
The crank that we
can use to, like,
rotate and lift that up.
And let's say we do that.
So we have some
external actor
that's out here that
starts cranking
this and lifts it, right?
This is then going
to be brought up.
Let's see to some
height here.
Let's say initially we
have some supporting
surface here,
and then we move that in,
and we rest it
there, right?
And then the height
that we have for
this displacement
is then age.
So we have a
surface S here,
a weight here, a
pulley, you know,
someone literally turning
a crank to raise that up.
This initial state here,
we'll call it state one.
This other one here
we'll call as,
um, state two, okay?
And the reason
why we're able
to move that is right
there is someone
who's outside here
who's transferring that
work in to move it up.
We could also consider
a scenario here where
we let it go back
down to one, right?
And in order to let
that go back down,
we'll also, you
know, have to be
applying sort of a
force resisting,
you know, that
movement back to
the surface so that it's
done slowly, right?
And if we look at
going 1-2 to one,
we can talk about
the change in
the work, right?
And that complete
integral there,
right is then equal
to zero, right?
Because we took
this thing.
We lifted it up to a
height very slowly, right?
We didn't do anything
where there was a
lot of friction.
And then we basically
released it,
brought it back down
very slowly to that.
So we did work
to transfer up,
and then we
received work or
transferred work out
then when it went there,
and the result of that of
one to two to
one is we have
no change in work, okay?
Okay.
Times that.
Cool. All right.
So we can do
this experiment.
A similar experiment
again of,
like, raising and
lowering weights.
And the point this time,
let's say this is our
weight, which is here.
Let's say this goes
up again to a pulley.
So we have some
pulley here, right,
where we're, you know,
wrapping our rope around.
This is then going into
um, a container here.
Let's say this container
is full with liquid.
Let's say we can measure
the temperature inside
here with a thermometer.
And instead of, right,
transferring this work,
let's say, you know,
out of the system
into what might
be like, potential energy,
maybe there's another
weight out here that
you're lifting
and lowering.
In this case, what
we'd like to do is
to dissipate that
with a break, right?
So this is basically
a break here, okay?
And so if we do,
let's say, um, um,
If we were to
take this from,
let's say, like, a state
one, which is here,
and then we lower
that down, you know,
let's say, you know,
some distance.
Let's say that distance is
then, you know,
something like,
you know, something
like the H that we had
there, we'd have
that process.
Okay? So we can
go one to two
with that. All right.
So you would take this,
you release some energy.
That'd be transferring
to the b.
And the result of that
is that you would heat
up the fluid here, right?
And so my question is,
how do you return?
So if I, again, release
the potential energy,
I heat up the water here,
how do you return
back to state one?
No. Okay. That's
it, right?
So to go back, you
need to cool, right?
To get back to state
one there, right?
And what should
be clear from
this case is that if we
go one to two to one,
this integral,
right, that we had
written before,
it's not equal
to zero, right?
This is what we would
call essentially
an irreversible process,
or you've done
something and you can't
get it back, okay?
And People like Joule,
so who the unit of
energy is named after
did a lot of experiments
that were like
this, right?
So a lot of
experiments like
that where you raise
and lower the heat,
or especially this type,
where you lower
a weight, okay?
So, you know, you
take, you know,
some change, let's say,
an energy, and
you produce it.
You know, you
transfer that then,
you know, and generate
heat in a system, right?
In the 19th century,
this was, like,
a big problem.
People used to take,
like, cannon bores, right?
And they would, you know,
try to bore them out.
And at that time, people
didn't really
understand what he was.
They thought it was
called caloric theory.
They thought it flowed,
you know, like water,
basically, um, um, you
know, flows there.
And so these were,
like, deep questions
that they were,
you know, concerned
with was the
mechanisms and
what went on.
And so what Jewel did
is through like
a series of,
like, weights and
lowering them
different heights,
and then measuring the
change in temperature,
what he showed was that,
um, dq, which stands
for heat, right, minus.
So this is heap in
minus the
complete integral
of work transferred out
was then equal
to zero, okay?
This is called sometimes
the mechanical
equivalent of
heat, all right?
So it may be
obvious to us now,
but again, I can't
emphasize enough that,
like, people used to
think that it was
like he was a
substance, all right?
Um, This is one statement
of the first law of
thermodynamics, right?
So I you know,
one way to look at
the first law is
that energy is conserved.
So if I take all of
the net heat right
into this system,
you know,
doing that whole
process and all of
the network that's
transferred out of that,
the difference
between that for
a closed system
like that should be
equal to zero, okay?
So yeah, essentially,
this is first law.
All right. Okay.
This is good.
I want to bring
back my one.
I promise a lot better
board management
once my camera gets fixed.
Alright? Okay.
Okay, so now let's
consider the following.
Let's say that we
have a state zero,
which is here, and let's
say this is a
state one, okay?
And let's say that we
have a process of going
from state one to
state zero, which
we'll call A.
And we'll consider
two trips back, okay?
Let's say the direct way,
and let's call path C
the scenic route, okay?
That was a dead joke.
All right, fine.
Scenic drone. Okay.
Um. All right.
So from a statement
that we have there,
what we can
write then is in
the integral from one A
to zero of dq minus dw,
plus the integral then
of zero B to one.
So zero B to one of
dq minus dw is equal
to zero. All right?
Now, we can consider
the same thing,
but a return trip as,
again, the scenic
route, right?
So we have one A to
zero dq minus dw,
plus the integral
of zero C to
one of dq minus dw, right?
And so if we combine these
two, these two terms,
this is going to subtract,
and so this term and
this term are going
to be equivalent, right?
So our integral of
zero to one B of our
dq minus dw is equal to
zero C to one
of dq minus dw.
Yeah. Okay. So let's
move that one there.
Let's bring it back.
Yeah. Okay. So.
So the integral of
basically the
difference of
dQ and minus dw
is essentially fixed by
the endpoints, all right?
Yes, please. Go ahead.
Heat. It's like
heat transfer.
So Q and thermodynamics
is heat transfer.
Other questions?
Clarifications? Yes, please.
Name Zach.
No, this should just
be one. I'm sorry.
So one is the start.
I apologize. Thank you
for catching that.
Okay. This should
be zero B, yes.
You get up here
and I don't know
what happens.
Suddenly, like letters
change. I'm not kidding.
Okay. Other questions?
Okay. Thank you.
All right. All right.
So the point is that
and I'll get
into it later,
but the point of
this is that this dQ
minus this DW all I need
to know to have this
is essentially the final
and the initial
states, okay?
And the same then for
the other process, okay?
So what we can write
then is that E one,
so let's call
that energy in
the system minus E
zero is then the
integral 0-1 of
dq minus dw,
which is then equal
to Q minus W, right?
So this is basically
the energy
right in the system
at state one.
This is the energy in
the system at state zero.
Q is the heat transferred
into the system,
and W is the work
transferred out, okay?
In mechanical
engineering and
thermal here, that's
the convention.
If you see Q, and it
doesn't say in or out,
it is positive when
you transfer in,
and W is positive when
it's transferred out.
And the reason
for that is if
you think about
a power plant,
you put heat into it
and you get work
out of it, right?
That's the way to
remember. If you go
to physics, They're weird.
Sorry. And they do things
differently, all
right? Okay.
All right, so we can
take the differential
of this, right?
So then we can talk about
D, right being equal
to dQ minus R dw.
And this is what
I would say is
a very common
way that you'll
see the first law written.
So the change in
the energy of
your system is equal
to the change and
the amount is equal to
the amount of heat
transferred in minus
the amount of work
transferred
out, all right?
Okay.
Were to also go with this.
We generally don't care
about the absolute
amount of energy, right?
If we care about
a process, like
I mentioned before,
you care about difference.
If you went in
and you wanted
to tally up all the
energy in something,
right, you'd have to
talk about, you know,
your kinetic
energies, your
potential energies,
any magnetism,
capillarity, and whatever
that goes into it,
it gets exhausting, right?
Um, Again, as an engineer,
you don't really care
about the absolute value,
but you do care about
the difference, right?
So go from something hot
to cold, that's there.
That's something that's
going to be done.
And so what you'll do is
you'll talk about
a reference state.
So when we get into
properties,
you'll say, okay,
here is
some arbitrarily chosen
reference state.
We all agree on it, like
we all agree on
the time for
whatever reason in the UK
that we have GMT zero.
We accept that
in the same way
in our tables in
our calculations,
there's going to be
some reference value,
and we compute property
changes in and
around, um, that, okay?
So again, there's
no absolute value.
Well, there could be
an absolute value
of what we call here
is internal energy.
But again, we don't care.
That's not questions
that we ask
in this in this
class, okay?
Um, okay.
This is a property, right?
Internal energy
is a property.
If I know the
temperature and
the pressure or
the specific volume
of my system,
I know the
internal energy,
okay? It's a property.
Heat and work, I cannot
stress this enough,
are not properties,
right? They're not.
You know, you
transfer heat in,
you transfer
work out, okay?
When we think about
the, you know,
the and where
you transfer it
in and out are at
boundaries, right?
So you look at, you
know, let's say, again,
back to our piston
example, Right?
So, if this is,
let's say, the, you know,
what I define as the
boundary of my system,
you'd be transferring heat
in at that boundary.
You'd be transferring work
also out of that, okay?
What you'll see in
the textbook to
drive this home,
the fact that this
is not a property,
is that this D, a lot of
times will be written
as like a Delta, okay?
And this Delta,
what it means
is it's an inexact
differential.
What the hell does
that mean for us?
It means you need to
know the process.
Like, you need
to know every
single little
change there.
You have to have
complete information
about it in order
to integrate.
I'll make it clear
later how we do that,
but that's why
they'll write
delta in the textbook.
Again, because
internal energy,
this is a property, and
the properties
only depend on
the starting and
the end states.
You have an exact
differential
for that, a D, okay?
Cool. To, to do.
So what you should
not write, let's
see if we stick with
our example there,
you should not
write W zero.
You should not
write W one.
That doesn't make sense.
But something
like maybe w01,
that might make
sense, right?
Because that's a process
between two states.
The same might be said
of something like
third quarter
one there, okay?
Great. Yeah.
Okay, so again, this
is just some basics.
Again, I'll try to
make this exciting,
and we'll connect
it back to I mean,
I think this's super
exciting, but, like,
we'll connect it back
to the rest later.
But again, in every
thermal problem,
the most important thing,
the very first
thing you should
do is to draw a boundary.
You look at a system and
your first reaction
on a quiz or a test,
is you draw
a nice picture,
better than what
I've done here.
I know you're
capable, and then
you draw the boundary
to it, right?
And what we
call that here,
so we draw that boundary,
the area contained in it.
The term is the
control volume, right?
And again, the
whole purpose
of this course
is looking at
the ways that
we can exchange
energy in and out of
the control volume.
For this, we're
looking at heat
in and out, work
in and out.
Later on, when we think
about data centers,
when we think
about turbines,
when we think about that,
we're also going
to be able to
bring in a fluid, right?
We're going to
be able to bring
in mass in and out,
and that's the third
way that you can
exchange energy
there, okay?
Great. What else
am I missing?
We're doing super
today. We're like,
amazingly on time.
You guys are a
great group.
Okay, so I've exhausted
my notes on all that.
So I just have some
closing remarks then,
and then I can
release you all
early to go to
your homework one,
two, and three before,
you know, next lecture.
So, this is a quote from
a very famous
German professor
Arnold Sommerfeld.
So first statement,
you know,
thermo is a funny subject.
The first time you
go through it,
you don't understand
it at all.
The second time
you go through it,
you think you
get it except
for one or two parts.
The third time you
go through it,
you know you don't
understand it,
but by that time,
you're used to it
and it doesn't bother
you anymore, okay?
So anyways, he was
very famous. He
was very famous.
He himself didn't win
any Nobel Prizes,
but a bunch of his
students, you know, did.
Maybe they didn't
need it three
times to take it.
So this is where you
are sort of today,
you're going through it.
You know, by the end
of this, hopefully,
you know, you'll
be ready for
the next part there.
Thank you all today.
Great turnout.
If you have any questions,
I'm up here for the
next few minutes.
I'm looking forward
to the semester.