So I'm going to get
started. So today we're
talking about
pure substances.
Before I get into that, at
some point in
the near future,
please go on to
prairiet.prairietest.com,
and please log in.
They told me to
tell you that.
So yeah, that way,
basically, you're
registered and exist.
You exist, but then
you will exist,
alright? Thank you.
Um, So Goa, today,
we're going to talk about
the concept of
pure substance.
We already kind
of gave you
a brief explanation
before.
We're going to do
some illustrations on
some diagrams that we're
going to use a lot
during the semester.
And then we're
going to come
up with some
procedures for
how we determine
thermite properties.
I'm going to teach
the hand tool, right?
And then I'm going to show
you the power tool, okay?
And hopefully at
the end of this,
while you will appreciate
the hand tool,
you will only use
the power tool,
hopefully in this class.
Okay, pure
substances, again,
sort of a review.
So it's a pure substance.
I'd like to talk
about it in terms of
these examples.
It's useful for me.
So a pure substance
here would be something
like nitrogen, right?
Pure nitrogen, air, right?
So, all right, air,
right, is mostly nitrogen,
but you also have some
oxygen in it, right?
But there's
nothing condensed.
There's no
condensed phases.
There everything is
basically gaseous.
Another example of a pure
substance would
be like water,
and this could
be water that's
coexisting between
its different phases.
So we get a vapor and
liquid liquid and solid,
you know, solid and vapor,
but no other components.
As soon as we
start to create
multi species,
multiphase things.
So if I took,
for example, you
know, a balloon.
If you took a
balloon filled
with air that I
blew it up with,
and I started to put that,
you know, into
liquid nitrogen.
Oxygen will condense
out of that.
So I'll end up
having a condensed,
let's say oxygen
phase there.
You know, and then
next to a nitrogen,
you know, next to
a nitrogen, you
know, vapor,
and in that case, it's
not a pure substance.
As I say it out loud,
it sounds kind
of complicated.
If it sounds pretty
complicated,
you know, probably
is not pure, okay?
But again, these
are some examples.
The most important
one that we're
going to deal
with right for
the majority of
this class is
pretty much
this situation,
either this
situation of, like,
air or this situation
of water, okay?
All right. So phases.
So we talk about phases
of of a pure
substance, right?
This can be a solid,
a liquid and a gas.
So the gas, we've
talked a lot
about, especially
ideal gases,
which are, you know,
they're like billliard
balls here, right,
liquid you know, if we
start with the gas,
the most, you
know, let's say,
um, you know,
random and moving one
here towards a
liquid, right?
The difference is
that you start to
have molecules that
attract each other, okay?
That's what
separates the liquid
from the gas, right?
So this is actually
the most complicated,
let's say, of the three.
And then if you
decrease the
temperature further,
you'll end up with
a solid, right?
And classical example of
how to visualize a solid,
what makes a solid
different from a
liquid in a gas, right?
The atoms are in
a lattice and
within that lattice,
they do not move, right?
They're fixed,
a little bit of
time out, right?
So, you know, here's
where you are and you
don't you don't move.
You know, position.
Okay. But they are allowed
to vibrate, right?
So the way that, you know,
Einstein
visualized this is
he saw it as like
springs, right?
So if I take, like, a
bunch of these atoms in
position and I connected
them via springs,
that ability to
oscillate then,
you know, would
allow it to
then store energy, okay?
So it stores it
through vibration.
Um, This type
of solid here
that I'm drawing
is called actually
it's called the
Einstein solid, right?
And the development
of this, this kind of
fun little cartoon here
was a very
important step in
the history of quantum
mechanics, right?
So one important result
at the time, you
know, this is like,
early 1900s is in,
you know, classical
mechanics and stuff.
You know, in their models,
they said the specific
heat was a constant.
It didn't depend
on temperature.
Awesome. Thank you. I need
more there's people
after me, I assume.
So thank you.
We're like the
buddy now, right?
Actually, they're
not Yeah,
they're not
energizers, though.
Okay. Anyways,
right, so, you know,
but the point is
that in reality,
the specific heat did
depend upon
temperature, right?
And so to explain that,
he came up with
this model.
And what's neat about it
is that in order
to get that,
essentially, you're
quantizing, right?
So basically, um, Also
around that
time, Max Plank,
you know, it had already
sort of stumbled on and
it quantized to avoid
the UV catastrophe.
Einstein took a bit
of that and then was
able with this kind of
nice model to predict
how specific heat
depends on temperature.
And then after that,
he did his
photoelectric effect.
And then, you know,
after that, those are
basically two pillars
of quantum mechanics.
Okay?
So thermodynamics, you
know, was, let's say,
one third one third of
one half of that
sort of development,
okay, which then
went much later.
Okay. Okay, so,
right, gases,
liquids, solids,
when we look at
phase changing,
this is very
important for us.
So think about, you
know, boiling of water.
We think about, you
know, right now,
I'm sweating a little bit.
It feels like a
human. I don't know.
Anyway,
so I'm not evapating
enough apparently.
But the point is that
right a lot of these,
you know, prostates
are very important.
The way to view
this, okay,
let's say we have
a state one.
So, you know, we
have a pressure.
It's like, 1
atmosphere in 20,
um, you know, see.
So let's say this
is, you know,
water there,
then it's going to
be as a liquid.
We start to heat
it up towards 100.
At some point around
there, you know,
we're going to
start to vaporize,
we start to heat it up.
So this is going to
go from here and
it's going to
become hot, okay?
It's going to
become a liquid.
And then at some point, as
we start to introduce
more heat there,
we start to
evaporate, okay,
maybe even boil some
of that liquid.
And, right, because
the gas there
is about 100 times
less dense than
the liquid,
you expect
expansion, right?
You know, and
then beyond that,
continue to add heat
in which you need
a lot of it,
right to boil off
all this liquid.
Eventually, you
end up with,
you know, a vapor,
saturated vapor.
And then after
that, you know,
we get into a
very hot vapor,
which we call
wet for water.
Louder. Steam. Yeah, it's
basically end up
with steam, okay?
But the volume, the point
is that the volume, right,
is increasing from left to
right in this
process. Okay, one.
Two, um,
If I take for a pure
substance, right?
So one post load
is if I take for
a pure substance two
independent properties,
I will be able to
then determine
a third dependent
property, right?
We showed this a lot
with the ideal gas.
Are you thinking
about ideal gas?
PV is MRT.
If I know P and V,
RPV is RT there.
Red if I know P and V,
then basically I
know, temperature.
Sort of a a simple case.
But it also works out for,
um, for water, too, right?
And so here
this is a three
dimensional representation
of that, okay?
So what does it
mean to have
with two independent
properties,
the ability to compute
a third dependent
property,
that means there's
a surface, right?
Basically, I
have a surface,
right, where I'd be able
to then, you know,
with these two,
let's say, independent on
that surface that exists,
the dependent
property, right?
Um, This is what Gibbs.
So Gibbs was
obsessed with.
If you're taking
calc three, right,
multidimensional calculus,
that was developed
for this, okay?
It was developed
basically for
this because not
only do you know,
let's say, the
pressure, I know
a specific volume
and temperature,
therefore, no pressure.
But if I start to
take derivatives,
at that point, I
get other things.
I will determine my
other properties there.
So it's very, um,
it's a very important,
um, you know, thing.
So again, the
point is that in
this case, you
know, the map,
so here, here, and let's
say I end up at
this case, right?
This type of
representation.
So apparently,
Maxwell, so,
you know, of
Maxwell's equations,
apparently like this a
lot and I guess tried
to make up a version
of this to, like,
give to Gibbs.
So a gift. So
Thermot and Amesis
apparently also
give gifts.
And, so Maxwell had made
up kind of a
three D mockup of
this kind of a surface
here to the right?
But yeah, like I said,
as soon as you can
have two of these things
for a pure substance,
and you find yourself
on that surface,
you know everything,
everything about
the state.
Okay, what are key
points on this?
So if we want to
orient ourselves
because this is kind
of complicated.
The one that you
should all know
from chemistry is
the triple line.
So what's the triple
line or triple point,
right? It where ice.
So the solid,
the liquid in
the vapor can coexist.
So that's here.
The second important point
is what's called
the critical point.
We'll go into
this a little bit
more today, the
meaning of it.
And then for
this class, sort
of the three phases
or the three regions
that we're most
concerned with
are this liquid,
the liquid vapor and
the vapor, all right?
So I can kind of
crop that out.
So if I crop out
that, let's say,
the icy region there
or the solid region,
we can start to
make some of
the PV and PT or VT
diagrams, right?
So how do I look
at this plot?
So this is for water.
So P and V, right?
So this is basically a
cut in this plane in
the PV plane along here.
Um, What's in
the dark line
here is the liquid
vapor region, the
saturation line.
That's this kind of
parabolic upside down,
you know, parabolic line.
Here again, you're slicing
you're basically
slicing through that.
So that's the line
that you see.
Alright. One, two, we
have isolines, right?
So if I were to
make, um You know,
if I were to
basically look
as a projection of,
in this case,
instead of a slice,
if I did a projection
of PV and I just
look from this direction
towards it, right,
we'd see these kinds of
different isolines,
which are here, right?
The one that's denoted in
this case is the
triple line.
So this kind of
dash line that you
see here and shoots
up is the triple.
I also have it
over 200 Celsius,
300 Celsius all the way
on up until the
critical point.
What you'll see in
terms of the
regions, right?
This is vapor to vapor,
vapor liquid to
vapor liquid,
and then liquid, which
is, which is there.
And again, the
critical point,
which I'll discuss
in a second, right?
And as usual, if you want,
you can generate
all these plots
from that script, right?
Um, This is the
TV diagram.
So if we look then
from this perspective,
so the top view,
basically.
So if we took,
like, a top view
perspective of
this plot, again,
we'd still get
the same dome,
and then our isolines
are then our isobars,
right, lines of
constant pressure.
So here's the triple line
at a very low, you know,
some hundreds of pascals
there all the way on
up until the critical
point for water, right?
And again, vapor liquid,
and then liquid.
And then the final one is
then the PT diagram.
All right. And this
is important, okay?
So if I look from
this perspective.
So if I'm looking
from temperature on
the horizontal axis
pressure on the vertical,
this kind of vapor
liquid region that
we see here looks
like a line, okay?
It looks like
a line, right?
And so if I start
to draw the ochres,
so the lines of
constant volume, right,
when I'm in the vapor
region, you know,
out, you know, here, it
kind of makes sense.
I see them different.
But as soon
as I get to the
liquid vapor region,
right, they
collapse, right?
And why is that?
Okay? Why is that?
It's because when I
go from a liquid,
which is here, I have
very low specific volume,
right? I'm dense.
I have very low
specific volume.
When I go to my vapor,
I have very high
specific volume.
I have I have
low density, you
know, with that.
And when I look from
this perspective,
I just see a line.
So I have a huge jump in
specific volume
when I go from
my liquid to my
vapor, all right?
Um, Why does that matter?
So, who cares?
Why am I telling
you about that?
Because if I know
my temperature and my
pressure, all right?
I told you before,
pure substances with
two independent
properties,
I know everything, right?
The only caveat I'm
going to give it to
you is that when you're in
the liquid vapor region,
temperature and pressure
are not enough, okay?
In the liquid vapor
region, you know,
you need to know
specific volume
and pressure or
and temperature, right?
And it has to do
with the fact
that when I
boil something,
it's going to boil
with constant
pressure, right?
You make brilla, you
know, at home, you know,
pasta at home, and it
gives you directions,
you boil, okay?
And you do it for that
it's super repeatable.
That's why it's an
instruction on there,
right?
The temperature is also
constant during
that process.
So that whole process
of basically going from,
let's say,
the full liquid at
the boiling point.
So a saturated liquid,
I'll come into what
that means in a second,
all the way to being
completely evaporated.
So a saturated vapor,
the temperature and
the pressure are constant.
But obviously,
something is changing.
The specific volume of
that mixture is
changing, okay?
So you can use
the, you know,
so when you're liquid,
when you're vapor, when
you're above the
critical point, right?
Any two of these pairs is
enough for you to map out.
But I want you to
think about this
when you say, okay,
when I have a saturated
liquid vapor mixture,
you think back to this
beautiful, you know,
Maxwell, you know, looking
carved solid here,
and you would
say, okay, look
at the side view
here, right?
I know that PNT is not
enough because there's
a whole bunch of states
into the page there,
you know, where,
you know, so
it's not enough
information to it, okay?
I feel like I
confused you all,
but it will make sense
with time. Go ahead.
Are there any
other regions
where two aren't enough?
So, you look at this.
Basically, if you look at,
um, you know, the
diagram here.
I would say that
this is the
only one that I
know of where
you have that,
you know, well,
it's not the only one,
right, because you
can also have
a solid vapor,
you know,
coexistence with the
same sort of thing,
right?
You basically go from
the low density of that,
but aside from
that, you know,
if you look at then
solid liquids depending on
the density of the
phase transition.
But for the purposes
of this class,
it's the coexistence
of the liquid in
the vapor region where
you have this
challenge, okay?
But specific volume,
you cannot go wrong.
Specific volume, you know,
you're not going
to go wrong, you
know, with that, okay?
Yes, please.
Name, by the way.
Sorry, I'm. David.
I do not have plasma
on this plot.
The fourth phase. Yeah.
Okay. Cross over
to, you know,
your physics
building for that.
Other questions?
Okay. Yes. So how
does the book denote this?
So what did I tell you?
I told you about
vapor, liquid vapor,
liquid, and I mentioned
a critical point.
And so that's
the terminology
that I like, okay?
The book has other names.
So this region, so I
show you the TV
diagram, right?
So very high density or
low specific volume
high density.
So you have a liquid.
The book a lot of times
calls this, like,
a compressed liquid
region, okay?
All right? I don't know.
Anyways, it's a
liquid, right?
It's very hard to
compress actually
a liquid, right?
It's like
compressing a solid.
You can't really
make the atoms much,
you know, a lot
of times it's
incompressible, as
we call it, right?
So you have compressed
liquid, All right.
So the next one is
that, again, this dome.
So we call this a dome.
To the left of the
critical point,
we call this as a
saturated liquid line.
What does it mean?
If you're anywhere
on this line,
it means that you are
a pure liquid, okay?
At the critical point
to the right here,
we have what's called
the saturated vapor line.
The way to
visualize this is
you've just boiled off
that absolute last amount
of liquid into
a vapor, okay?
Saturated vapor, alright?
Um, region in between
it and it is a saturated
liquid vapor region.
The way to visualize
this is almost like
percent evaporated
of the substance.
So zero as I have
0% evaporated,
so I'm a saturated liquid.
To here, I have
100% evaporated,
so I'm the the pure vapor.
And then to the
right of this is
what's called the
superheated vapor region,
which for water is Steam.
Steam. It's basically
steam steam here, okay?
And a lot of times on the
plots, too, so
additionally,
you see lines, and
these lines are
normally denoted
some constant value.
So if I'm plotting
temperature in
specific volume,
this is going to
be an isobar.
So lines of
constant pressure.
You see in the phase
change region,
so the saturated
liquid vapor region,
that the temperature
is constant.
So the pressure
is constant and
the temperature is
constant, okay?
Just like we had
said before.
And then the same thing
with the PV diagram.
So we have the isobars
are which are
temperature, okay?
Okay, so what is
this critical point,
alright? Is there
a question?
This is like the globe.
I don't care what
you call it,
as long as you can get
yourself there, okay?
We get different names for
different countries and
whatever and languages.
So as long as you
like, you know,
are at this GPS coordinates
in flatland here,
then well, curve
flatland's enough
for me, okay?
All right. Other
questions?
That's a fair question.
Okay, so what's
the meaning
of this critical
point, alright?
So we can talk about this.
So imagine so
let's say I'm at
this temperature,
you know,
down here, and let's
say that I'm uh um,
you know, and we
analyze this line.
So here, right?
The specific volume
is pretty low,
okay, when I'm a liquid.
And then when I'm a vapor,
the specific volume
is pretty high.
The difference
between them is
relatively large,
all right?
Now I start to move
up in temperature.
The liquid specific
volume it's higher,
and the vapor specific
volume is lower.
And this continues on
and on until
you reach up to
this point where
the difference
in the specific volume,
the difference in
the density
between the liquid
and the vapor cannot
be detected anymore, okay?
You cannot differentiate
between them, all right?
Does anyone know what
we call that fluid?
Say it again?
I can't hear.
Sorry. Liquid vapor?
No, not liquid vapor.
What do we call
that substance?
Okay,
it's called a supercritical
fluid, all right?
And you can ask
yourself, who cares
about a
supercritical fluid?
Um You're too young
to care about this,
but maybe when
you're older,
you want to drink
decaffeinated coffee
because I don't
know, you're wild.
The way that you
decaffeinate
coffee is you use
carbon dioxide and you put
it to a high temperature
and a high pressure.
You make it super
critical, right?
It turns out it's
great solvent for
things like that.
For power plants, when
you want to get to,
like, to be very,
very efficient,
which means
to run at very
high temperatures.
You know, they're for
water. You can heat
water also above this
critical point, right?
To get to basically at
higher temperature and
pressures to more
efficiently,
you know, generate
it, okay?
This is not you know,
like a fourth
phase of matter.
It's still a fluid, but
it's a fluid
where you cannot
differentiate
between a liquid
and a vapor, right?
They can't be
distinguished.
Um, The type of
phase transition.
So if I start off,
we'll start off
with the first one.
So if I started
with this type of
transition where
I go from, like,
a liquid to a vapor,
we call that as
a first order
transition, right?
It's a big change
in the density
from being one to
the other, right?
It's called first
order. 1 second.
When we talk about
this one going from
a critical point,
and then I'm down.
So if I started at
a high temperature,
let's say constant
specific volume,
and I start to
decrease there,
that's a second order
transition, okay?
And if you want to
read more about that,
there's beautiful
theories of Lev Landau.
He was a phenomenal
Soviet physicist
who did a number
of things,
but also looked
at these sort
of what are called
second order,
um, you know, transitions.
And the way you visualize
it is that, again,
you start out with
very small differences
in the density or
specific volume,
and then basically
they linearly
get larger. Yes, please.
So is that site
more of a smart?
Does it have more of
the properties of
a fluid or more of a gas?
It's a fluid, okay?
And a gas and a
liquid are a fluid.
Okay? So I said liquid,
and I said gas.
A liquid and a gas
are both fluids.
Okay. Other questions.
Read about Lando.
Very interesting.
Actually died very
young. It was tragic.
He won a Nobel
Prize, though.
Okay. Um, Okay, yeah,
so we talked about
basically this critical
point where, again,
you can't
differentiate between
the liquid and the vapor.
So the PV diagram.
We'll use this one
a lot, especially
later on with some cycles.
PT diagram, not really
used very much.
The only reason I show it
here is because, right?
Most substances would
look like this,
but water is a
tremendously weird, very,
very weird substance,
where the ice is less,
you know, its solid
phase is less
dense than it's
it's liquid, okay?
So basically, that's
the one where
it bends backwards,
and we'll use this a
little bit later in,
like, we, um, 13.
We want to
estimate, you know,
how much energy it takes
to evaporate. Okay.
Alright, that's all done.
We'll come for
a second now.
So again, so again, pure
substances, two
independent properties.
You know, we can compute
the dependence and
everything after that.
Um, The hand tool.
So the old
fashioned way to do
this is the
property table.
So here you have 34 of
them at the back
of your book.
If you were to
pick one of these,
let's say table A four,
so saturated water and
temperature table.
What you'll see here is
right temperature with it,
the pressure
associated with that,
and then things like
saturated liquid,
saturated vapor,
because remember, the
density will vary
continuously from being
the liquid to the vapor,
saturated liquid
internal energy,
and so on and so forth
with that, okay?
So again, you have
your temperature
as one of them.
The corresponding
saturation
temperature or pressure
your specific volume of
your liquid and your
specific volume
of your vapor,
okay? Why is it F?
It's not F because
it's fluid.
It's F because
it's fluykit,
okay, which is German
for liquid, all right?
The Germans did all
this, all right?
So not my fault, okay?
So the F there, again,
if you want to go and
do an old school,
you know, and use
a saw by hand,
I respect that.
It's going to
take a long time,
but that's the F, okay?
The saturated
vapor is G, okay?
And the G is then
all the properties
of saturated vapor,
and gas east gas.
Gas is gas, okay, in
both of them, right?
So you'll see
things like VG,
right, which is then
the specific volume
of the vapor.
F, specific volumes
of the liquid,
and sometimes
you'll see the
difference reported.
Sometimes you'll see FG,
and that's nothing but
specific volume of the gas
minus the specific volume
of the liquid, alright.
You'll also see
there then sort
of this HFG. We'll
get to what H means.
It means enthalpy.
But this HFG,
the way to think
about this is
kind of the difference
at constant pressure.
The difference in or
the amount of energy
you need to put in,
the amount of heat you
need to transfer in
or the energy to
transfer in to
boil a kilogram of
liquid water, okay?
So for these conditions,
it's like 2,200 joules
per gram for water,
which I can tell you
is a lot of energy.
It takes a lot
of energy to
boil boil water, okay?
Yeah. And so, again,
if you go in,
like,
a typical problem that
we're going to work on,
you'll be given
things like,
let's say, temperature
and quality.
Alright? So you're
going to tell me,
Professor Schutz,
you told me,
like, temperature
and pressure.
You know, these are pretty
much my independent
properties.
Sure. But there's
other ones that
also exist there that
we're going to get into.
One of them is
called quality,
alright? And
there's quality.
Alright? So when I
say the term like
saturated vapor and
saturated liquid,
the quality is
like how much
Have I gone from being a
liquid to a vapor, right?
So if I have a
quality of zero,
I am a saturated liquid.
If I have a
quality of one,
it means that I have
a saturated vapor.
I have no liquid left,
mathematically, right?
It's inside of, let's
say, a container.
The mass that's the vapor
divided by the
total mass, okay?
And it's only relevant,
right when you're
in the saturated
liquid vapor region, okay?
Cool. So again, we love
graphs here in plots.
So here's again,
TV, all right?
I want to know this
property at B, all right?
And for this type of
problem that I've
given you here,
essentially what I've
said is that this is
a temperature of 85
degrees Celsius.
And let's say
at the moment
that this is an equality
roughly sort of
equality of some value.
This looks to me
like less than 0.5,
but let's say
that's the value.
So you can understand
then by giving you
this temperature and
giving you this value,
you could say where
point B is, right?
It's halfway between
A and C there, okay?
Again, like, look
through this and,
you know, and
understand it.
Again, C would be
like X is one,
A would be X is zero
at this
temperature, right?
So yeah, you can go
through and compute it.
So if you looked
up then, you know,
you could look up in
the tables then
at point C,
what would be
the saturated,
um, specific volume of
the saturated vapor.
At 85 C, you could
look up what
is the saturated liquid?
Specific volume at 85
C, you would have them.
And this specific volume
in the middle
is nothing but
Vg X plus Vf one minus X.
To see if that
works out, if
X was one, right,
this is gone.
You have the specific
volume of the gas.
If X is zero,
this is gone,
and you have the
specific volume
of your liquid there.
Okay. Yeah, cool. You
can go in and do it.
Again, this is, you know,
my best attempt at
showing you essentially
what it is.
So you find that table.
You click on that.
You'd go and find edge 85
C. You then pick out
what your VG
and your VF is,
and you'd have
them there, okay?
Cool. When I
was a student,
we, like, programmed
all this in, like,
a TI 83 calculator
to, like,
make it fast on
a midterm. It was
brutal, okay?
Yeah,
so that's what it would
look like, you know,
VFVG you could go in,
substitute that value, and
then you would
end up with 1.4,
you know, kilograms per
meter cubed, right?
And to check
yourself, to make
sure that you did
this right, right?
That specific volume
that you determined there
should be
intermediate between
a vapor and a
liquid, right?
If it was less than
the liquid or greater
than the vapor,
you did something
wrong, right?
You know, with it.
That's the kind of
critical thinking that one
can do for such
a calculation,
all right? Quality, right?
All right, good. There's
other ones, too.
So you can go in and
do compressed liquid.
You can do
superheated vapor
for these things.
So this is what a
temperature you know,
enthalpy diagram,
temperature,
internal energy.
These are two
other sort of
independent properties
that we can use.
If you wanted to use
the superheated
water vapor,
you'd go to table A six.
You'd have to know
what your pressure is.
You put in your pressure.
You check that your
temperature is
greater than the
saturation temperature,
and then you could start
to do what's called
interpolation.
You start to interpolate
between values.
There's compressed
liquid, again,
the same drill,
no pressure.
And, you know, find
your temperature,
the closest one and either
select it or
interpolate with it.
Your GSIs will take
you through
some of that if
you have questions, okay?
But The same thing
essentially holds.
As long as you
know these sort
of two independent
properties,
you'll be able to
compute everything.
So if you said, I have
a problem here with
like 200 C and 150,
you know, kpA, you
could hazard a guess
that, like, okay, this,
you know, the pressure in
this room is
probably close to
what 110, you know,
order 100 pA. You
can hazard a
guess that, okay,
maybe the pressure
is, you know,
50% higher, but
my temperature
is much higher.
200 C. You can hazard
a guess and say,
that's probably maybe
a superheated vapor.
And so these two
property values
together are going
to be able to tell
me everything about
the system, right?
So then what you
can do right in
Python is just put
your substance,
water, put T is
that temperature,
P is that value.
And then with
dot notation,
you define this
object, and
then you'd know
everything t dot U,
internal energy, t dot V,
specific volume
and so on and so
forth with that, okay?
But they're the same
thing. Actually, doing
it this way is going
to be more accurate.
What you'll see
when you try to do
these linear
interpretations or
when you do interpolation
between values,
you're going to see
that it's assuming
like linearity,
which may not be
the case, right?
The curves bend
and all of that.
So this would be exact
if you do it this way.
Cool. So to check that,
let's see if you
know what you're
talking about here.
All right.
So in this problem,
what I want you to do,
I'll launch it,
but essentially
look at this plot
here, right?
So I have this diagram
of a TV diagram.
I say I have 50
kilograms of
saturated liquid
water at ADC.
And what are the three
answers to this?
Take like 5 minutes for
that and then we'll