All right, I got 210.
I'm going to get started.
Two. So today,
we're going to
continue with
entropy analysis.
Before I get into that, I
just want to make
a note, right?
So this class is right,
it's a lower division.
It's core subject there,
which is
kind of a euphemism
for application light.
Like we don't get too much
into applications
right there.
In the spring, though,
I'm going to be teaching
a class and on
data center,
basically energy
management in
large scale systems,
which at the moment
means data centers.
So I'm not going to
read through it.
It's all there, but
the take home is,
you know, one third
thermodynamics
fluid mechanics
heat transfer.
No requisite knowledge
on that coming in.
Next third is essentially
implementation there,
and then the
final third is
solving problems,
use inspired cases.
We'll have guest lectures
from, um, you know,
computational flu dynamics
experts at good companies,
cadence Nvidia,
vert, and related.
So if that sounds
nice, you know,
you're welcome to join.
We'd love to
have you, right?
Okay, so after today,
you should be
able to analyze
reversible steady
flow work and
the important parameters
and then be able to
discuss the best
performance for
various adiabatic
steady flow devices.
So we'll look at turbine,
and if there's
time today, we'll
look at the nozzle.
And in your homework,
you're going to
be doing a I'm sorry,
we'll be doing turbine
and compressor,
and then you'll also have
that in your
homework, okay?
But first,
let's finish the problem
that we started last time.
So last time we were
analyzing a
heat exchanger.
So we were looking at
a hot water and
cold water that were
coming together.
So we had a cold
water stream
coming in with a
mass flow rate here,
ten degrees C and with
some mass flow rate.
It was exiting
at 70 degrees C,
and then hot water,
which was coming in
at 85 degrees C and
a mass flow rate
and an unknown.
And what we did
is we first
applied right we did
a control volume
or on the cold on
the cold water stream,
right, which was here.
Okay. And because we knew
the incoming and the
exiting properties
and the mass flow rate,
we were able to
determine how much heat
was being
transferred into it.
So we knew the q.in.
With that information,
the mass flow rate
of this and the
temperature
of the incoming stream,
we were able to determine
the enthalpy and
the temperature of the
exiting stream, okay?
And so from this, we had
complete knowledge
then about the states.
So essentially, we knew
state one, we
knew state two,
we knew state three, and
we knew state four, okay?
And where we stopped
was in the analysis of
the rate of
entropy generation
inside of the heat
exchanger, okay?
So to do this part
of it, right?
So remember, for this,
I said to break it down.
Single fluid stream, dry
your control volume
to your analysis.
Figure out your states.
When you do entropy
generation problems,
you're going to
then combine
all these control
volumes, right?
So if I call this,
I don't know,
control volume one, and
then maybe the dash one is
control volume two.
When we do the
entropy analysis,
we're going to do it
for all of them, okay?
So I'm basically
just going to draw
the red dashed line
around that, okay?
And just like with
the energy balance,
all right, we
can say, right,
that the rate of change of
entropy in
this control volume,
which I will call,
you know, maybe I'll
call this, you know,
one plus two, so
the red one here.
Is equal to the rate
that entropy enters
minus the rate
that it exits
plus the rate that it's
generated, all right?
The one really key
conceptual difference
in this analysis
compared to energy,
is that one entropy,
right,
for the entire system
that we look at there,
the combined one, it
can either be zero
or it can right,
it can increase.
And as a result
of that, right,
we have this gen term,
which is due to
essentially
irreversibilities,
right, as we talked
about, okay?
So if you assume
steady flow, right?
So if you have a steady
flow device, device.
Okay, this term is
going to go to zero.
And so S dot gen
is going to be
equal to the rate
that entropy enters.
I'm sorry.
S dot gen is going
to be equal to
the rate that
entropy leaves,
so dot out minus
s.in, right?
So if we call this one,
so this is a mass
flow rate coming in,
let's say it's M dot cold.
And then this is
the mass flow rate,
let's say M dot hot hot.
Oh, my God.
That's a new one.
So which fluid streams
are leaving the
heat exchanger?
Which states are
at the exit of
the seed exchanger?
There's two.
What are they?
I know the loss
didn't feel very
good this weekend.
Okay, so it's the
even numbers, right?
So we have the entropy
that's leaving, right,
which is, we'll write
a little S two, okay?
And we'll have a little
S four, which
is here, okay?
Now, we need to multiply
this by its mass
flow rate, right?
So the S dot out
from the cold water stream
then is going to be
your dot let's say dot
cold cold, which is there.
And for the SDOT
or this case here,
then is going to be
the MDOT hot, okay?
And so that's your
SDOT out, all right?
Now, this is
minus the rate
of entropy
that's entering.
Now this is entering
then being carried in
with the fluid at state
one and state three.
So the MDT cold should
be multiplied by what?
S? One. Thank
you. All right.
And then this is plus
m dot hot times what?
Three, right? S three.
And so you can
rearrange this.
If you rearrange this, we
can write this
as a function of
the we can pull out
the mass flow rate.
So we can have dot,
let's say, cold,
and that could be times S
two or little S two
minus little S one,
it's S two minus S one,
and that could be
times M dot hot
times the leading term
there should be
S four, okay?
And that's four
minus S three, okay?
And that's the rate of
entropy generation.
Let's see if I have
some numbers to this.
First of all, let
me make sure I
did it right.
I'm not cold. I'm not hot.
Yes, that looks correct.
Mm hmm. Yeah, so if you
substituted in
the properties
that we continue there,
so the dot gen big
dot gen is an equal
to 0.063 kilowatts
per kelvin, okay?
Um Yeah,
and why are we able
to determine this?
Because if you look at dot
or basically your
S parameters,
see, these are
properties, okay?
And we were able to
determine, right,
the properties of
the fluid into
the analysis at the end
of the last
lecture, right?
So these are things that
you just like look up.
You know, as a function of
the fluid chain
that's coming in.
So, that's the substance,
and then let's say
the pressure and
the temperature.
Or in this case, we
analyze the enthalpy.
So we need the
pressure the enthalpy,
and you'll be able
to get that, right?
So you have it,
you substitution
and you get it.
Um If you want to
reflect on this,
as I said before,
so for this process,
the generation
can either be
zero or it can be a
positive value, right?
Because essentially
you have
within even if this
device is adiabatic,
so even if no
heat transfer
is coming in
from the outside
because there's heat being
exchanged between the cold
and the hot streams,
you'd have expectation of
a positive value, okay?
So start simple, right?
Do control volumes
for the individual
streams.
Good understanding then
of the states, okay?
Once you know that,
it's easy to go in
and then do the rate
of heat transfer.
And again, just applying
this analysis of the
entropy analysis
of a control volume.
You just draw it around
the entire device,
and then plug and chug.
It's pretty
straightforward, all right?
Questions? Great.
All right.
So there's not as usal,
you can click on
that link and follow
through if you have
questions when
you're doing
your homework
and all that.
All right, do do.
So reversible
steady flow work.
So what we'll do at this
stage is we're going
to continue to build on
that concept of
a process being,
you know, reversible and
adiabatic is isentropic,
and we're going to use
this to write maybe one of
the most famous equations
in fluid mechanics, right?
So this equation
we're going to
derive is called the
Bernoulli equation.
Daniel Bernoulli
was a Swiss guy,
came from a very
prominent family
of mathematicians
there, okay?
So And really what
the formula is
that will derive is that
essentially pressure
on a fluid causes
it to move.
Okay? So maybe
you knew that,
but ME 40 thermodynamics,
if you didn't, now,
you know it today.
All. Okay. Um do do.
Alright, so we can
start with the pipe.
So imagine we
have here a pipe.
Let's say we have
some state one at
the inlet and let's say
a state two at the exit.
We can draw a control
volume around the pipe.
We can do our conservation
equations, right?
So this is our control
volume, right?
The dm CV dt is equal to
m.in minus M
dot out, right?
So we have a single stream
in and a single
stream out.
And if we assume,
this is a steady
flow device.
Okay, right? This
is going to go out.
You write the
same thing for
our conservation
of energy, DE, CV,
dt, and it's equal to our
e.in minus our E dot out.
And for the same
reason, if it's
a steady flow device,
There's no change in
the energy of the
control volume,
which means that
that term also
goes to zero, right?
We can write our
e dot, right?
So our generalized e dot
could be a work power,
so W dot Q dot,
an dot times an enthalpy
of velocity squared
divided by two,
and then a G Z, right?
So this is the enthalpy.
So internal energy
plus flow work,
kinetic energy,
potential energy there.
Consequence of
this is that.in is
equal to M dot out
is equal to m dot.
Great. All right.
So we make
some further assumptions
assumptions.
So one of them
is that we have
an incompressible
fluid, Icopressible.
What's an example of an
incompressible fluid?
Water.
Okay, so water
is one example.
We're going to
assume, right,
adiabatic adiabatic
plus reversible.
Which implies
what? Isentropic.
Okay. So we have
an isentropic.
Right? So we have an
isentropic flow, right?
Do do. We're also
going to have
no shaft work.
So we have no
shaft work there.
And so if we write
our conservation
of energy equation,
we're going to
be able to say,
just to maybe come back
here and write it.
So if we say that
there's no work,
there's no heat transfer,
the MDOT in is
the MDOT out.
Essentially, it's just
going to be enthalp P
plus kinetic energy
plus potential energy.
The inlet is
equal to the same
at the outlet, right?
So you're going
to say that H
one plus velocity
one squared
divided by two plus
gz one is equal to H
two plus w squared divided
by two plus g two.
That's a two. All right.
Good. Mm hmm.
You recall the derivation
that we did
before where we
related changes
in entropy to
changes in enthalpy
and pressure.
So ds is equal to
dH minus V dp.
So TD little S,
d little H minus
little V dp and right,
so since V is equal to a,
um, is equal
to a constant.
We can integrate this.
So if we integrated
this, then here,
what we'd have is
then T times S
two minus S one
is equal to
H two minus H one minus
V P two minus P one.
It's isentropic
isentropic,
which implies
what that's it.
R S two is this one,
which in this case
implies that rate
h2h2 minus H one
is going to be equal
to the negative of
little V P two
minus P one.
Yes, please. H
two minus H one,
this should be a positive.
Thank you. Other feedback.
So just for on
the recording,
this should be a positive.
Okay. No.
Okay.
Yeah, so we can rearrange.
So if we rearrange
our original
formula that's
up there, maybe I'll
do it right here.
So if we rearrange
that to be
H two minus H one,
this would be W one
squared divided by
two plus G Z one
is equal to H
two minus H one plus
W two squared divided
by two plus G two.
Mm hmm. This, right?
We can do a
substitution to here.
And so that'll be V
P two minus P one,
and close to
our final form.
So if I can write this
as let's see here.
So I can do zero, right?
Zero is equal to
V P two minus P
one. All right.
We can do the W terms now.
So plus W looks like W two
squared minus W one
squared divided by two,
and then plus G Z
two minus Z one.
There newly equation.
Yeah, so this works.
So, what is this valid?
This is basically
valid for, right?
Incompressible fluids.
Like you mentioned,
water, no friction.
All right. And
no fun things
like shock waves.
All right. All right.
And the take home message,
all right, is
that you can do
things like, you know,
have trade offs between
pressures that
you apply, okay?
Which can cause
fluids to move,
right, to gain
kinetic energy.
And you can
also store that
as potential
energy, right?
So this could be,
like what we would
call as a
hydrostatic term,
something like a tall
column of liquid,
right?
There might be a lot
of pressure at
the base of that.
And if there
was no pressure
applied right across from,
let's say at the
top of the column,
right, you have
atmospheric pressure,
maybe at the bottom of
it also atmospheric,
and then you poke
a hole, right?
Right? Initially,
you start off with
no velocity at one
end of the pipe,
and at the other
one, you have
a very large one, okay?
So pressure on a fluid
causes it to
move, all right?
Icon incompsible,
no friction,
no shock waves, essentially,
isentropic flow.
All right? Questions?
You'll use it at M one
oh six. All right?
I think it's say you
already know it.
Good. Um let's see. Do do.
All right. So
moving along.
So now we can
continue with
this analysis
in isentropic
and apply it
towards devices.
If you remember before,
what I mentioned was
that we're going to
treat these devices as
isotropic to figure out,
in the case of
a compressor,
what's the minimum amount
of work I need to put in,
or in the case
of a turbine,
what's the
maximum amount of
work that I could get out?
And what we're
going to do today,
we'll start with
the turbine is to
account for a reality,
actual systems.
So actual systems have
friction and that,
and the way that this
is expressed is in
terms of isentropic
efficiencies, right?
So what's an isotropic
efficiency in the
case of a turbine?
It's the ratio
of the actual
turbine work that's done
normalized or divided by
the isentropic
turbine work, right?
Just to remind you
how these turbines
look like,
you have an
upstream condition
that's the same in
both, all right?
So you have a
pressure, let's
say that's coming
out of a boiler,
so superheated steam
at some pressure
and temperature that's
entering into
your turbine.
In the case of
a reversible
adiabatic turbine,
right, it's isotropic.
You're going to
be given, usually
the pressure
downstream, right?
And again, in a
rankin cycle,
that's going to be
what's inside of
the condenser, but
that's a given.
And in order to determine
the enthal P here
at this state,
you have to
assume something,
which in this case,
adiabatic reversible,
it's the same
entropy, right?
So S one here is
equal to S two,
and you can
analyze that and
then get the
denominator, right?
From that,
we essentially have
the denominator.
In this case,
again, you have
the same upstream,
the same pressure.
To analyze this, you'd
be given
inefficiency, right?
And the name of the
game is you use
this information to
determine enthalpy two.
You can also determine
the entropy,
but essentially,
you'll determine
the enthalpy
at this state.
And then with that,
you'll be able to say
how much power
you actually
get out of the device.
I'm presenting
this graphically.
So here you see a plot of
pressure enthalpy
for water, right?
So saturated liquid,
saturated vapor,
both starting at the
same initial state.
You see here the
move to two S,
and then here actually
two A, right?
So which one of those
produces more work?
One to two S or
one to two A?
What does the work of
a turbine depend on?
What is the formula
for a turbine?
W dot turbine is
equal to M dot
times w. All right.
H one by H two.
Which of these has
the larger
difference between H
one and H two?
You don't have to
answer. It's rhetorical.
We'll do it in
this example
All right. So we'd
like to derive.
So the goal of this is
we're going to derive
derive isentropic
efficiency
of a turbine.
All right. And
the next thing
we're going to do is
we're going to be
given of a turbine.
So if it's an adiabatic
adiabatic turbine.
And if we're told that
P one is equal to three p,
and T one is equal to
350 degrees Celsius,
and P two is
equal to 75 and
pa with an isentropic
efficiency
of the turbine
equal to 0.9,
determine T to actual
and T two isentropic.
So in my notation here,
when I speak about
the downstream state,
so that's the state
two out of my turbine.
When I write S, this
is the isentropic,
and when I write A,
this means actual.
I think the book
does the same.
And then we'll show it on
a diagram. I'm
showing it there.
So you have pH
a pH diagram.
Okay. All right.
So our assumptions are
that we have, right,
control volume, right,
mass enters and
crosses the boundary.
We can't assume an ideal
gas because this is water.
Um, We're going to
neglect kinetic energy
and potential
energy effects.
It's an adiabatic process.
It's a steady
flow process,
and we have a
single inlet and
a single outlet, right?
So if we again,
if we write our w.in plus
q.in plus dot
plus w squared
divided by two
plus gz one is
equal to our w dot
out plus Q dot
out plus our.h2 plus
w squared divided
by two, gz two.
All right. Adiabatic,
right? So this is gone.
We don't have any
work transferring
because this is a turbine.
We don't have
significant changes
in kinetic and
potential energies.
And so our W dot
right out is nothing
but dot times H
one minus H two.
Now, in this case,
where we know we now
determine our states.
So we're going to
talk about state one.
With state one,
I know P one,
and I know T one,
which means that
I know S one
and I know H one, okay?
Talk about state two
S. For state two S,
I know P two,
and I know that
little S two is
equal to little
S one, right?
And so it means that
I can determine h2s,
and I can determine TS,
and that's one of
the things we'd
like to know.
All right. That's great.
So we know the states.
Let's come back to
our formula here.
So we can define
a W dot out of
the isotropic system is
the mass flow rate times
H one minus H twos.
We can also
define the power
out of the device
for the actual,
and that's dot H one
minus H two actual.
You see here
the definition
of the isentropic
efficiency,
which is given in
the problem as 0.9.
So the isentropic
efficiency is defined
as the power out
of the turbine for
the actual case,
divided by the power
out for the isentropic.
And this is going
to be a number
that's less than
one, right?
Because you can't
do better than
the isentropic case.
That's the
maximum power out
you're going to be
able to get out of
this adiabatic
turbine is W dot out
S. If W dot
out of the actual was
actually isentropic,
if it had an isentropic
effiency of one,
then they're
essentially the same.
So you can substitute
these two equations
that we have above.
And so you'll have M dot,
H one minus H two A
divided by m.h1 minus h2s.
The dots cancel,
and that's what
it's defined as.
The book calls this
an approximation.
Why is this an
approximation?
What approximation
do we make?
We neglected kinetic and
potential energy
changes, okay?
So here, that's
the assumption
that's implicit when
you write this.
So in the book,
you'll see sometimes
it's writing it
as like
approximately equal,
but this is what
you'll do, right?
So you have this defined,
and then you'll go to
a formula like that.
And the goal out of this
exercise is we know H one.
We know H twos, right?
Because we
determined it here.
And so what you're
trying to find from
this analysis in
the substitution
is actually
H two A, all right?
So again, you're
given upstream state.
You can determine
the isentropic
downstream state,
and you're given
E to T, right?
So the isentropic
efficiency
the turbine is 0.9.
And so you solve
for H two A.
All right. And
by knowing that,
so now with state two,
so we can call
state two A,
by knowing that, we know P
two just as it was before,
and now we know H two A.
And with that, we can
determine then T two A,
which was one of the
asks out of the problem.
So we use Pi color.
I'm going to use
Pi color again,
define this state
here, I have TS.
Define that state
to have T two A.
And so the T I
have as our T start with
T two A. I have T A,
which is equal to o
no, I've printed now.
Oh, that's awesome.
I've printed
the same value twice.
Super good. I All right.
So this is anyways,
this would be
the analysis,
and then this is the way
that you'd get to it.
I'll update the
Jupyter Notebook
and post the link
to that there.
But again, just
to summarize,
the whole point of this
exercise is you're
going to be given
upstream state,
a downstream pressure,
an isotropic efficiency,
and you're going
to be asked to
determine things like
what is the work,
the power output
of the device.
You go to this formula,
solve for H twoA.
With the downstream
pressure,
you'll have complete
information, okay?
You could also
determine, because
once you have H twoA,
you could also determine,
right, the actual
power output
by then substituting
into that formula,
all right?
Okay. Cool.
Yeah. And so if you
look at this diagram,
so I've also used the
defined a process
for this.
So I define a state
one to state two,
and I use the
process class
of Pi Killor to
create a pH diagram.
And you'll see here
that for state two S,
the enthalpy is less
than that for two A,
right? So the
difference, right?
The difference in
the enthalpy between
H one and H twoS
is greater than
the difference of
H one and H two A.
And so what it
means, right,
is that one to two S
is going to produce
more power, right?
This value here
is going to be
larger than that
one, right?
So this would
be very easy,
and you would just
take that with you,
and I wouldn't have
to say more, but,
you know, because we
like to make things
interesting,
we'll talk about
now a compressor.
In the case of
a compressor,
it is not the ratio of
the actual work divided
by the isotropic, right?
So it's what is
the work here?
This is the work
you transfer
into the system, okay?
So an isentropic
efficiency
of a compressor is
the isentropic
compressor work
in divided by the actual
compressor work in.
The turbine is the
actual turbine work
out divided by the
isotropic turbine workout.
The way that I think
about this is,
in the case of a
turbine, I want to
maximize my
workout, right?
And if this is
an efficiency,
the maximum term has
to be in the denominator.
I want that to be
less than one.
It's the same with
the compressor.
For the compressor,
I want to put
the minimum work in
to compress that gas.
So that minimum work
has to be then in
the numerator
with it, right?
Okay. Cool. Do do do?
Where should I start?
I think I will
keep this formula
here and just jump
off from here.
So just like with
the turbine,
so we're going
to derive the
isentropic efficiency
of a compressor.
We're going to
assume adiabatic.
And for one of
the cases, we're
going to assume
reversible.
So we're going to
determine the
isotropic state.
We're going to
neglect kinetic
and potential
energies, right?
So we can write.
This one is no
longer gone, right?
This is going to be w.in.
We're not going to have
a W dot out, right?
So the w.in is going
to be equal to m
dot times H two.
Minus H one.
We can write this for
the isotropic case, right?
So that's going
to be M dot H
twos minus H one.
And we can write
w.in actual,
which is then.h2a
minus H one.
The definition, so E to C,
so the isentropic
efficiency of
a compressor is
then the ratio of
w.in isentropic divided
by w.in actual.
If we do our
substitutions,
M dot H twos minus H one,
m.h2a minus H one.
The dots cancel this
is then just H two,
excuse me, H one,
H two A minus H one.
Again, the book
says this is
an approximation
because again,
we're neglecting
changes in
kinetic and
potential energy.
Good. But now we
need some right?
We need to basically
determine some
properties here.
Let's look and see.
I think I have
some properties
for this problem.
Okay. So again, we want to
define isotropic
efficiency of
a compressor. All right.
It's adiabatic.
Our P one and our
T one are equal to
100 kpa and let's
say 20 degrees C,
so something from ambient.
The P two is five
times P one,
so we can do 500 pa,
and the isotropic
efficiency
of the compressor is 0.9.
And again, we want
to determine those
temperatures,
and we'll also plot
a temperature TS
we'll create a TS diagram.
All right, so let's
look at state one,
so we can determine H one.
So state one here,
we know P one,
and we know T one.
And so from this, we're
going to know S one,
little S one, and
little H one.
So we have that.
We can determine
state two S. All right.
The input there
is that little
S two is equal
to little S one,
and we know P two.
So we have h2s there,
and we'll have
T two, right?
So the isentropic
enthalpy and temperature.
If we come back now
to Our formula.
So what did I say?
I said that this
is a given this is 0.9.
This we determined, right?
Determined determined.
HwS we determined.
And so what you're
solving for here again
is H two A.
All right. And
so with this,
I have state two A.
Again, I know P two,
just like before, and
now I know H two.
And so with this, you're
going to be able to
determine T two actual,
right, which was Right?
So we know that
and we know that,
and that's what we
were asked to do
in the problem.
And thankfully,
in this case,
I did not print
the same value.
So here, T two,
what I have from
using Pyclor.
So with T two A,
I have 481 Kelvin.
And with TS, I
have 463 Kelvin.
And why does
that make sense?
That makes sense.
Because in the
case when it's
an isentropic work
transfer process,
you need less work in.
You're transferring
less energy into
the system.
And so if this is
something like,
you know, this was air,
we're working with
areas of fluid here,
compressors always
work with gases.
So if this is areas of
fluid, if we assume,
which we didn't
need to here, but
if you want to think
logically about it,
that air probably
behaves like
an ideal gas, right?
I put work into that,
transfer work in.
I'd have an expectation of
a change of my
internal energy,
and that only depends
on temperature.
So in this case, For
the case when I
put less work in,
I would expect a
lower temperature
at the end of the
compressor compared
to the actual case where I
have irreversibilities,
all right?
But again, the problem
solving approach
is identical,
you know, to the turbine.
I just have I have
a different formula for
the isentropic efficiency.
So in this case,
the ratio of
the isentropic work in
divided by the actual
work in, all right?
So that's the
only part where I
would say confusion
comes up into this.
Otherwise, we
have the formula.
You got that. Again,
plug and shug.
It should be straightfor.
Questions about this.
Am I going to finish
early? Yes, please.
Thank you, we expect
the temperature to
be higher on.
Say it again.
For the turbine, would
the temperature
differences be
swapped from
the compressor
with the temperature
higher on
the isotropic I'm not
sure. I have to see.
I'll have to see with
it. But what you would
expect for a system
that gets more workout.
So if you're thinking
about workout,
I think the better
question to ask
is actually
about pressure.
So which one actually
gets to, you know,
what is the you know,
if I was going
to think about
a term I know it
was fixed here.
I know the downstream
pressure was fixed,
but if I was
going to think
about one that was
going to be maximizing
more out of it,
I would think about like
a pressure term
downstream.
So yeah. But, I mean,
if I do have a
system and I take
more work out of it,
so if I, you know,
flipped it and
I said, I took
more work out of
this compared to,
you know, let's say I had
a turbine running on air,
right? It's an ideal gas.
If I took more work out
of one process
versus the other,
you know, what would
you expect the effect
on temperature at
the outlet to be?
Be lower, right? Yeah, so
and so I would think
then for the
steam turbine,
not applying ideal, but
if I looked at that,
that would be my
expectation going in.
Other questions?
Nice question.
And I got to
remember how to
use print in Python.
Alright. Great.
So that's it. I.
So what you're going to
be able to do, again,
so reversible steady
flow work, you know,
processes there, we
drive Bernoulli today,
and you're going to
be able to apply now.
We have two new
things, right,
isentropic efficiency
of a turbine,
of a compressor.
This allows us to
analyze real
devices, right?
You can go in and analyze.
These are things you
can look up, right?
You can look
that up and have
it and facilitate it.
I am happy to stay
until the end of
lecture here in case
people have questions.
What I would say for
the quiz is we're
hard at work grading.
I hope to be done.
We hope to be
done by Friday
and release, okay?
Thank you.