Wonderful. So today, we
continue with vapor
power cycles.
So after today, you're
going to be
able to analyze
a reheat vapor
power cycle and
a regenerative
vapor power cycle.
I've already
introduced you to
regeneration
in the context
of a Braden cycle.
We're going to do it
today in the context
of a closed loop
rankin cycle, okay?
Before I get
into that, since
you As about Quiz two,
what I will note is
that the practice
quiz is already online.
This is what I
ran last year.
Last year, at this point,
what I asked was an
entry be generation,
an ideal Humphries cycle,
which is a great cycle.
It's a detonation
engine, super good.
Then the ideal
Ericsson cycle.
Ericsson is Sterling is
a piston cylinder device.
Basically the
most efficient
piston cylinder device
you could have.
Ericsson is the most
efficient steady
flow device
you could have
for an engine.
I'll continue to
add more as I find
5 minutes and
10 minutes in
my day to have
problems, right?
Okay, so, David,
last time,
well, I don't see him,
had brought up this point
about how can
we think about
improving the efficiency
of a ranking cycle?
There are several
ways one can do this.
So one, which
I show here is
essentially reducing
the pressure in
the condenser.
So if you think about what
our system looks
like, right?
We have this boiler, okay?
So we have q.in,
which is here, right?
Steam comes out at
some state here.
We put this
into a turbine.
Okay. You know, here
we expand that.
We then put that into
a surface condenser.
So many, many tubes
where water condenses.
And then this goes back
into a pump where we have
aw.in to a pump. Okay?
And then this goes
back into the boiler.
So this is where our
Q dot out happens.
This is where our shaft
work out happens, right?
And so what sets
the pressure in
the condenser?
So again, this
condenser right?
I can draw like kind of
a side view of this.
So if I was showing this
as like a side view,
the way that this works,
is that you have steam
that comes into the top of
this thing from
the turbine
and then exits
as a liquid.
Remember, this great
discussion from, you know,
Ben in the last
lecture about what
a condensed
state is and how
we define it, right?
So you have a quality
here that's equal to zero.
It comes out
of liquid, and
it comes as a
superheated vapor.
And the way that
we condense is we
have many tubes, right?
This is one version of it.
You have like many tubes.
I'm not really
showing that many,
where we're
bringing, let's say,
cooling water in at
some temperature.
So maybe this is like a T,
you know, five coming in,
and maybe this is a T
six that's coming out,
and it's a liquid, right?
A lot of this is
groundwater that
we bring in,
we pass through, right,
and it exits this system.
And then on the outside
of these tubes,
this is where water
condenses, right?
So water is going
to condense on
the outside of these
tubes, all right?
And then it's
going to when the
droplets are big enough,
it's going to start
to, you know,
drip down and
drain into here.
So what sets, there's
a lot of. Okay.
So what's going to set
the pressure that's in
there is the temperature,
because this is a saturated
condition, right?
I have a mixture of
vapor and liquid.
And so this something,
let's say between T
five and T six. Okay?
So let's say, you know,
we have some temperature
that's the average,
I don't know,
T five plus T six,
you know, there.
So we have some
temperature like that.
The lower Let's say
that you make this,
and then the lower will be
the saturation vapor
pressure that's there.
So the colder
that I get that,
the colder or the
lower then will be
the pressure that I
have then inside
of that condenser.
Alright? What it means
is since the workout
of this device,
what's the workout of
a steady flow device?
What's the shaft work
going to be equal to?
AV, Alex.
Okay.
Now, David is here.
You moved on me.
So what's the workout
of a steady flow device?
So piston cylinder,
it's PDV.
What is it as steady flow?
Don't make me ask
Melanie. She's behind.
H.
No, not H. It could
be H. It could be DH,
yes. But what's
another way, right?
So if I talked
about a shaft work,
I could say PDV when
it was a piston
cylinder device.
And when I talked about
a steady flow device,
it's isochoric, but I
have a pressure
difference across it.
So the V is constant.
So V times,
that's it, right?
So you have a specific
volume there, right?
I have, let's say,
if this is one,
two, three, four, so one,
two, three, and then
four is a state,
then what you're
going to have is
P three minus P four.
So the reason why you
get more work out of
this make the
temperature lower,
you make the
pressure, right?
P or P four,
they're lower.
So you have a bigger
Delta P, right?
That's one way to make
it more efficient.
What actually happens
in power plants,
though, is the other way.
You start off pristine.
Everything is great.
And these pipes corrode,
they get fouled.
And what it means
is that the outside
of these tubes get warmer.
It means the
pressure goes up,
the Delta P less.
It means you get
less workout.
They call that derating
de rating, okay?
And it's not a small
amount of energy.
It's not a small
amount. It's measuring
like several percent
power plants.
You put that on
a global scale.
It's a lot of energy.
It's a lot of extra
CO two emissions.
It's a lot, okay?
So you can try to,
you know, make
this colder.
That's why you can
use water. Water will
get you to a lower
temperature.
Other ones will use air.
So sometimes you'll
see, you know,
maybe they'll blow air
and try to reject heat.
It depends on where
you're located.
But my gut would
say that with air,
you're probably not
going to get to
a lower temperature
compared to
something like water
water cooled, okay?
Great. So that's
what it is, right?
So I get to
lower pressure,
and then because of that,
I'm going to
have that extra
area within my loop.
The area enclosed
in that loop is,
of course, the net Q in,
which for a cycle is
the network
out, all right?
Other way we can
do it is, right?
You can just simply
go to higher temperatures.
We talked about
that before,
but there's
limits to this.
So if you think about
a rank in cycle,
What limits the
temperature
and the pressure
here is the boiler.
How stable can
I make that?
That's like, the first
thing. So how hot?
How much pressure
can this handle?
The second thing is, will
my blades melt, right?
Will I be able to run
a steam or something
through that
that doesn't absolutely
destroy my system?
So the combination
of those two things,
I believe it's the boilers
that actually
set the limit
at the moment for water.
But there will be
an upper limit
that you can handle,
and that will be set.
Okay, but there's
another approach, okay?
So if we say that the
materials and all
of that can handle only,
you know, an upper
pressure and
an upper temperature
associated with them.
One thing you can do is to
run what's called
a rank and reheat.
So essentially, you take
the steam leaving the
original turbine,
as I would show in
State four here,
and you run it through
the boiler again, okay?
So you run it through
the boiler again,
that comes back out,
and you run it then
through that enters
in a lower
pressure turbine,
and you try to
eke more work out
of it that way.
So this process is called
a reheat, a
reheat process.
Okay? We talked
about regeneration,
which I'll do in
the next example.
This one is a reheat
there, right?
And hopefully it's clear
why you would do that from
a TS diagram, right?
So here I went to
that higher pressure
and temperature.
I dropped it down, right,
with my work extraction
until I was a
saturated vapor,
and then I
reheated it again.
But this pressure is
going to be lower.
P five here is going to
be less than P three.
I'm showing the
isobars here,
but it still
has that upper
temperature limit
with it, right?
I that boiler,
I'm not going
to get a higher
temperature.
I can only get the
max temperature
again, and then it
drops back down.
But you have that
extra, you know,
slice of area
enclosing that curve,
and that gives you
a boost, okay?
So let's reheat reheat.
All right. So
what I'm going to
do now is I'll go
through this analysis.
We'll go through the
analysis of this one.
How do you do reheat.
Yeah, and the work
that's in my lab,
we work basically
on coatings and
stuff to prevent
fouling that
happens on the
inside of these and
corrosion on the
inside of these tubes.
So if you're
ever interested
in seeing that,
let me know.
I can put you
in contact with
the researchers who
actually do the work.
Okay. All right, so
the ideal reheat.
Let me see. This one's
still okay? It's okay ish.
I Alright, so what
do we have here?
So we have first,
we have our pump.
So we have a pump
that's here.
This is going
into our boiler,
which looks like this.
This goes out, and then
into a high pressure
turbine, just like that.
This is connected
in series then to
a low pressure turbine,
which looks like that.
And then this is
my W dot out,
which is happening there.
This enters
into The boiler
here goes back out
and then becomes
the inlet to the low
pressure turbine.
Exit of this then
passes through the
surface condenser,
just like the one that
I showed you, right?
And then this goes back
into the pump, right?
So this has aw.in Here,
we have aq.in,
which is here.
We have the W dot
out, which is there,
and we have a Q dot out,
which is happening
from the condenser.
We label states,
the state at
the exit of the
condenser is state one,
State two is
entering the boiler.
State three is
exiting the boiler.
This is just as we
did for Rankin.
State four is the exiting
of the first turbine,
and then this is where we
start to have differences.
State five is then at
the exit of the
reheat process.
State six is then at
the exit of the low
pressure turbine.
So one, two, three,
four, five, six,
so two additional
states to do reheat.
All right? What are we
given in the problem?
So we can start with
our state five.
It's a state Um,
So we're told four
or state three.
Let's start with
State three.
State three is
given, right?
So our state three,
we know that we
have a T three that's
equal to 315
degrees Celsius,
and we have a P three
that's equal to
4.14 MPA, all right?
And that's the nor, right?
So you typically in
these problems are
going to be given
the exit state
of the boiler.
That's like
automatic, all right?
And out of this,
all right,
um, Well, of course,
no specific
enthropy and specific
entropy there.
It's a pure substance,
two pieces of two
independent properties
because it's a
superheated vapor,
temperature and
pressure work,
so we have complete
knowledge there.
All right. Next
thing that's given.
We can get to state I'm
going to go to
state five here.
Okay. And state five,
again, essentially
exit of the boiler.
We know that T five
here is 315 degrees C,
just like T three
because it's
passing through
the same boiler.
But the pressure is
going to be less, right,
because this has
already passed through,
right?
It's expanded through
the um first turbine here,
so the pressure is
going to be less.
P five is going to be
less than P three,
and the pressure we're
told here is 1.38 PA.
And the same,
we know H five,
and we know S five
there. All right.
Good what else do we know?
Basically, state
six, State six,
we're told the pressure at
the exit of the
second turbine,
the low pressure turbine,
that's 0.069 PA.
Okay, Good.
And so what we
can do is we can
go device by device,
essentially do our mass,
energy and
entropy analysis
for these individual
control volumes.
From that, we'll
be able to say
things like how much
energy is in or out,
how much entropy
changes with that.
And then with
those parameters,
we'll come back to states.
And then once we
have the states,
we'll have our enthalpies.
We'll go back and
substitute numbers and
be able to say
how much heat
was added or rejected,
and then the thermal
efficiency of the cycle.
So let's start drawing
some control volumes.
Alright. Okay. All right,
so our first one
is with our pump.
So we have a control
volume for our pump.
We have our control
volume for the boiler,
control volume for
high pressure turbine,
low pressure turbine,
and then the
control volume
for the condenser.
All right. Do do
do. All right.
So if we go with our pump,
so if we start with one
to two, and our pump.
So we have work in.
So we have
a steady flow device for
all of these, right?
Delta M, CV is equal
to zero, Delta E,
CV is equal to
zero, and Delta S,
zero for all
of these devices, right?
So for the pump, we
only have work in,
okay? We're
neglecting, right?
So Delta KE is
equal to Delta PE,
which is equal to zero for
all these devices,
all right?
And so what you'll
have then is,
um, All right,
m.in equals M dot
out equals to m dot.
And so for here, the work
that's going to go
in is then going to
be H two minus
H one, right?
If we do an entropy
balance here,
I'll do it for this
one, and then I'll
just skip through it
for the others, right?
But ds cv dt is equal
to.in minus rs dot out,
S dot out plus rs dot gen.
So steady flow device?
So this is gone.
Um, and because this is
an ideal reheat
rank and cycle,
what that means for
work transfer processes
is that these are
adiabatic and
they're reversible.
So what do you think that
means for this formula?
What simplification
do I make if I
have something that's
adiabatic and reversible,
Zs dot gen is gone, right?
And so the reason for
this is adiabatic.
And reversible
reversible, all right?
And the keyword for
this for work
transfer things
is that you see the
word ideal, okay?
So ideal means that
work transfer devices
are isentropic.
And the meaning of
isentropic is that
it's adiabatic
and reversible.
Adiabatic means no
heat in or out.
Reversible means,
as I run it,
I don't generate
friction, right?
Essentially, I don't
generate heat.
That's the meaning
of that, all right?
Okay, so out of this,
right, I can write M dot.
N is dot out, right?
So.in times little S N
is equal to my dot out
times little S out.
M.in is M dot out,
right, that's gone.
And so what it means
is S in is S out.
So S one is equal to
little S one is equal
to little S two, okay?
So now we know
something about state,
um Right?
Now we know basically
something about
state state two, right?
So we have here state
can write state two.
So here I'm saying S
two is equal to S one,
okay? Great. All right.
On to our next device.
So I will not
go as detailed
for the next one,
but for the next
one, two to three.
So I'm looking at
my control volume.
Maybe I should spend
a little bit more
time with that.
So now we have two or
what I would call
essentially what is it?
It's two to three,
and then it's
also four to
five, all right?
Four to five
is the boiler.
All right, so I look
at the control volume.
It's steady flow, right?
MDT in is MDT out of
that control volume.
And so We have the dot,
the way that energy
is entering,
I have dot times two plus
m dot times H four
must be equal
to plus.in q.in is
then equal to the
way that it exits.
Mm dot times three,
plus dot times H
five to do we're not
going to do we're
not going to do
an entropy analysis
on the boiler here.
Good. What's next?
Let me just
check my notes,
make sure I'm on track.
Do. Other questions
so far? Mmm.
Okay. We can write this
in for the rate
of heat addition
and heat rejection.
What I have in my
solution is we solve for.
So what I can do
is I can divide
both sides by dot.
If I did that, I'll have H
two plus four plus
little Q in, right?
So heat per unit mass is
then equal to H
three plus H five.
So then little Q in
is then equal to
H three plus five
minus H two plus four.
I swear I read this thing,
and then geez
too many pages.
Yeah, H three plus
H five minus H
two minus H four.
Okay, that's great.
So that's good.
Now we can go on to
more familiar things.
So then three to
five is our turbine.
So we have no work in.
We have no heat in or out,
neglecting changes in
potential kinetic energy.
So W dot out of
our turbine is
dot times this is
three to four,
sorry, three to
43 to four H
three minus H four.
That's very good.
The second turbine.
So our next turbine,
which is then
five to four.
So we have five to six.
If there's questions.
Okay. Five to six.
So then the W dot
out of this lower
pressure turbine,
maybe I'll call
it I don't know.
Maybe I can call that two,
maybe I'll call that one.
But the W dot out
of this one is
then m.h5 minus six.
What we can do for both of
these cases is also
the entropy analysis.
So no change in the
control volume,
adiabatic reversible
because it's ideal.
So what it means then is
the same thing
here, S four.
Little four is going
to be equal to
little S three,
and the same for the
other one little S
six is going to be
equal to little S
five there, right?
So that's isomropic.
And then our last one
is then our condenser.
So it's condenser.
We don't have
work in or out.
We have no heat in.
We only have
heat out, right?
So we do our then
this is six to one.
So six to one,
our condenser,
our Q dot out is
going to be equal to
M dot times the
enthalpy at state six,
a six minus the enthalpy
at state one, okay?
Great. Let us I
will move this to
this side here.
I will bring back
my estates here,
and I will move this
one into the middle.
And now we can go bit by
bit and map out
our estates,
now that we have
enough information
there, alright?
Okay, so we have
State three,
which we know this is
an important part of
analyzing these things is
figuring out
where you have
complete information.
So you start from
these points.
Alright,
so it's state three
entering the turbine.
I'm I'm good there.
I go down to state four.
So state State four.
I know that this turbine
operates
isentropically, right?
So, S is equal to S three.
Trying to see
how that looks.
Maybe I'll go full
screen here. All right.
And as far as S three,
what else do you think
you know about State
four based on
what I've drawn
here? Hazard a guess.
Quality, no, Cody.
Sure. That's
it. Look ahead.
Look backwards, but
also look forwards.
Normally, I say don't
look backwards in life,
but in Rankin, look
backwards and forwards
like Cody said.
Basically, your
pressure here because
you're passing through
a heat exchanger,
P four is equal
to P five and P
five is given.
This is equal to 1.38 PA.
This is good. Now I know
my or I know my four here.
That's good. State
five is given.
We come to state six now.
State six from
what we wrote
over there is that S
is equal to S five.
So S is equal to S five,
and S five, we
determined here.
So now you have
complete information.
You can get the enthalpy
at state six for this.
We're good.
Continuing along,
now we're at we're
at state one.
This is State State one.
At state one, because
a condenser is a
glorified heat exchanger,
P one is equal to
P six is equal to
0.069 PA. That's good.
What else do you know
about the condenser?
Yeah. Elias. And the
quality is zero.
That's it, right? The
quality is zero here.
So X one is equal
to zero because
it's a condenser.
That's a part
about a Rankin.
Okay, I remember that.
And with this, you have
S one and you have H one.
So now I have state one,
okay? Continuing along.
I'm looking at it. I got
three, four, five, six.
I almost got a bingo here.
Actually, that
I have a bingo,
but I need an extra
one for a reheat.
So the last part is
that I know an OS one
at state two
because the pump
operates isentropically.
I know this um
a specific entropy
at state two.
And like Cody had said,
because of boiler is
a heat exchanger,
I know that P two,
if I look ahead,
is equal to P three,
and that's a given.
That's given as 4.14
PA. And so what
that means is that
I have H two.
Right? So all I
need to determine
the heat additions
and the heat
rejections, I've got.
So I've got my I guess
going in order, right?
I have H one, right?
I have my age two, I
have my age three,
I have my age four,
I have my age five,
and I have my
age six, okay?
So let's get into it.
We're given the power.
So we're given
that the w.net,
which is equal to the w.in
minus the W dot out,
um, which is, of course,
also equal to q.in,
I'm sorry, W dot out.
Excuse me. It's
Friday W dot out.
W dot N is equal to
q.in minus Q dot out,
which is equal to 5
megawatts, right?
5 megawatts. All right.
I This is good.
This means that I have
dot times little W out
minus little W
in is equal to
the dot of Q in
minus little Q out.
Okay, um, four.
So it depends on
what we could do.
I would say, in this case,
since it's asking
us for the
heat addition
and rejection,
we can focus on the Q in.
So our Q in was an
dot times what?
Our little Q in we
wrote over there
was not an M dot.
It was H three plus H
five minus H two
plus H four.
I've got that.
That's good.
The little Q
out All right.
Where do we write it?
That would be H
six minus H one.
Okay? That's good.
So now what you
would do is
substitute those
values use
Pi calorie. You
got those values.
You'll take this Q in,
you'll put it into here,
you'll take this Q out,
you'll put it into
here, you'll set this
equal to 5 megawatts.
And from this, you'll
know the mass
flow rate, right?
The M dot, okay?
And then by knowing
the dot, right?
You can take the dot.
Substitute into there.
That's Q dot out,
and then my q.in, which
I'll write here then.
So then my q.in is
nothing but my dot
times my Q in, right?
So this dot would
then come here.
You would substitute.
You put your Q in there,
and then you would
have the Q in and
the Q out. That's good.
And the thermal
efficiency is nothing but
one minus Q dot
out over q.in,
or in this case, you
could also write that as
one minus little Q
out over little
Q in, okay?
If you want some numbers,
I have some numbers.
At least I have a number
for the efficiency
of this,
given the parameters.
The efficiency
that I have,
if you substitute
in is that
Ea I have an Eta
that's equal to 27.9%.
It's a little bit
on a little on
the lower side.
And then I find it
always instructive at
these points to compare
with what I would
have as Carne.
So if you want to compare
this then with Carnot,
Carnot is equal to
one minus the
coldest temperature
divided by the hottest
temperature of the cycle.
So you would have
that from um,
the temperature
at state one and
the temperature then
at state three.
And if you put that in,
the absolute
maximum efficiency
this cycle could have
would then be 38.4%.
Okay?
Questions, Elias.
Two to three. On
the far right.
So all I said is that for
the so you mean
this line here. How
did I write this?
Like just so I understand,
your question is how did
I get to this? Yeah.
I don't have two
to three, right?
I have two, three,
four and five, right?
Yeah. So there's no six.
Yeah. The point is
that you have to draw
a control volume around
the heat exchanger.
And what you do is you
think about how is
energy entering and
leaving this
control volume?
What are the inlets to
this control
volume? That's it.
So I'm going to
have an.h4 plus an
m.h2 plus a Q
dot N. That's what's
entering. What's leaving?
M.h3+m.h5.
Okay? And that's what
I've written here.
So this is what's entering
and this is
what's leaving.
I divide both
sides by M dot.
H two, H four Qn little
QN H three, H five.
Reorganize. This is my
QN. That makes sense?
Okay. But that's an
especially critical part
of control
volume analysis.
If you didn't know
how to do that
well in your fundamentals,
you would not do this
problem well, right?
Yes, please,
David. The arrows?
Yeah. I will
probably give you
words and then tell
you to work it out.
Really an
important part of
this class, I don't groan.
You can groan. It's
First Amendment groan.
But the point out of
this class is really that
I give you almost
like a prompt,
and the reply is this,
you should be able
to do that, okay?
Yes, please. But if
I draw a diagram,
certainly at least
numerically,
I would give you numbers
and then you can
go, in numerical order.
Yes, please.
Let's focus on
the first one.
2-3, we treat it as
a heat exchanger.
And when I do
heat additions,
there may be a
pressure difference,
but that contribution
in terms of
an energy difference
is negligible
compared to how much
heat I'm adding.
We say that 2-3,
it's isobaric
constant pressure.
Good. 4-5, I run
pipes into that,
they communicate.
It's diathermal.
I can transfer heat in,
but they don't communicate
in terms of pressure.
So H four is not the same
as H three or H two, okay?
All I'm saying is that
I'm adding heat 4-5,
and 4-5, it's the
same pressure.
So four to five, I
have the same
pressure, okay?
Again, because it's
a heat exchanger,
and for heat exchangers,
from the inlet
to the outlet,
we assume in this class,
no pressure drop.
No pressure drops,
one oh six.
Yes, please, Cody.
If we were not given,
would we be able to make
the assumption that
saturated If I don't
have the pressure
at state three,
I don't believe I can
solve this problem.
I need really a firm state
to start with and then use
this isentropic
assumptions because
basically by having
state three,
I know the pressure
at state two.
And by assuming the
pump is isentropic,
I know that the
specific entropy
here is the same as here.
It's like with the
pressure here and
assuming this isentropic,
I know state two.
I was just saying
there's that
doesn't solve just want to
know that
saturated At the
exit of a condenser,
it's a saturated liquid.
I'm telling you that
that's best
practice, right?
No, it will be
compressed, right?
You can't see it
on this diagram,
but you would see it here.
One to two here is
I am increasing
my pressure,
which means that I'm
moving more into this.
This is an exaggeration,
though, right?
It's an incompressible
substance.
So when I put
that work in,
not much really
changes there.
That's why when I plot
it on a real plot,
you can't see the
difference 1-2.
They pretty much are
on top of each other.
But it is a
little bit away
from the saturated
liquid line.
Okay?
Other questions?
Yes, please.
This determines the limit.
The limit is Carne.
You cannot do
better than Carne.
All we're doing with
these tricks and stuff
is essentially extending,
we're extending basically
the temperature
where we transfer
heat in, right?
So one way to view
this is by doing
this process of the
zigzag here, excuse me.
I'm transferring
heat in from
a higher temperature
compared to here, right?
So basically,
the average
temperature where I'm
transferring heat
into this cycle
is higher because
I'm doing this.
That's the trick. Or,
like I said before,
lowering the temperature
where transfer heat out.
But at the end of
it, everything
is limited by Carne.
So you'll never be able to
do better than 38.4%.
Seems like a pretty
bad grade, huh?
I don't want to take
that class. Alright, I'm
going to start erasing
and then go on, alright?
I have taken those kinds
of classes, but yeah.
Alright. Um do do do.
So when you see this,
it looks cumbersome,
but step by step,
like a marathon.
If you think about
the whole thing,
you'll shut down.
But if you see it
and you stick to
fundamentals and
just remember
it's one step at a time,
everything is
possible, okay?
And just like a marathon,
don't go too fast
at the beginning,
you know, you can
trip. Alright.
Okay.
Okay. Great.
All right. So that
was reheat, okay?
And again, the whole point
was extending that region
where we transfer the heat
in from a higher
temperature.
We can also do
regeneration, all right?
And remember, in
regeneration,
the whole point of
regeneration is I
want to increase
the temperature
of my fluid
before dumping heat
into it, right?
I want the temperature at
the inlet to my boiler
to be higher, right?
In Brighton, that's
what we did, right?
We tried to increase
the temperature
of the fluid
prior to entering
the combustor by warming
it up with exhaust
gases, all right?
That's what we did.
So this is what
it looks like,
one way it can
look like for
a ranking cycle, right?
So let's start from
let's start from the
second pump, okay?
So the second pump,
that's not too dissimilar,
except that it's state
four now, but fine.
So I leave the pump,
I go into my boiler,
I pass through my
turbine, all right?
And what you have here at
the turbine is you have
two exits, two exits.
One that goes to
the condenser.
Passes through
the pump and
goes into the box
and then continues.
And then another
one at state six,
which does not pass
through the condenser,
which means that
it stays warm?
So you bleed off some
of the steam from
the turbine and you mix it
with you mix it
with some of the,
the compressed
water that's
coming out of
the first pump.
This is an open
feed water heater,
okay? And they mix.
We haven't done this,
I think, really
much in this class,
but this is a case where
I have two streams in,
they mix and there's
one leaving, all right?
Okay. But this one
shouldn't shock you.
There's no work here in
or out, and
it's adiabatic.
What it means is that
I have an M dot,
some M dot coming into
here with an enthalpy.
I have some M dot coming
in here with an enthalpy.
The sum of those
two M dots is
my original M dot times
another enthropy?
Um, So that's the one
thing that's new.
The second thing
that's new is
the way that we
describe the fraction.
Let's say the
turbine steady flow,
I have some dot going
through my pump,
through my boiler, and
entering my turbine.
The way that these
problems are stated is
that there's a fraction
Y, let's say 0-1,
a fraction that is Y
of that dot
that goes here,
and there's a
fraction dot times
one minus Y that goes
into here, okay?
So mixing and then
fractions of mass. David.
Why do we need
a water heater?
I'm going to show you.
Okay. I'll show you. Okay.
Yeah, and
so this is what the
cycle looks like.
If you were to shot
on a TS diagram,
you have one to two to
well, let's focus
on this, right?
So if I had just the
normal three, four,
five, you know, let's
say, three, four, 571.
So that's the, you know,
cycle that essentially
looks like that.
The new thing is then the
three to six that you,
um, that you have, okay?
But remember, the
whole point of this,
David, is that I,
through this process,
want to increase
the temperature
at state four before
I start dumping
heat into it.
So the whole point
is that, like,
when I do my heat
addition from my boiler,
I don't want to
dump it in at
a temperature at state
two, which is low.
I'd love to dump it into
something that's
at state four,
which is warmer, okay?
So that's why we do
it. Yes, please.
Will you be able to change
the condenser to adjust
the temperature?
I'm not sure I
understand the question.
Say it again.
Um Okay. All right.
So I will speed
through this one,
but in short,
right, we can go
step by step here
through the problem.
Maybe I'll just jump
to this in the
interest of time.
So what you
have All right,
so let's go to
what's given.
What's given is
that the quality at
the exit of
the open feed water
heater is zero.
So it's a saturated
liquid there.
To Cody's point.
So why is that?
Because at state two, I
am not saturated
anymore, right?
I have compressed
that liquid there.
And so when I mix it then
with this warmer steam,
what's going to
exit is then
a saturated liquid, okay?
So that's one thing.
So the saturated liquid,
we know State five,
so at the exit of
the boiler, right,
we have complete
information there.
Good. We're told
the pressure at
the exit of the turbine
prior to entering
the condenser.
So we're given that.
And we're also
given the pressure.
Of the let's say
the bleed line.
So basically the steam
that we're bleeding off,
we're also given
that pressure.
And we know because
this is a condenser,
at state one, we are
a saturated liquid.
And this is
allowed, right,
X three and X one
are allowed to be
zero because of the fact
that I transfer work here,
and I'm compressing
the liquid, okay?
So at state two, I am
not a saturated liquid.
And what you want to
determine here is
the fraction of the steam
that you have to take off,
that you have
to bleed out of
the turbine Y, okay?
And then what
is the thermal
efficiency of this cycle?
What assumptions
do you make, okay?
So we can start with
doing the analysis of
the turbine, okay?
So it's an ideal
regenerative.
This means that
the turbine
is adiabatic
and reversible.
It means that the
entropy at the exit of
the turbine is the
same as the inlet.
So S six is S five,
and S seven is
also S five, okay?
But they're two
different states
because they have two
different pressures.
But you know state six and
you know state
seven, okay?
Because you know
state seven, you
know the pressure at
state seven, right?
Condenser is a
heat exchanger,
so P one is equal
to p7x1 was given.
Now I know state
one, all right?
Okay. This open feed
water heater, right?
It's a mixing
chamber, right?
Just like a
heat exchanger,
there are not going
to be pressure drops
across these
devices, right?
So because I know
the pressure because I
know state six and
another pressure,
I'm going to know
the pressure at
state three at the exit,
and I'm also going
to know the pressure
at the inlet,
the other inlet.
So P two is also
P six, right?
Because the pump
is isentropic,
S two is S one, now
I know state two.
Because we were
given X three,
and now we know
P three from
this, you know
state three.
If you go on
to state four,
the pump operates
isentropically S
four is S three.
Because the boiler
is a heat exchanger,
P four is equal to P five.
So now I got state four.
State five was given.
I know all of my states.
I have all of my
states here now.
What I will write out,
and I'll spend time in is
the analysis of the
open feed water heater.
So the open feed
water heater
looks like this.
All right.
And this is important
to be able to define.
So I have one inlet,
I have another inlet,
and I have one outlet.
This is adiabatic,
and there's no
work transfer,
all right? So let's
look at this.
I have here, state six,
which is entering, right?
I have a let's do our
mass balance first.
So the mass balance
here is I have
an M dot times
Y. I have an M dot times
one minus Y entering,
and then here I
have an M dot.
Conservation of mass.
The same thing now
for conservation
of energy,
okay? Right?
So neglecting
kinetic energy
and potential
energy changes
in this process, right?
I have an M dot
times Y times H six,
which carries me in an
M dot times one minus
Y times H two, which
is carrying me in.
And then I have
an M dot times
H three, which is out.
So this plus this
must equal to
this. All right?
O. So dot times
Y six plus dot
times one minus
Y times H two
must be equal to m
dot times H three.
Our dots are going
to drop, okay?
And so what we
will have is
Y age six plus H
two minus Y H
two is a three.
We reorganize for Y,
Y times age six
minus H two
is equal to age
three minus H two,
Y is equal to H
three minus H two
divided by age
six minus H two.
Because I know
all my states,
I can solve for
this Y here, okay?
Good. Let me go back.
The thermal efficiency
of this cycle
is going to be the same as
every other one that
we've done, right?
The heat in, right,
one minus Q out divided
by Q in, right?
You would know
the Q out, right?
Essentially,
you'd have dot,
one minus Y times H
seven minus H one, okay?
And your heat
in is going to
be dot, just dot,
and that's going
to be times
H five minus H four, okay?
Are there questions
about this?
I hope the only
radical thing I
said here was about
the mixing chamber,
but with this,
you're able to
define the why,
and then that's
the one thing that
was different
compared to the
other problems.
All right. That's
what it looks like
on a TS diagram.
That's what it
would look like
on a PV diagram.
With this, you should
be able to analyze
these regenerative and
reheat power cycles.
We'll continue with
our last one there.
After the next lecture,
that closes Module two,
and that's all
the material that
you're responsible
for on Qiz two.
If you have questions,
I'm up here.
Otherwise, have a
wonderful weekend.