I got 210 entropy.
Yeah, so basically, we're
going to look
at some aspects
of change in entropy
ideal gases.
We're going to
look at especially
in the isentropic process.
These have two
examples today and
show you how that's
useful for, like,
understanding work
in or workout
of steady flow
devices, all right?
Then we'll also
derive some
deriving equation.
All right. So an
isentropic process, right?
So before We had this,
we said changes in
entropy were equal to
an amount of heat
transferred in,
divided by temperature,
and amount of heat
transferred out divided
by temperature.
So the first part of
calling something like
isotropic is that there's
no heat transfer.
That's step one.
The second thing
is imagine that
the device operates
reversibly,
no friction, right?
You don't have
anything that's
very far from equilibrium.
So if you see
something like, Hey,
this is adiabatic
and it's reversible,
that should trigger
something in
your head to say
isotropic, right?
So those are keywords
that allow you
to be there.
But an adiabatic
process is not
necessarily an isotropic
process, okay?
And the same for something
like reversible.
A device could be
operating reversibly,
but I could be
transferring
heat into it, okay?
And that second one
we'll classify and
call is actually we'll
give a terminology,
and I'll call that
one as, like,
what's called
internally reversible.
This whole thing operates
perfectly and reversibly,
but maybe I'm
adding heat or
taking heat out
of it, okay?
Um, All right,
so that's the part about
isentropic, right?
The second thing
is that entropy
is a property, right?
So just like enthropy,
if I think about a
fluid, so if you look
up here at this, if I
think about the fluid,
the fluid can have
a property of
an enthropy when it
enters an internal energy,
a pressure,
specific volume,
and also an entropy.
So it can have an
entropy, right?
And when something
is, let's
say in this steady
flow device,
if this is operating
isentropically,
the entropy
specific entropy
of the steam entering here
is going to be equal to
the specific entropy
of the steam leaving.
And that is very,
very useful, okay?
This is going to
make it possible for
us in very, like,
easy ways to analyze
power plants and
devices later, okay?
And again, just to
remind you before,
when something is
operating like this,
this is the
theoretical limit
of performance, right?
So we're doing this.
We're thinking about
theoretical limits.
Later on, we'll talk
about some ways and
account for the
fact that things,
you know, life is
imperfect, okay?
So we'll account
for that later.
But today, life's perfect.
Cool. So an example.
So here I'm showing
you a very
important device.
This is a turbine, right?
So this is what you
would see, again,
you know, here,
the work transferred
out here.
What would be what is
transferred to, like,
a generator and
electricity production
in a thermoelectric
power plant.
You're given inlets.
So this is
superheated steam.
That's a high
pressure, and
that's a very
high temperature.
So you have superheated
steam that's
entering here,
work transferred out,
no heat transferred in,
and, you know, the
outlet pressure.
And this is a reversible
adiabatic turbine,
right?
So the entropy of
the fluid specific
entropy of
the fluid exiting
is equal here.
What does that look
like on a TS diagram?
So here you have the
saturated shinom
on a TS diagram, so
temperature entropy.
Here you are at
high pressure,
and then dropping
to the low, again,
along this line of
constant entropy.
When you leave
here, you're still
a superheated vapor.
So let's get into
it. All right.
Okay.
I'm not going to
redraw the diagram.
You see here where
the control volume,
where the control
volume is
defined at state
one entering
and state two exiting.
All right. And here,
the goal that we want
to get out is the work
transferred out
per unit mass.
So what we're calling
is W out here is equal to
W dot out divided by
the mass flow rate of
this entering, right?
I have one inlet, I have
one exit, right there.
Okay? So what we assume,
is that we can neglect
All right, KE and P,
similar elect
kinetic energy
and potential
energy changes,
so Delta KE and
Delta P. Let me
make sure that
looks good. Um.
We cannot treat this as
an ideal gas properties
determined from
Pi K. We're not
going to apply
the ideal gas equation
to a steam turbine.
We're going to assume
it's reversible, right?
So it's a
reversible process,
reversible plus
adiabatic, okay?
Adiabatic, which
basically implies
that it's isotropic.
All right, that
steady flow.
It's a steady flow device,
steady flow,
right, which means
that, you know,
changes in the mass
of the control
volume is zero,
and changes in
the energy of
the control volume is
also equal to zero.
And we'll switch over.
This marker is dead.
We'll move over
into red now.
I All right.
We have a single inlet
and outlet, right?
Single inlet plus
outlet there.
All right? Cool.
So our physical laws,
the physical laws that
we'll write here, right?
So the first is the
conservation of mass.
So dmCv dt right
is equal to m.in.
Minus M dot out.
Let me see how that looks.
That looks pretty good.
M dot out, because
this is steady flow,
this is going
to go to zero.
And what this implies is
that dot is equal to m.in,
which is equal to M dot
out to do the same thing
for the conservation
of energy,
dcvdt is equal to
e.in minus E dot out.
Steady flow this
goes to zero.
So your e.in is equal to
your E dot out
there. Yeah.
All right. Underneath
this. All right.
So the ways we can
transfer energy in again,
write w.in plus our
q.in plus our M dot.
Remember this is m.in,
but that's equal to
M dot, Enthal P one,
state one is entering
plus velocity
one squared divided
by two plus gz one,
the potential energy is
equal to your W dot out,
plus your Q dot out.
Plus M dot out,
which is just M
dot, enthalpy two,
which is at the
exit velocity two
squared divided
by two, gz two.
Kinetic terms are gone,
adiabatic heat
terms are gone,
and we don't have work in.
This is workout. O W dot
out here is equal to
our M dot times H
one minus H two.
You can check if
this makes sense.
You would expect
the enthalpy
of the steam entering
the turbine to be higher
than that exiting.
There's basically
more energy in
the steam when
it's coming in
and you want to
extract that.
H one should be
greater than H two.
We have the M dot. What
we're interested in,
though, is W dot out
divided by M dot.
So if we then
take that dot,
and we shift it to
the other side,
right? That's what
we have, right?
So the work
transferred out on
a per mass basis
from the turbine is
equal to the
difference from
the enthalpy at the inlet.
Basically the
enthropy at the inlet
minus the enthropy at
the exit there, right?
So that's super,
super simple, right?
But we know H one.
So let's talk about
some properties here.
So H one state
one State one,
we know P one is equal
to our five MPA.
We know that T
one is equal to
our 450 degrees
C. And from this,
we can get enthropy one
and also entropy
one, okay?
So the specific enthropy
and the specific entropy.
So for State two, All
we know is the pressure.
Right now, P two is
equal to 1.4 MPA?
And S two specific
enthalpy at state
two is equal to
the specific enthalpy
at state one, okay?
Because this is isotropic.
And this is not
complete information.
So pressure with
specific entropy
means that I also then
know enthalpy two, right?
You can use PKolor,
plug this in.
There was a question
before about
what unit if you
want to put this in for
Picor, how could
you declare this?
So if I said
something like,
let's say, Um, right?
Maybe ST two is equal
to h dot state,
all of my substance.
So here I'd have
water. All right.
Right? I have my
P. So the P here
is then equal to
what is that?
That's 1.4 comma.
And you can put in
quotes M PA and for S,
if you wanted to put
that in here, right,
you could just
put in the value
that you would
have for S two.
So we get S two.
And then in here, it
would be kilojoules.
It's basically a
little K. So you'd
have, um, All right.
Kilojoules per
kilogram space
Kelvin like that.
All right. I'll update
this later in
the readme file,
but you can also declare
units for this for
enthalpy, like that, okay?
So you'd have this,
you'd have the H two.
And then when you
substitute you
can go in and substitute
some numbers.
So if we substitute it
then write this W dot
out divided by M
dot being equal to
H one minus H two.
What I have as
a value is 350,
then kilojoules per
kilogram as an answer.
The thing to reflect
on is, again,
that this is adiabatic
and reversible,
and that allows
you then to
set the entropies
equal and
determine state two,
namely enthalpy two.
Cool. Questions
about that?
And that's why you
care about entropy
because it makes
it easy, right?
This makes it easy to
analyze and at least
understand what will be
maximum performance
that can
be had out of your device.
Yes, please.
Define so let me just
be clear, right?
So if I define right,
if I define state one,
what I'm defining in Pi or
is an object called
ST one, right?
So if I define
ST one, right,
S one is equal to
St one dots, right?
And then if I
know that, then
I just put it in.
So you could
also just write,
you know, St
one dots here.
And then what you need
to understand is that
the default unit of this
is like what's
in the textbook,
which is kilojoules
per kilogram kelvin.
So the outputs are set,
but then you
can convert to
whatever unit would
you would want,
and then you would just
declare what that unit
is if you want it
as an input, okay?
Or just default and say,
Hey, you know, I
live dangerously.
I'm just going to
put kilojoules
per kilogram per kelvin.
I know that,
I'm just going
to write it
without the unit.
But I advise
always write in
the unit because you
get to reflect and think,
you know, am I
doing the right
thing? All right.
Other questions?
Great. So now,
a derivation.
So everything that
I just showed
you right there
is enough to
now start analyzing so
I just showed you
the vapor cycle.
And with that approach
that I just showed you,
it's totally valid to
analyze air cycles
the same way,
compressors and
that, right?
So you can use Pi
killer and do it.
What I'm going to
do now is something
that for ideal gases
allows you not to
need property
tables, right?
And this basically
develops out of the fact
that before it was
a pain in the neck to,
like, look up properties.
So if you read
the book chapter,
we're going to talk about
these things called
TDS relation.
So I'm going to see if
I can find a black.
Nope, they took everything.
That's awesome.
Okay. That is, like,
empty. That's amazing.
It's amazing. Here we go.
The goods. All right.
That's better. Okay.
Um Yeah, so the context
of this is think this
is going to be a
useful formula
that may make my life
even easier
when I analyze,
like, compressors, jet
engines, gas turbines.
That's the
mindset they have
for the following
derivation.
Okay, so entropy
differential relations.
Okay, do. Okay.
So before I get into
the first step of this is,
we want to show is
basically for
an ideal gas,
that for an
isotropic process,
we can relate things
like temperature,
pressure and
specific volume.
So think like
a compressor.
I know the temperature
and the pressure upstream.
I know the pressure
downstream.
I would like to know
the temperature
downstream, okay?
There's going to be
a formula for that.
And why do I care
about temperatures?
Because differences
in enthalpy
for an ideal gas are what?
You're going to do amazing
on quiiz one. Yes, please.
That's it. Functions
of temperature.
So if I get
Delta Ts across
these devices with
a constant CP,
I know changes
in enthal peak.
Bang bang, okay? So
that's the mindset.
It's going to be a
tool that allows you
to rapidly get
the temperatures
upstream or downstream
of a device. Okay.
Step one. Now, I told
you before, right,
that dq divided by
T was by definition,
equal to ds.
And that is true
for these devices.
If they don't
themselves generate
entropy, okay?
So remember, if I take
a device and I have a lot
of friction there, right?
I'm going to be
generating entropy
from that, right?
I'm going to
heat from that
heat's going to be
transferred in,
it's going to be a
mess, all right?
So to calculate, then
the change in entropy
for such a device,
when I add heat to
it or take heat out,
I'm going to call
this as internally
reversible, all right?
So the device can have
changes in entropy,
but those changes in
entropy are only
going to be due to me
bringing heat in
or heat out and
not due to friction, okay?
Stay with me.
Maybe the weirdest part
of the course, all right?
I got two subscripts.
Um, So, yeah,
an internally
reversible process
is one without
irreversibility.
So no friction within
the device, right?
So if this is like a
compressor within here,
everything is
isothermal, right?
So I have no friction
inside of this.
It's reversible, right?
This is my happy place,
okay? That's in here.
Any temperature differences
in all of that,
all that stuff exists
outside of my boundary.
That's the meaning
of internally, um,
uh, uh, reversible, okay?
All right. So that's
the first thing.
Now we'll start with
the first first law here.
All right.
So the first law for
this then is going to be
the change in
internal energy is
equal to the change in
heat transferred for
an internally
reversible process
minus the change in
the work transferred,
also for an internally
reversible process,
okay?
And for, like, a
simple system,
so think of like
a piston, right?
So if we think
about a piston,
you know, no
mass in or out,
um, And this piston,
let's say the substance
in there is compressible.
Let's say it's like air,
right? It's an ideal gas.
The only kind of work
that this can do
is PDV work, okay?
So if it's
reversible, right,
it would be PDV, right?
You can think about
other types of work like
electrical work
transferred
in, but that's
not reversible.
I pass electrons
through that.
I'm going to get heat.
That's not reversible.
So the only kind
of work then there
I can do for
a simple compressible
system is P PdV.
This from the
formula up here then
is nothing but TDS
we're going to write
d is an equal to TdS
minus PdV
for an internally
reversible process.
Do, do, do. We can
rearrange this,
and we say ds is
equal to d plus P dv.
We can divide both
sides by mass,
and then I can write
this as dS is equal to
d plus P d little
V. All right.
There's two forms that
we're going to use.
So this is one that's
going to be useful.
We have another one
that involves enthalpy.
So for that,
let's say recall.
Recall that H is
equal to U plus pv.
If I take the
differential of this,
I can have d is equal
to dh is equal to d plus
P dv plus V dp, some
chain rule there.
If I rearrange this
as a function of d,
I can then do a
substitution.
So d is equal to
dh minus pdv minus
V dp. All right.
Substitute that
into there,
and I can have then
T ds is equal to
d minus pdv minus
V dp plus pdv.
And so it's going
to go away, right?
This is going to go,
and then this
is going to go.
And so then our
Tds relation,
another one will be ds
is equal to dh minus V dp.
The All right.
And so what's nice
about this is right,
changes in entropy, right,
which we can't
measure, right?
So ds is then going to
be related to things
that might be knowable
or might be able to
be looked up, right?
DH divided by T minus V dp
also divided by T. Okay?
So for the ideal
gas, so remember,
the type of system we're
interested in here
compressible system,
a simple
compressible system.
And at this point,
we're going
to declare ideal gas.
So for an ideal
gas, um, right?
We know that changes in
enthalpy are
equal to Cp dt.
And the substitution
that I want to
make is going to be
for specific
volume, right?
So then I know
that pv equals RT,
so that means V is equal
to RT divided by P,
where R is the specific
gas constant, right?
So dh into here,
and V into there.
And so what you'll
have then is
ds is equal to
cp dt divided by
T. We can integrate
that now,
and then minus, right,
Rt divided by P times V
divided by T
dp, all right?
Temperatures go
away. And again,
this is, what
did I do wrong?
What did I do
wrong? I should
not have a V because I
substituted in
for V, right?
So I substitute
to VRT by P.
The one over T
stays there with
the dp and so what
you in the end
then is R let me just
write it out ds is
equal to Cp dt
divided by T minus R,
dp divided by P, okay?
And then we can
integrate, right?
So we can basically
integrate this.
This is straightforward.
Let's say from state
one to state two.
R is a constant,
so I can pull
that out of the
integral from P
one to P two.
And then here, we have to
make a decision, right?
So I could write the
integral like this.
Specifically does
depend on temperature,
not very strongly
in the regions that
we care about in this
class, but it does.
So I can integrate
this 1-2.
And then what I
would have to do is
I'd have to take an
average value, right,
or I'd have to
essentially have CP
as a function of
temperature and
integrate, right?
We're practical
people, okay?
And I'm an engineer,
and I like things
to be easy,
at least in my
first attempt.
So I'll say this.
And then what you'll
do is you'll just say
that the CP is a constant.
I like to take the value
of the specific heats at
the temperature
that I start from.
A lot of times
in this class,
you're going to
hear us take
essentially this value at
room temperature
condition.
For engines, we call that
the cold air assumption,
cold air assumption there.
So you just do that
because we want
life to be easy, right?
And so with that
integration, right,
I'm going to have S one or
S two minus little S one.
Is equal to cp,
the natural log
of T two divided by T one
minus the specific gas
constant R times P
two divided by P
one, all right?
And that's our first
relation there, okay.
Okay, we can also
remember that for
an ideal gas,
the d is equal to CV dt.
Let me see. Am I
off the board?
I think I'm off the board.
CV dt.
Let me at the state,
I'll turn that off.
Okay. So CV dt.
And instead of
writing this as
a function of a
specific volume,
I can do it for
pressure, right?
P is equal to rt divided
by specific volume.
Okay. Okay. So if I
have the TDS, right?
So if we have
the Tds relation
that is here, so
that original one.
So what I can
say is the Tds T
d little S is equal
to d plus pdv.
So the d is then
Cv dt plus P dv.
So the P here then is
R T divided by V dv, okay?
You can divide both
sides by temperature.
So T, T and T.
And if we do that,
this T is gone.
All right. And of course,
this T is also
gone. All right.
And so we'll have ds
is equal to Cv dt by
T plus R dv
by V. Can integrate
from state one to two.
Here. Again, I could
write the integral here,
but today I want
life to be easy.
This is the happy place,
stay one to two here,
and then R is a constant.
This is one to two.
And so then little S
two minus little S
one is equal to
CV natural log
of T two by T
one plus a specific
gas constant,
natural log of V two
divided by V one.
That's our
second relation.
All right. All right.
And so what you do next,
again, because we're
interested in, right,
as I said before,
we're going to
assume isentropic.
And with isentropic,
I'm going to be
able to rate
temperature to volume
from state one
to state two,
temperature to pressure.
And with those
two equations,
pressure to volume.
So what we're going to do
is we're going
to set S two
minus S one, two,
Zero, right?
That's great.
Took the words
out of my mouth. I
like that, right?
So if we do that four,
so we can start with our
temperature and
pressure one.
So if we do that,
right, we're
going to have CP,
natural log of T two by T
one is equal to
specific gas constant,
natural log of P two
divided by P one, right?
You can divide
both sides by CP?
I could write
here, R divided by
CP gets rid of that.
And because this is a uh,
uh, write a
coefficient here,
this is essentially
the same as R
divided by CP, okay?
And because now it's a
natural log on both sides,
natural log can
now go away, okay?
So what you're left
with then is T two by T
one is equal to
pressure two divided
by pressure one,
gas constant divided
by specific heat.
And we can do
the same thing
for our other
formula, right?
So CV, natural log of T
two divided by T one
is equal then to
the negative of R,
natural log of V two
divided by V one.
Okay, we divide
this by CV.
So both sides we
can divide by
CV. So this goes away.
It's a natural log,
I can put this to
the exponent, right?
So I can go negative
R divided by CV.
All right. And now I
have natural logs.
So now natural
logs can go away.
So I have one
relation, I have two.
And because T two by
T one is equal
to here, right?
I can have them
be equal, okay?
So the take
home message is
for the isotropic
processes, right?
It can relate upstream
and downstream, you know,
let's say, the ratio
the temperatures
upstream and
downstream to ratios of
the pressures to some
constants, right?
So properties
that we assume,
let's say, at T one.
The same thing
for temperatures
to specific volumes.
And because these two are
the same on the
left hand side,
you can go pressures to
specific volumes
as well, right?
And the name of
the game in this
analysis, though,
is usually to get to
temperatures because
differences in temperatures
in compressors,
gas turbines tells us
differences in enthalpy,
which tells us what?
Work in, work out.
That's what you
care about.
All right?
Cool. You can do
some simplification.
I'm going to spare
you it here.
If you click on, you know,
if you click on the link
there, it can take
you through it.
But, um, convenient
ways that we can,
um, represent this
are the following.
The first is
that instead of
writing things
like R and CV,
we can recognize
that R is equal
to Cp minus CV, right?
That's the first thing.
So the specific heat
at constant pressure minus
the specific heat for
constant volume is equal
to the gas constant.
The second thing is
that we're going to
talk about a constant K,
which is then Cp
divided by CV?
This is the
adiabatic index.
This came up before
when we were
doing adiabatic
expansion, right?
So this is, um,
the same constant.
If you read other things
other than your textbook,
things on the Internet,
sometimes this
adiabatic index is
also written with a
variable Gamma there,
but the book uses K or
Kappa for that, all right?
So again, with
some math and
some rearranging,
which you can have then
are the following.
So T two divided by T one,
is equal to P two
divided by P one
to the K minus
one divided by a minus
one divided by Kappa,
there T two
divided by T one
is equal to V one
divided by V two,
and then this
is to the Kapa
minus one minus one,
And then, again, if
you set these things
equal and you rearrange,
what you can
show is that P
two divided by
P one is equal
to V one divided by V
two to the K or
Kappa. All right.
More generally, again, you
could rearrange this to be
that all on one side would
be temperature
one pressure one,
all on the other side is
temperature two
pressure two,
or in the case of
something like the PV,
like we did for the
adiabatic problem,
I could put p1v1 to
the K on the
left hand side,
and it's equal
to a constant.
What this implies here
is that pressure,
volume to the K is
equal to a constant,
as we did before, but
you could also
show from this.
What we did not show
before are the other two.
So temperature
times pressure to
the one minus K
divided by K is also
equal to a constant.
And temperature times
specific volume to
the K minus one is also
equal to a constant,
all right?
And again, these hold
four ideal gases
and right,
ist isentropic
processes, okay?
And these will be useful
when we do things
like I said,
the gas turbine analysis,
which is called
Brayton cycles
when we get into
the jet propulsion,
especially the
temperature and
the pressure ratio here.
That's that's a
pretty handy formula.
Questions about
that? Yes, please.
What do you think?
I mean, some molecules
have more than that.
Some things are
also solid, right?
Yeah. Yes, of
course, it depends.
CP here, right?
So this CP is our units
of kilojoules
per kilogram.
Kelvin the same
for the CV.
Yeah, that definitely
depends on
the substance, and
you can call this.
So remember before
we did Pi kilo.
So if you had, let's say,
a state one defined,
if you went dot CP or
you did St dot CV,
it will spit out
these constants.
So you can call this,
and then if you just
take the ratio of them,
you have the Adiabatic
index from it, okay?
The questions? Good. Yes,
please. Just to clarify.
Yeah, so the units of
this are kilojoules
per kilogram
Kelvin, right?
Which here would
mean that it is.
If you wanted to
convert that to
the universal,
you would know
the molecular weight
of your substance,
and you could
recover R, okay?
Maybe since we're on the
subject of talking
about this,
you can also see the
following, right?
You can see the universal
gas constant being
written to the
specific heat
on a molar basis,
minus specific heat at
constant volume
on a molar basis.
And this holds then for
all ideal gases, okay?
So RUCp minus CV
there for the monotonic
gases is like that.
I don't really, you know,
I'm only mentioning
it since you
brought it up and
triggered me with it,
but you can look into it.
But yeah, this is then
the specific gas constant.
Okay? Other questions?
Yes, please.
In the play by play.
So the play by
play here is that
what I'm saying
with this first
statement is
for a process,
the only types of changes
in entropy can be for me
transferring heat in or
out, internally
reversible there.
You write the first law
with this first law
written in this format,
assuming that I have this
compressible system
internally reversible.
I don't have any friction.
The type of work I can do
is boundary work, PDV,
and the way that entropy
can change there is TDS,
keep being transferred
in and out,
and that's equal to DU.
So first law
written now and
a second law of
way, all right?
Um, this, I'm just
repeating it.
This I'm dividing by mass.
This, I'm telling you
a definition of enthalpy.
Here I'm doing chain rule.
Here I'm substituting
that chain rule
back into this,
and I'm just writing
one version of what's
called the TDS equation.
Or if you like to
write old guy names,
you can it the
Gibbs equation.
But I like TDS. That's
my old man's initials.
So TDS is there.
Um, So you've got that.
I rearrange now because
what I'm interested
in is changes just
in the property
of entropy.
Here, I want to relate
changes in entropy to
changes in
properties I can
measure, things
that I care about.
So I do that here.
I divide by
temperature, fine.
Now I got a bunch of
things that I
can't integrate.
I need to substitute in,
for dH CP dT,
because that makes
that integrable.
And then with V, I have
an equation of state.
I have the ideal gas
I substitute in.
And ultimately, what
I get is changes in
entropy related to
things I can measure.
And then I say, I
want this to be
isotropic because I want
to talk about the
maximum possible.
And now I can
relate temperature
to pressure with
constants that I know.
And that's
convenient. It was
especially convenient
when you had tables.
When you had to do
tables and look it up,
this was like,
Whoa. Oh, my God.
I only want to
work with air,
you know, forget water.
All right? So that's
one approach that you
can get one formula
from that, right?
But we also know
that changes in
internal energy can be
related to changes in
temperature through CV,
another constant
that we know, okay?
And it turns out
that if we can write
a second equation
where changes in
entropy are
temperatures in
specific volumes,
set that to zero.
Now I can relate
temperature to
specific volume for a
reversible process.
All I got to know is
some constants that I can
look up or, uh,
even easier.
And then everything
after that
is me just mathing
it, right?
So everything after
that is some math.
And then saying that, boy,
writing R and CP and CV
is kind of annoying.
Remember before
when we had
that PV polytropic
process to the K,
I kind of like K
or Kappa, okay?
That's a choice.
You don't have to
make that choice,
but someone made
that choice.
So we have Kappa
that's there.
And essentially,
we recover
that adiabatic equation,
PV to the K is equal
to a constant,
and then two
other formulas
or one other formula
that we have and
another one that
emerges because we set
those two original
equations
equal to each other.
But the name of the game
is that I can relate
measurable properties
to each other,
assuming that it is
isotropic and
an ideal gas,
which is relevant
for engines.
So any engine
that runs on air,
you know, propulsion,
all of that,
these hold for
the ideal cases.
And we can get into, okay,
what if it's
not isentropic?
Yeah, we'll get
to there next,
but this is the
step. Is that clear?
Yes, please. David, right?
David. Yes. Thank you.
Are we going to them?
I don't care. Just be
consistent, you know?
If you like it, do it.
But just be consistent.
I can translate.
Other questions?
But just know that in
the book, it's Kapp.
In the book, it's KappA.
And when you look
it up in the book,
it's also KappA, right?
And you won't be able
to call that with P Kalre.
What you can call
with Pi Kilo
is you can call CP and CV.
And so then K or
Kappa or Gamma,
in your case would
be defined then as
the ratio of
the two, okay?
Look, you know, if
you want physics,
it's a great
place, but you
crossed that road, okay?
Fine. And this
building, these people,
I feel maybe are
closer to us as
engineers than they
are to the physicists.
So this is more of a Kappa
crowd than maybe a Gamma.
Okay. Other
questions? These are
nice questions. Okay.
And so, you know, what
does this look like?
So remember
before we wrote
this PV diagram for
the Karno cycle.
So for the ideal gas
Karno cycle there,
what I'm plotting now
is that same thing,
and I'm computing
temperature and
entropy based on
those relations.
All right. And
so what you'll
see in the end is
that this is going to
draw a rectangle because
that's exactly what
Karno is, isn't it?
A Karno is a transfer heat
in at constant
temperature,
transfer heat out at
constant temperature,
and work transfer
processes
are adiabatic and
reversible, okay?
So isotropic.
So that's why
those, right?
So that would be
your workout,
and that's your
work in, okay?
I'll get played again,
I guess, while I erase.
Cool. Don't answer that,
just sketch.
Cool.
Yeah, and so now I
can show you the
application of that.
And so with this,
I'll show you
two approaches.
So I'll analyze one
using Pi Killor, right?
So what I showed you
for the turbine,
and I'm going to do
another one with
the isotropic relations
that we just did,
and then you can
compare the difference
and the answers
at the end,
and then decide,
you know, do I
feel lucky or not, okay?
When you decide
to do that.
Okay, so what are we
talking about here?
So we have a compressor,
and it runs on nitrogen.
compress a compressor.
So what does a
compressor look like?
It takes something from
high specific volume
and makes it low.
So this would
be, let's say,
like an inlet here.
And then this would
be, let's say,
like an outlet here.
Let's call this
state one in state
two and give it a
control volume.
So I'm going control
volume all right here
in green, like that.
So that's my CV.
And the gas here
is nitrogen.
So N two is what
we're compressing.
What we're told
is that it's
entering at a pressure
of P one is 110 kPa,
so atmospheric
pressure and
a temperature of 30
degrees Celsius,
so a bit of a warm day.
And then it exits at
a pressure of P two,
which is 682 kPa.
Okay? And you're told that
this process is
reversible, okay?
So you're told this is,
uh reversible and that
this compressor
operates adiabatically.
So this is an adiabatic
adiabatic compressor,
which basically means
for us that this
is an isotropic, right.
So it means basically
from S one,
Specific entropy
at state one is
going to be equal to
specific entropy at
state state two, okay?
All right, we're going
to neglect, right?
So we neglect,
changes in E,
neglect changes in
potential energy.
Reversible adiabatic,
it's a steady flow device.
So the steady flow
device, right,
the change in the mass of
the control
volume is zero,
and the change
in the energy of
our control volume is
also equal to zero.
All right. Um All right,
so then your DE, right?
So D MCV dt, right,
m.in minus M dot out,
right? This goes to zero.
So what it
implies is right
M dot is equal to m.in,
is equal to M dot out.
For our energy equation,
DECv dt is e.in
minus E dot out
because it's steady
flow, right?
That goes to zero. So your
e.in is equal to your
e dot out, right?
Okay, for this
to be, right?
So this is a compressor.
So what it means is
that we're going
to have work, right?
That's transferred
in, right?
So I'm going to have
some w.in that's there.
There's my dot
that's entering.
It's adiabatic.
So it means my
q.in is equal to
my Q dot out is
equal to zero.
Our velocities are
essentially zero
in the sense
that they don't contribute
very much to the rate
of energy in and out.
And so we don't have
any workout, right?
So we have w.in plus.h1,
m.h1 is equal to m.h2.
All right, so I
neglect all the
other stuff, right?
And so then when
I rearrange,
I have w dot N is equal to
M dot times H
two minus H one.
That makes sense
because I'd
expect S two to
be at a higher
temperature, right?
I'm compressing that I'
putting energy
through work,
so I'd expect
that to be at
a higher enthalpy
than state one.
And that formula H
two minus H one
reflects that there.
Okay. Mm. So I
can move that.
Blah, blah, blah.
Okay, so for state, so
let's do P Killor style.
So for state
one, State one,
we know P one,
we know T one.
And so what this
means is that we
know S one and
we know H one.
So I can substitute
that H one that I
had into there,
and I can use
information about S one.
For state two, all
we know is P two.
And because from
the assumption
of isentropic,
S two is equal to S one.
And so from this, we
can get to H two, okay?
The other thing I'll
note with this,
because we're going to
use it for the ideal gas,
is that with this
information, you
could also get,
like, a CP,
right, a specific heat
at constant pressure.
You could also
get a CV, right,
a specific heat at
constant at constant
volume, right?
And so with this, right,
that's enough
information to, right,
determine the workout
per unit mass.
So if I go with W dot
N divided by M dot,
right, that's H
two minus H one,
which you would
know from Pi color.
And in this case, what
I'm going to get is
215 kilojoules
per kilogram
with using Pi kilo
for determining
properties.
Okay, but I told
you before we could treat,
you know, if
we assume now.
So if we assume
that nitrogen is
an ideal gas and that this
is an isotropic process.
And I can relate
T two is equal
to T one for an isotropic
process times P
two divided by
P one to the K
minus one divided
by K there.
And again, just
recall that this is
equal to cp divided by CB.
You need to get
this from PCLor.
This is also like at
the very start of
the tables in
the textbook.
All right.
Also, for an ideal gas,
you can remember
that changes in
enthalp for an ideal gas
are equal to Cp times
changes in
temperature, right?
So for us, H two
minus H one is Cp
two minus T one
there, okay?
And if you
substitute numbers
in for that, right?
So then this H two
minus the H one
for the ideal gas,
what I find is
216.7 kilojoules
per kilogram, okay?
So what are we talking?
Half a percent.
So you have half a
percent difference in
the work per unit
mass output of
the compressor
when you assume ideal gas
with specific heats at
the inlet
temperature versus
the case when you
go in and you compute very
accurately the
process, okay?
So the take home message
out of that is that it's
a pretty good
approximation
to do, right,
these approaches.
You know, if you do have
the isentropic
process using this,
relating differences
in enthalpy
to a specific heat
that you select,
let's say,
a T one, the inlet
temperature times that
Delta T gets you a
pretty darn close value,
okay. Better than 2%.
All right? I'll
move this over.
Questions about that?
Yes, please. 216.7.
Yes, please.
Equation for the turbine,
it's on the
equation sheet.
So would you have
to show the process
of getting up to
there on the exam?
You just have to
state assumptions.
I write things in
great detail so
that you can get into the
mental habit of
going through.
But as long as you
say, like, hey,
steady flow, e,
dot, e, dot dot,
neglect heat, right,
neglect workout,
and I come up
with this, that's
perfectly
acceptable to me.
The main thing is that if
I have to partially
grade you
and you don't show me
logic and work,
it's so hard.
And then I get in a
bad mood and I get
grumpy and my
wife's mad at me.
So just show some work.
Other questions?
Okay. So we
are 30 seconds early.
With that, I'm
going to close it.
If you have questions,
I'm up here.