With gas power cycles.
The the final unit
of this today.
After today,
you're going to be
able to analyze
propulsion power
and efficiency
of a jet propulsion cycle.
So a jet engine.
We're going to
talk about this,
and then we'll analyze
the efficiency of
the most efficient
engine that can be done.
And then with this,
we close, and we
move into vapor power.
Okay? All right.
So what is jet propulsion?
So again, On the left
here was kind of our
pinwheel example, right?
We blow air on
a propeller.
We get it to move, we get
shaft work, vice
versa, right?
I can put in shaft work,
rotate this thing
and move air and go.
And essentially, if
you're going to say
this simply with
the propeller,
you want to
accelerate slightly
accelerate a very large
mass of fluid, right?
That's essentially what
a propeller is doing.
Um, if you want to
go much faster,
so if you want to go
faster than the
speed of sound,
okay, this has limits.
Once you get to the
speed of sound,
it doesn't
accelerate anymore.
You need new
mechanisms, okay?
And the strategy here is
essentially you greatly
accelerate a very
small packet of fuel,
right or air, a
very small amount
of air, um, okay?
So what is
the ideal jet propulsion
cycle look like?
So air enters in
here at atmospheric
pressure,
at atmospheric
temperature, right?
And it's moving
with some velocity.
And the way that we're
going to analyze
this is that
we're going to
say that in this
reference frame
it is not moving, okay?
So obviously,
you are moving,
but for the purposes
of this analysis,
we treat the
engine as static,
And the speed that
the jet moves with.
So essentially
the speed of
the aircraft is then
equal to the velocity
of the inlet, okay?
So we have, you know,
velocity coming in at
some relatively fast speed
at T one and T one,
which is atmospheric
pressure
and atmospheric
temperature.
So that goes into
a diffuser, right?
A diffuser slows
this down. Go ahead.
How does it work?
I mean, how does it
work when it's
standing still?
You're not doing
your job then, okay?
So I guess what
you're alluding to is
the startup phase,
basically, the
transients there.
That's not what I'm
doing. Okay? So this
is steady
process, alright?
Do you want to
get unsteady?
It's another class, okay?
Um So essentially,
you have that coming
into a diffuser,
and a diffuser is then
going to decelerate, okay?
So essentially, we're
going to take a lot
of kinetic energy here
and some enthalpy,
and we're going
to slow it down,
which essentially
means you're
going to gain enthalpy
at state two.
Things are going to
heat up a bit, okay?
And we're going
to treat this as
an isentropic process.
State one to two,
we're going to call
this diffuser as an
isentropic nozzle.
What type of flow
was isentropic flow?
So, so the B
ends in noulli.
Okay, so, right,
so basically have
an isotropic
flow from here.
So we have this, you know,
enthalpy and
kinetic energy,
which basically becomes
all enthalpy here, okay?
Then you have
a compressor.
This is going to
operate adiabatically
and reversibly,
which means
isotropically, okay?
So you have an
isotropic compression.
It's going to get even
warmer through this.
So now you're at
a high pressure.
And a moderate
temperature.
Then you have a
combustion chamber, okay?
Then the combustion
chamber.
All right, we're
going to have
at a constant pressure
process of the
heat addition.
So here you're going to
get to a higher
temperature.
Then you're going to run
a turbine, all right?
4-5, that's going to
operate isentropically.
And what's interesting
about this and
what sets this apart from
what we did in Brayton
is that all of
the work that you have
out of the turbine,
you put back into
the compressor.
It's like you have stocks
and you make
money on that,
and you just put all
the money back into
the stocks and
you reinvest.
It's the same thing.
You don't have any,
You don't have
any net shaft work
leaving this device.
You got cue in, okay?
You got cue in, and
you're going to have some
what we're going to
call propulsion power out.
But basically, all the
work out of the turbine
is going to go back
into the compressor
and compress the
fluid, okay?
Good. Five to six then,
this is a nozzle, right?
So entering the
nozzle, right,
you're going to have
a lot of enthalpy
and not very much
kinetic energy.
And what you're going
to then do there
is to have an
isotropic flow,
where then you have
some enthalpy and
a lot of kinetic energy,
okay, at the exit.
And that's the whole
point because at
the end of this, right,
you're going to
want a um a force
or a propulsive power
to drive this, okay?
So you really want to,
you know, up speed
things up here.
Okay? Cool. So let's go
through now that I've
set you up on that,
let's go through
the analysis here.
I'll give you
some numbers.
So again, similarly,
I'll give you some
numbers and also
derive into the
analysis of how
we arrive at efficiency.
So, you say you
have a turbojet,
a turbo jet aircraft
flying with a velocity
the aircraft equal to
260 meters/second.
Let me just check my
writing. It looks good.
At an altitude where
the pressure so we'll
call it P zero for now,
but then we'll
set it to P one.
We have 34.5 PA.
All right. And that
makes sense, right?
So why do you fly
high? You fly
high because you have less
drag up there, right?
If a commercial
and you go far,
so and so the pressure is
obviously going to
be lower there,
and it's cold, right?
-40 degrees
Celsius, all right?
We're told that we have
a compression ratio.
So, um,
sure RP for our compressor
is equal to ten.
So essentially, the
pressure at state
three is equal
to ten times
that of state two.
So P three is equal
to ten times P two.
And the temperature of
the gases at the turbine
inlet is a big number.
So we're then told
that T at T four.
So basically T four,
we're told is equal to
1039 degrees
Celsius, right?
And the final bit
of information
we're given is an MDOT.
We're told that
the mass flow rate
of air entering
the compressor
is 45 kilograms/second,
right?
What are we
told to assume?
So we're told to assume
The cold air
standard assumption.
Right?
Which to remind you,
is that if we
just talk about
the air standard
assumption,
assumption says first that
we treat all combustion
processes as
heat addition.
So three to four is going
to be a heat
addition process.
There is no introduction
of mass from the
fuel into that.
We have an m.in
and an M dot out,
which is steady
and only air.
It's justified
because most of
air is not reactive.
It's nitrogen, right?
So most of what
goes in and
most comes out
as nitrogen,
which doesn't react or
mostly doesn't react.
And because of that,
the fluid's going to
behave like air, right?
So we're going to
basically treat
the thermodynamic
properties of
the fluid throughout
this whole process
as an ideal gas,
including into the
combustion chamber.
For the cold part of it,
the cold just means
that we're lazy.
It means that we just
take the specific heats
at that we keep
these specific
heats constant,
and we set their
values to be
that at room temperature
and pressure.
Or in this case, I'm going
to set it at
the state one,
essentially at state one
when it enters there.
So that's the meaning
of cold, alright?
And we do this
it's convenient,
and I'll show you that
the error at the
end of this,
the efficiency
the error in
the final efficiency
is less than 10%.
So it's not
a bad assumption to
get started with.
Okay, um Yes.
Again, we're going to
treat this as stationary.
Like I said before,
stationary,
meaning that the
jet, you know,
it's like I could
either be flying
and I could
have, you know,
air entering, you
know, relatively,
or I could just
be stationary
and have all that velocity
entering in that way.
Um, For the diffuser,
I'll get to these
assumptions,
but we're going to
make some
assumptions about
the diffuser
and the nozzle.
In the case of
the diffuser,
we're going to have a lot
of kinetic
energy entering,
and we're going to neglect
kinetic energy
at the exit.
For the nozzle, it's
vice versa, right?
So the whole
point is that you
want to accelerate
the fluid,
so the velocity coming in
doesn't have a lot
of kinetic energy,
but when it
exits, it does.
We can treat this
as an ideal gas,
or we can use Piclor to
determine properties.
Again, in my notebook,
you can go through
and see that.
So yeah,
the compressors and
turbines are reversible.
They're diabatic.
That means
that they're isentropic.
This is a steady
flow process.
And the heat exchange
here, the heat exchanger,
we're going to treat
is isobaric like we
do for the other
ones, right?
Okay, so this helps
us to get started.
So process one
to two, one.
To do. So if I look
at my diffuser here,
which is kind of like it's
a little bit different.
I'll draw it like
this to give kind
of the meeting.
So we have you're
entering at
state one at state two.
Here's your
control volume.
We have an m.in and
then M dot out,
which means we have
an M dot, right?
Steady flow, m.in
is M dot out.
And we don't have
any change in energy in
the control volume, right?
Oe.in is equal to R dot,
R dot out here, right?
Steady flow. So, um, two.
Exactly. So the ways
that we don't have
work transfer,
we don't have heat
transfer here.
So what we can have
is we can have
an M dot times H one,
which is entering plus
a velocity one
squared divided by
two is then equal to
an M dot times
times H two, right?
So really from this,
what you have is
that H two, right,
is equal to H one
plus velocity one
squared divided by two.
And why don't I have?
I mean, of course,
I could write I could
write here that
I have W two squared
divided by two like that.
But the reason why I don't
is because I'm decelerating
the fluid, right?
The whole point of
the diffuser is
that you're
decelerating the fluid,
and so W one is much,
much greater than
right than W two.
And so what it means is
that this goes
away, a right?
I would say it's
intuitive, but, yeah,
that's what you
when you do
this analysis, that's
what you would do.
There may be
some cases where
I might give you
a diffuser and
I give you an
inlet and I give
you an outlet velocity.
That's fine. If you
make this assumption,
I probably could
accept it.
But you could also
just, you know,
compare them. You can
calculate the value.
You could say that
you neglected,
or probably what's easiest
is that you just do
the substitution
and you determine
the enthalpy
at state two, right?
Okay, um, Good. I
also said, right?
I said that this was
an isentropic process.
So, of course, we could do
an entropy analysis also
on this control volume.
And what you would
see from that
is that right,
there's no change
in the steady flow.
There's no change
in the entropy
in this control volume.
It's isentropic.
It means that there's
no entropy generated.
And so what that
means is that S two
is little S two is
equal to little
S one, okay?
And that can be useful.
Well, that would be
useful if you use
Pi color because now
you would know H two,
and you know an S
two, you'd have that.
You could also use
TDS relations, right?
I could use TDS
relations and also then
work out other properties
like temperature
and pressure.
Okay?
Good. Any questions
till now?
Yes, please, Presley.
Say it one more time
Comity Comssibility.
So you are by
definition compressing
this fluid.
Why? Well, I mean,
what do you see
about State
three relative
to State two?
You're compressing. If I
take a fluid
and I compress,
you are
compressible. Okay.
Other questions?
All right. Great.
So now we've done
our entropy and our
energy analysis
of one to two, so
we can move on.
All right, two to three.
So two to three. So from
states two to three,
here I have a
compressor, right?
So this is what
my compressor
would look like.
I have here my shaft,
okay, that I'm rotating.
I have some w.in that
I'm transferring
there. All right.
This is State two
here. All right.
And this is, um,
State three,
which is exiting.
Here's my control
volume, looks like that.
Again, steady flow device,
so there's no
change in energy
in the control volume,
no change in mass, no
change in entropy.
All right. Um. And some
piece of information
that we know,
we know that P
three is equal to
ten times P two
because we're told.
Right? Um Good.
So that's one part of it.
If we do, again, our e.in,
it's steady flow
is equal to
our E dot out, right?
There is it's
adiabatic here,
so there's no
heat in or out.
There is work that's in,
and there's mass
that enters
with an enthal
P at state two.
We neglect changes in
kinetic and
potential energy.
So then what this is equal
to is then an MDOT,
and there's no workout,
there's no heat out.
And so this is then
going to be like this.
And so then your w.in
here is going to be
M dot times H three,
minus minus H two.
We do our entropy
analysis, right?
There's no change
in entropy in here.
There is no entropy
generation.
And so what you'll
have then here is that
S three is equal to S two.
All right. Good. So
that takes care of us
then for two to three.
Okay. All right,
three to four
is a combustion chamber.
Three to four is
a combustion
chamber. All right.
Mm mm. All right.
And if we draw this, so
the way that this
would look like
idealized is that we
have some fluid entering
in at state three,
exiting at state four,
draw control volume.
We assume the standard
error assumption,
which means we replace
combustion processes
here by heat addition.
So we have some
do some q.in.
Again, no change, m.in
is dot out is dot,
e.in is equal to
our E dot out.
We have aq.in.
We don't have
work in. We have an M dot.
We have a fluid
with an enthalpy,
specific enthalpy,
H three is equal
to no workout,
no heat out, m.h4.
And again, for the
heat exchanger,
we're going to
neglect changes in
kinetic and
potential energy.
So your q.in an
m.h4 minus H
three. All right.
Okay. All right,
four to five,
four to five is
our turbine.
So you've seen lots
of examples of
this here, W dot out.
Here's our control volume.
I've got some fluid
entering here.
leaving here.
This is entering
at state four.
It's exiting
at state five.
M.in is M dot
out of M dot.
E.in is equal to E is
equal to E dot out.
It's adiabatic.
So the only way energy
is entering is
through the fluid.
So.h4 neglect
changes the kinetic
and potential energy.
This is then equal
to W dot out.
We don't have any Q out.
We also have a
fluid leaving.
So we have an M dot
then times H five.
And so our W dot
out here is equal
to M dot times H
four minus H five.
All right. Questions?
All clear. Yes, please.
We are looking for
here, let me zoom out.
I said at the
beginning, but okay.
So I should write it.
So we're looking for A.
You're looking for the
temperature T five,
so the temperature
at the exit of
the turbine and P five.
B, what we're
looking for is
the velocity of the gases
at the nozzle exit.
So that's the velocity
at state six.
And then C, we
want to know what
is the propulsion
efficiency.
Okay? Now, through
these different steps,
this is straightforward.
This is analysis
that you've seen.
Part B is also
straightforward.
This is going to be
analysis that you've seen.
We're just stringing
it all together.
Part C is then new.
So defining then the
propulsion efficiency.
Other questions?
Yes, please.
One employees for my
So we're driving a
turbine here, right?
So the thing is, what
do you want to have
the higher enthalpy at
the entrance or the exit?
If I'm taking work out of
a control volume there,
which enthropy
should be higher?
The inlet or the outlet?
The inlet, right?
So this has to be
greater because that's
what drives it.
The difference
in the enthalpy
is what's going to
give you the work.
So a four minus
a five times DOT
is the work
transferred out.
Yes, please. Are?
One more time?
For every single one.
So give me an example
of another one.
Okay.
So you could think about
instead of doing
steady combustion,
you could do
detonation, right?
So detonation then is
that what assumption would
you have in detonation?
What cycle did we
analyze before that
operated with detonation?
No, I want a name,
a German name.
So what were
the cycles that
we analyzed in
combustion so
far for gas power cycles?
Carne is a
generalized one,
but I'll give you
a point. Next.
Others. Yes, please, Cody.
Auto, right? Auto
is essentially
the combustion process is
so rapid, we
treat it as what?
Volume.
Constant volume,
isochoric.
Diesel slower, right?
Isobaric.
Here, this heat addition
process is what?
F three to four.
What did we
assume 3-4 here?
It's a heat exchange,
a steady flow
heat exchanger.
What do we assume
for he exchangers?
Isobaric. Thank you, Maya.
Okay? So if you wanted
to go in and do
an interesting one, you
could do detonation,
treat it not as
isobaric as isochoric,
and then you could
piece that into this
and then you
could solve that.
Sounds like a great
quiz problem.
Okay, you inspired
me. Other questions?
Yes, please. So
why don't we?
Why don't you
have one nozzle?
You could do this, okay?
That's as simple as
you can get it, okay?
If you want the
postmodernist interpretation
of a jet power cycle,
you make a ramjet,
which is it.
There's an inlet, there's
an outlet, and that's it.
The trouble is that
this is very
difficult to start.
This is not like I
turn the key and
I go, all right?
There's a lot. You've
already got to be
flying very quickly before
you can do something
like that.
It is a great question.
Go to SpaceX.
Other questions?
You can see it later,
right? I'll move it.
I'll move it. Sit closer,
sit on that side.
All right. So that
was four to five.
Does that help, Alex?
Yes. Okay. Okay.
Um, where was I?
D to do. Okay,
so we did yeah,
so the point is that 4-5,
we can also do an entropy
analysis of this.
It's adiabatic.
So there.
And it's a steady
flow device,
so we don't have any
change in entropy
in the control volume.
It's isentropic, so I
don't have any
entropy generated,
and it means that
my specific entropy
at state five is
equal to my
specific entropy
at state four, okay?
So S is four.
Okay. Um All right.
Before I get into
the step and the analysis
with the nozzle,
I would like to
draw I'd like
to combine the compressor.
So here is my
compressor here
connected to my turbine.
All right? I
have an inlet.
I have an outlet, an inlet
and an outlet like this.
So the entrance to
the compressor
is state two.
Three. And then for
skipping, we don't
have to skip.
We can basically draw,
right? We can draw
our combustion
chamber like that.
Q in q.in.
That's at state three
to four, right?
It's like that. And then
the exit then is basically
state five, right?
And if I draw, if
you were to
essentially look at,
I don't know, control
volume that looks
like This, let's
say, right?
So in my energy analysis,
what I would have for
this control volume is
I have no so what goes in,
I have aq.in. I
have no work in.
I have an M dot,
and I have an H two,
right, which is entering.
And then what's
exiting here.
So I have no work
that's out, right?
I have basically an m.h5,
which is right, which
is out there, right?
And so, why is
that, Interesting.
Just give me a
second. All right?
That's interesting
because then essentially,
I can write H five is
equal to Q dot N divided
by m dot plus H two, okay?
So basically,
I'll determine
the enthalpy in
that way, okay?
What am I saying
with that?
What I'm basically saying
is that the work out of
the turbine is equal
to the work into
the compressor.
All right? Is that clear?
All right. And
then obviously the
q.in is then just
going to be an
M dot, right?
So I can write
this as an M dot.
Here, I'll write
it out explicitly.
So an M dot, the Q in.
Did I write it
over there? I did.
H four minus H three,
H four minus H three
divided by M dot
and plus H two,
and that's your H five.
And since this is an M dot
here, this is gone,
and that's gone.
Cool. Good.
All right,
bringing it home.
So five to six. So
process then five to six.
I think I've killed
this marker.
That's better.
Okay. All right,
so process then
five to six.
Again, it's a
steady flow device.
We have no work
in or workout.
It's adiabatic, no
heat in or heat out.
And we're going to neglect
the kinetic energy
at the inlet.
So then what it
means is I have
an M dot times H five,
which is equal to
an M dot times
H six plus velocity
six squared
divided by two.
All right. And so if
I rearrange this,
and I'm going to have is
a velocity six at the
exit of the nozzle,
which is equal to
the square root of
two times H
five minus six.
All right, um The
other thing that we know
about this, so again,
if I drew my if I
did this properly,
and I drew my
nozzle, okay?
So here's my control
volume on my nozzle.
This is my inlet,
that's my outlet,
state five, state six.
There's no change
in mass in here.
M.in is M dot
out is M dot.
There's no change
in energy in here,
ED in is e dot out.
This is a
consequence of that.
And then when it
comes to entropy,
there's no change in
entropy in the
control volume.
It's adiabatic,
it's reversible.
And so what that means
is that little S
five is equal to
little S six, right?
All right. The
final step here.
Well, there's two things
that we need to do.
The first is we need to
define propulsion
force and power,
and then we need to define
or we've already
defined the q.in.
So in order to define
the efficiency,
we need to know the
propulsion power.
And before we
get to power,
we need to know force.
So think back
to high school.
Transform yourselves.
F, Newton's second
law, right?
So we have a force,
and this is equal to
the mass flow rate
times the velocity
at the exit
minus N dot times the
velocity at the inlet.
Where does this come from?
Um, momentum is equal to
mass times, um
times velocity.
If I take, um the
derivative of this, right?
So what dp dt.
This is dm dt times V
plus dv dt, okay?
That's force.
F equals MA is
usually how Newton's
second law is presented,
but it's not
totally correct.
F is equal to m dot times
your velocity
plus A, okay?
Yeah. All right.
Let's move this
to the center.
All right. Right? And so
this is what we're talking
about here, right?
So this M dot times
the velocity is what we're
talking about
in this case.
All right. Mmm. All right.
Good. So what is
propulsion power
then? So propulsion power.
So our W dot P
is equal to.
So to get this into power,
I need to have
a force acting
on a distance
per unit time.
Force on a distance
Force times velocity
is that, okay?
So if I take this force,
which I've
defined here, F,
and I times it by
the velocity of
the aircraft,
I'm going to get
propulsion power.
And the efficiency,
the efficiency of
this EAP is nothing
but this w dot P
divided by Q dot
N. All right?
All right. Where
am I at on this?
All right, I can
probably erase this.
Uh huh. All right.
So our w dot P
here is equal to
m dot times the velocity
at the exit,
which is what?
What's the velocity
of the exit?
Minus the velocity
at the inlet.
Okay? And then
this is times
the velocity of
the aircraft.
Huh. Yes. So this
is nothing but
velocity one.
And what we'll assume
for the purposes
of this analysis,
not for the takeoff part,
which is relevant, is
we're going to assume
that this is equal
to the velocity of
the aircraft,
which makes sense.
I have a stationary
device, okay?
I have air coming in
at some velocity.
And I was saying
that that's
the velocity that I'm
moving with, okay?
Good. So this is your
formula for that.
So I have w dot P all set.
I know W six. I know
W this is a given.
The M dot was
also a given,
so I'm going to set there.
The.inThe q.in.
Right? So my q.in
here is equal
to my.h4 minus my
H three, which I think
I had already written.
Where did I write it?
Yeah, I already
wrote it here.
Let me start highlighting
some things.
So my q.in I had here.
All right. So with
my q.in, I'm good.
With my W dot propulsion
there, I'm good.
So my efficiency is
good. This is done.
The velocity at state six,
right, we determined
through here.
All right. So this
is also done.
And, um, If we come
here at state five,
okay, I need to determine
the temperature
and the pressure.
And so what do I know?
I can start stringing
things together,
but certainly what I know
is I know the entropy.
I know basically
my entropy
at state five. All right.
Yes.
And I would
have determined
H five from here, right?
So H five, I would have
determined through
this analysis.
So by knowing the
entropy specific entropy
at state five and the
enthropy at state five,
because this is a
pure substance,
I have complete
information,
and then from Pcolorn
dot notation,
I have T and pure.
Okay? All right.
Yeah, and if you want
to substitute numbers,
pull that up and
look at that, okay?
But that's roughly
what you need to know.
So what are they take
home message and
et propulsion?
Many things are
isentropic.
So the diffuser,
the compressor,
the turbine,
and the nozzle,
isentropic, okay?
So it means adiabatic,
and it means reversible.
One key piece
of information.
The second thing is
we treat this as
stationary for the
purposes of the analysis.
So we have this and
our inlet velocity
then is W one,
that's obvious, but
then we set that
equal to the velocity
of the aircraft,
okay? You need
to recall that.
Everything else
you've done,
you've done steady flow
analysis of a diffuser,
a compressor, a
heat exchanger,
which we do the standard
error assumptions for.
You've done turbine, and
you've also done
nozzle, right?
So each of these
individually is there.
The next key part
of it, which
sets it apart from
the other analyses
is all of the work
out of the turbine
you put into
the compressor.
So there is no network,
net shaft work out
of the system, okay?
So you use that then to
that fact to determine the
enthalpy at state five,
what's exiting
on the turbine.
And that's pretty
much it. Yes, please.
No, you start like a
good book at
the beginning.
All right. So,
what do we know?
Yeah, let's walk
through that.
So what you know is the
inlet temperature and
the limb pressure
that you're given.
T and P one, you know,
so you have complete
information
about that state.
State two, you're
told this,
you're told that
the pressure
at state three is
ten times P two, and
it's isontropic.
S three is S two.
So I have pressure. I have
specific um Oh,
I'm sorry, here.
So S two is
equal to S one.
Let me back up a second.
So T one and T one we
have. That's good.
For state two, you know,
the specific entropy at
state two is equal to
the specific entropy
at state one.
And you also know
the pressure, right?
You basically know,
I'm sorry, not
the pressure.
You know, the enthalpy
at state two.
So with the
specific entropy
and enthalpy at state two,
you have complete
information of state two.
All right? So it means you
know the pressure at
state two, right?
The pressure at
state three is
ten times P two,
so you have that.
S three is S two,
now state three.
Okay, State, um, State
four here, okay?
So for state four,
you are given it was
stated in the problem,
but you were given the
temperature at state four.
And this is an isobaric
process, right?
So the state the pressure
at state four is
going to be equal
to the pressure
at state three.
To the point that was
brought up before,
you could also treat
that isochorically if you
were doing a
detonation process.
So this is solved here.
You know, state four.
Inlet here, right?
So four to five,
you know that this
is isentropic.
So you know the
entropy at State five.
And from this analysis of
all the workout goes
into the compressor,
you can determine the
enthropy at state five.
Now I have enthalpy and
I have entropy next.
Onto onto State six.
So I'm holding
the wrong one.
Hold on. State six.
So for State six, then,
what you know is that
it's isentropic, right?
So S six is
equal to S five,
and P six is
equal to what?
Yeah, it's the
exit, right?
It's basically back
out to there, right?
So P six is P one,
and then you have
that there. Okay?
But again, I
would say all of
the previous things that
we had done would allow
you to string together
that process. Other
questions about t?
Yes, please. Yeah, you're
told the velocity
of an aircraft.
Yeah. So again, open
that, read it, and yeah.
Other questions? Yes,
please. You assume?
Because I want to
make this happen
in 40 minutes.
Okay.
But it's not unreasonable
if you think about like
you're moving, right?
So basically, I could
have something that's not
moving and air
blowing at me,
or I could be moving,
and then the air
essentially looks
stationary with
respect to me
flying, right?
So you could do one or
the other. There is
a reference frame,
right? Okay.
Other questions? Okay.
Great. Yeah, and think
about detonation.
Okay, how does it look
like if you want
to diagram that?
So again, what you need
to get into the habit
of doing now is
defining these states.
You know, use the
process classify
calor and make,
you know, plots.
So here, this kind
of illustrates
the isotropic nature of
literally every
process except
for the combustion
chamber.
So one to two
diffuser isotropic,
two to three,
compressor isotropic,
three to four
heat addition,
four to five
turbine isotropic,
five to six nozzle
isotropic, okay?
And check yourself, right?
Look at that and see.
Does that make sense?
Um, you can represent that
also in a PV
diagram, right?
We said that P one and
P six should be
the same, right?
I'm going to
that. So that's
what you would
expect there.
I'd expect, you know,
something with a
higher specific volume
right at the at the exit
because it's hotter.
T six is hotter
than T one,
so there I'd
expect a higher
specific volume at
the exit, okay?
But three to four, heat
addition, isoberic.
That's what I'm looking
for there, okay?
So plot. This is
a graph this is a
graphing class.
All right. So If
you really want to be
efficient or you really,
really want to go
fast there, you'll
end up designing
probably something
that looks like this
with all the need
of those different
components.
These are called ram
jets, all right?
My understanding,
I do not work
in this field,
but when I was a
student some years ago,
I was told these
things are
very hard to start, okay?
Once you get them going,
right, they can go,
but they are difficult to
basically start
from the ground,
but they can go
fast, they're light.
They're very efficient
there, okay?
Towards the comment
about compressibility,
this is not the class
in compressibility.
There have some
comments about
that, like what it means.
But in short,
if you want to
make things that
go supersonic,
you need to have
a very specific
type of nozzle.
This is called the D
Laval nozzle, right?
Gustav De LaVall was
a Swedish guy who
made milk, okay?
Alpha Laval.
Has anyone heard of
Alpha Laval? Is anyone?
Okay, they make
heat exchangers.
They're still a company.
That's the Laval
I believe that's
the Laval in the name.
But if you want to make
something that goes
faster than the speed of
sound, this is what
you need to do.
You have a converging,
diverging nozzle.
So you bring in
a fluid to here,
and this is all what's
called subsonic.
So it's moving
at aeed that's
less than the
speed of sound.
You compress the heck
out of this until it
hits the throat here,
okay? The throat.
At the throat,
you're moving sonic.
You are at Mach one.
Alright, Mach one.
At this condition, if
you do any further, right,
try to put any
further additions
into pressure, more
will not move through.
Because it's a throat,
it becomes choked.
You are choked, okay?
Out of this at the
back end there,
this is where things can
then get supersonic.
So everything that
you put in, and
you compress the
hell out of it,
at the end of
that it will be
allowed to expand
and it moves.
The analysis of
this can be done,
and it is also isentropic.
So these types of
nozzles are
called isotropic.
There are other ones
that are isenthalpic.
That's what we work
with when we do
research, isenthalpic.
But these things can be
modeled and all of that.
We're working
on a section,
especially for
the aero students
of some content towards
the end of the
semester that we
can give you on
Prairie Learn,
some additional
reading and
some stuff to have.
So at least you know
the terminology, okay?
All right. I will
go through this.
I won't be able to do
the full thing for it.
I expect you to read this.
I spent a lot of
time with this
going through
the analysis and
the derivation,
but the too
long and didn't
read is that until now
I haven't really given you
a cycle that is
Carne, okay?
You've done
elements of it.
If you remember
when I told you,
Hey, here was this
piston cylinder,
I put heat in, and there's
an equal amount of
work that's
transferred out.
This is the first stage of
what's called the
Sterling cycle, okay?
So I do the heat in
and the workout
isothermally.
Ar? I then, um
at that point.
So I'm doing heat
in and work out,
and I'm doing that
isothermally, alright?
That's good.
The next stage
in the process as I allow
um I allow basically
my device to expand
and cool, okay?
So I do go adiabatic
expansion.
So there's some work
transferred out,
and I allow my device
to cool, all right?
And then the third step is
essentially I compress it,
and while I'm compressing
it, it's heating up,
so I transfer heat out,
right, at constant
temperature.
So I cool isothermally.
And then I continue
to compress
reversibly, but
adiabatically.
So it means that
I warm up I
warm up my system.
All right.
So all of that's
fine and well.
But if you really
want to get this
to be a uh,
like a carnal, basically a
carnal level
of efficiency.
That process
of the cooling
and the heating there,
you would love to have
what's called
a regenerator.
So if you remember
last time when
we were talking about
the Braden cycle,
the purpose of
a regenerator
is that you get
to have yourself
kind of like a
boost or like
a heating effect or
a cooling effect
without actually having to
put extra heat into
the system, okay?
So what does one of
these cycles look like?
So there's two
types. One is
Sterling and one
is Ericsson, okay?
Sterling is essentially a
almost like if you think,
you know, a closed system.
So it's a piston
cylinder one, okay?
That gets you to
Carn efficiency.
Ericsson is like a
steady flow device,
turbines, compressor
heat exchangers, right?
So it's like Sterling is
like kind of like an
auto or a diesel cycle,
but, like, as efficient
as it can be.
Ericsson is
like a Brayton,
somewhat like a Brayton,
but as efficient as
that can be, right?
It basically gets you to
Karin, right? All right.
So step one, as
I mentioned,
you have heat in and
workout. Great, ar?
You then continue to
expand adiabatically
there.
You then slide
this whole thing
over a regenerator.
You basically slide
this whole thing
over a regenerator here,
which absorbs some
of the heat, okay?
What would this
look like? You want
to patent, like,
figure it out.
Like, go in and
look and come up
with a good idea.
This could be
something that's like
a metal foam, right?
But the idea
is that when I
move that hot fluid
over this thing,
it retains some of
that heat and cools
down and cools
down the fluid.
Again, you continue with
your right, the
movement to the end.
So now this is this gas
is at a low temperature.
He was high.
I transfer heat into
the regenerator.
I'm at a low. And now
what I do is I
transfer work in,
I compress, and then I
take heat out, okay?
Um, you know,
and then I sort of,
like, go back, right?
The slide this thing
back over the regenerator.
I warm it back up, and I
start from the
beginning, okay?
But the key element is if
you want to get
something, again,
either a closed
system type of
piston cylinder device or
a steady flow device,
if you really want to
approach
carnoefficiencies,
you have to have an
element that can
store energy thermally
within the cycle,
okay?
We call that
regeneration, right?
Again, Yeah. This
will make more sense.
I think when we get into
the end of Lecture
ten, if I have time,
then I'll try to go
through and then derive
maybe the Sterling
cycle and go
through a detailed
analysis with it, right?
But to get to be
Carne, right?
With this system, you'll
be able to show that
essentially
that you'll get
an efficiency,
which is, you know,
one over L divided by H,
if you analyze this there,
and it's only possible
because you have
this regeneration
step there.
Okay?
All right. Other
questions?
Okay, this is what
it would look like.
Again, I'm going to do
the analysis,
but in short,
this is what your
temperature entropy
diagrams look
like one to two.
And this whole process
of how do I go 4-1
and warm up without heat
addition, it's, you know,
all of that, you know,
area under the curve here,
essentially transferring
heat over into this.
This is how you do it.
Alright? Okay, with that,
I'm going to close
like 1 minute early.
So if you have
questions, I'm up
here there. Thank you.