PROFESSOR: So
coming back to our--
so when we were talking last
week about the Carnot cycle,
we were discussing processes
that were reversible.
Correct?
We talked about isothermal
adiabatic processes
that were reversible.
We strung them all together and
we got this idealized cycle.
I have a great book here.
It's a physics book
from Alonzo Finn.
A lot of today's lecture
is drawn from this.
For those of you who
really like old books
and are a big nerd like me,
you can go out and get that.
And in his book he
has this nice example.
And it's seemingly
simple, but you probably,
if you really want
to think about this
and think about reversible
and irreversible,
it's so simple but
complex at the same time.
So imagine you have
an ideal gas her.
You have some
weights on top of it.
There's a pressure
on the outside
here, some external pressure,
some internal pressure.
It's initially at
equilibrium and you
got a tiny little weight.
And with this weight,
you take it off,
the piston expands a little bit.
It has a bit of boundary work.
The pressure decreases
slightly as a result
and it comes into equilibrium,
and you do that many times.
You keeps sliding
these little weights
and eventually that piston
would come back up to the top.
And then if you repeated
the process there,
you would come back
down to the same height.
The key thing is
that if I showed you
this picture on the left and
this picture on the right,
and if I did a good
job scanning it,
you wouldn't be able to tell
the difference between the two.
There's no change
to your system.
There's no change in
your surroundings.
They are the same.
An irreversible process
is this example.
So imagine here I have a weight
A that's initially on here
and I take it off.
This thing is going to
expand very rapidly.
So this thing is going to move
up really quickly to there.
It's going to come
up to this height.
To bring the piston head back
down to the original height,
you then take this weight
B and you put it on there
and you come back.
And you look at the system
and you say, hey, look,
this thing is the
same as this thing.
That's reversible.
Except it isn't.
Because if I was to show you the
picture of the one on the left
and the picture in
the one on the right,
you would agree, hopefully,
that they are not the same.
Your surroundings have changed.
This is going to take you more
than the 30 seconds of looking
at it to process.
It's in your slides.
But come back to this
and think about it
because this is a
great example of what
reversible and
irreversible mean.
So you point out that there.
I just walked you through it.
You slide that weight over,
you slide the other one.
And the key thing
to pay attention to
is that these things are
not the same up here.
It goes without saying, too,
that reversible processes tend
to put out more work.
So as engineers, we're
interested in being
as close to reversible
as we possibly can.
Okay, that's on that.
So to help a little bit with
you being able to at your party
to explain the history
of thermodynamics,
we can about this book.
So this is a book written
by Rudolf Clausius.
Rudolf Clausius, again,
first chair of physics at
[INDISCERNIBLE] in Zurich.
He was the one who really sort
of formalized the second law.
So it was really Sadi Carnot who
wrote about it and had it there.
He used caloric theory,
which was wrong.
Clausius took it, polished
it, repackaged it there.
And in this book-- he has
many books and many things
that he wrote, but
he has this one
which is an English translation
of his of his German text, where
he looked at the
mechanical theory of heat
and the application
of it to heat engines.
Because, remember, the
whole thing is interesting.
You want to take heat
and you want to get work.
You want to maximize the amount
of work you get out for the heat
that you put in.
So you're obsessed with this.
I want to get as much
out as I can put in.
And as we had seen before, when
we had this piston example,
we know that with that ideal
gas, if we let the thing expand
there, we can get exactly the
amount of work out as we put in.
But to make it a cycle, we
need to bring that back.
And to bring that
piston head back
required transferring
heat out to cool it,
to bring it back to
the initial state.
And for all cycles require that.
You don't just get to keep
pumping heat in, in, in, in,
and get it.
As James told us, if
we keep doing that,
what would happen to
our system, James?
STUDENT: Sorry I was reading.
PROFESSOR: Sorry.
Anyways, it blows up.
He's so engrossed in it.
That's wonderful.
He's going to be very fun
at the party to talk to.
So anyway, so the point is
that we know a bit about that.
We're going to have
to put some heat in.
to take some heat out,
and we're going
to get some work.
And what we're going
to sense out of this
is that not all heat
is created the same.
So if I have a reservoir
and I transfer heat
from it at a high
temperature, this
is probably not going to be
the same as transferring heat
as a low temperature, as we know
now in how we produce energy.
And this is what
Clausius was looking at.
So if you look at his book--
again, I'm going to spare
you the details on it.
But the key point here, in this
500 voluminous page text, is he
writes this statement
about how he's
trying to link that
work out with the heat
that he's bringing in.
And he says that the work that
I'm trying to transfer out
is not going to be equal,
basically, proportional
to this Q. It's going to be
proportional to the Q divided
by the temperature
of the reservoir.
Now, this is deep shit.
Like, we're not going
to get this today.
You're going to think
about this for 10 years,
and I swear to God, if
you can do it in 10 years,
I'll be proud of you.
But this is what he's thinking.
So he's thinking,
all right, so if I'm
going to make them
equivalent and all of that,
probably I'm going
to have to control
for the for the temperature,
and this is what he writes.
But Q divided by T is going to
be key to the linking with this
with this work.
So coming back to entropy, since
most of you have heard about it.
So the change in entropy for
a reversible process is dS.
So if this differential S
is equal to dQ divided by T.
And this is for a for
a reversible process.
This is why I'm writing this
as an exact differential, where
the capital letter S is entropy.
And I'm writing this statement.
This is historically
how it was defined.
And my evidence, my receipts
of that are the previous slide.
That's how he developed it.
Has the units of
joules per Kelvin.
If it was little
less, it would be
joules per kilogram per Kelvin.
And it's from the
Greek for ergon, work,
like energy we
talked about before.
Entropy, transformation.
In his [INDISCERNIBLE]
classes, his [INDISCERNIBLE]
he calls this disgregation.
It's like the
opposite of aggregate.
So you have something aggregate.
The opposite of
aggregate is this word.
And he had another word,
transformational content,
like [GERMAN] or something
in German, just whatever.
Anyways, there was a Nobel
prize winner, Leon Cooper,
who supposedly,
according to Wikipedia,
is who the guy in big bang
theory is named after,
Sheldon Cooper.
So apparently it's this guy.
It doesn't matter.
So he said about
Clausius that in having
this nice word of
entropy, he succeeded
in coining a word that meant
the same thing to everybody,
nothing.
So, again, it's very difficult.
Entropy is a difficult term.
So if we can go
through and try to link
this change in entropy to heat
or linking entropy and heat.
So if we take that dS
is equal to the dQ by T
and we integrate, since entropy
is a property, so this is not
a path function,
this is a property.
So we have S2 minus S1 is then
equal to the integral there.
And it can be negative
or it can be positive,
depending on if heat is
absorbed or rejected.
And the reason for
this is that the T
that we're dealing with here
is the so-called absolute
temperature,
absolute temperature.
So this is Kelvin.
And in the Kelvin scale, there
is no negative temperature
unless you're doing some really,
really, really weird experiments
in the lab there.
So it's a positive quantity.
And so if you take--
again, so now we've linked
this change in entropy to heat
and we can look
at a special case.
If we're dealing with
an adiabatic, so no heat
transfer, reversible
transformation,
so because it's adiabatic,
the dQ is equal to 0.
And so the S2 minus the
S1 is then equal to 0.
And so for that reason,
adiabatic reversible
transformations are
also called isentropic.
So isentropic means
constant entropy.
We had isothermal,
constant temperature;
isobaric, constant pressure;
isochoric, constant volume;
isentropic, constant entropy.
Have we seen an isentropic
process already, actually?
Yes, you have.
If you came last
week, you saw one.
So if you want to
see this plotted,
so again, we love our diagram.
So we had our P-V
diagrams and all of that.
Very important one, when
we're analyzing systems
according to first and
second law principles
is what's called
the T-S diagram.
So on the vertical axis,
you have temperature.
On the horizontal,
you have entropy.
Let's say you start
at some state A1
and you finish at some state A2,
and this is your transformation.
The heat that you
transfer is then
equal to the integral from
state 1 to state 2 of this.
So basically, it's the area,
the shaded area that I draw here
under this curve, is the
heat that you transfer
for reversible transformation.
So if you thought
about, when we were
looking at something
like the Carnot cycle,
so we were looking at T
and we were looking at S,
and we were drawing those boxes
from our different states.
So in this case, let's
say this is the T cold
and this is the T hot.
So for the low part here, we
could integrate and have this.
For the higher part
here, we'd have
to do the integrate
all of that area.
And the isentropic part of
it is where it's constant.
So that's how that looks like.
And just like I've
drawn here, if you
were to take the integral
over the entire cycle,
so if you were to take
the integral over--
I'm smashing chalk back here.
If you're taking
the integral, then,
over this whole
cycle, as I have here,
so if you end up where
you end up before,
the amount of the
net, basically,
heat that you transfer is that,
just like I showed you here.
So you do this first process
here, this is an arbitrary one.
And you go back, then the net
heat absorbed by the system
is the is the shaded area.
And importantly,
for us as engineers,
that is going to be equivalent
to the work done by the system
during the cycle.
Because, you remember, before we
were dealing with these control
volumes, and in those cases,
in a cycle of a control volume
like that with no mass
in and no mass out,
the work done is equal
to the net heat absorbed.
And so I'm writing this
sentence and I'm saying,
entropy is a
variable that may be
used to describe a
process in the same way
that pressure, volume,
or temperature do.
And we can start out
by trying to say--
I mean, first of all, you might
read that and say, no, it isn't.
It doesn't make any sense to me.
So we can start by
thinking, let's start
with the one with pressure.
So if we're thinking
about how the relationship
between pressure and
energy, so we're sometimes
talking about like P dV, so
if we think about the boundary
work, so the pressure for,
for isobaric processes,
so the pressure times
the change in the volume
is going to be the
work that you do.
In the same way, if I
think about temperature
times the change in
entropy, it's the same.
What type of property are
pressure and temperature?
Are they intensive or extensive?
STUDENT: Intensive?
PROFESSOR: Intensive.
What type of
properties is volume?
STUDENT: Extensive--
PROFESSOR: What type of property
do you think entropy is then?
STUDENT: Extensive?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
So these things depend on
the size of the system.
What's difficult, if I told
you like to measure pressure,
that would be straightforward.
If I told you to measure
temperature of this room,
it would be straightforward.
If I told you to measure
the volume of this room,
you might say, screw you.
That's really hard.
But if I gave you a tape
measure and a lot of money,
probably you would do it.
If I asked you to measure
the entropy of the room,
that's not so straightforward.
We'd have to do something
with this link of Q. Maybe
we're doing something with
like a heat transfer in.
We're looking at a
temperature response,
and then we're
getting the entropy.
It's not as obvious.
So use these analogies with
kind of a grain of salt,
but that's just to give
you a sense of that.
And you'll find
it in the tables.
So if you look in
the tables, again,
like I said before,
so you'll see
it's the little s, which is
then in the units of kilojoules
per kilogram Kelvin.
And so if we look at,
again, another special case,
so here if we look at the
instead of an adiabatic,
if we look at the isothermal,
so the change in entropy
during an isothermal
reversible process,
so recall before we had this
equation S2 minus S1 was
equal to this integral.
If the temperature
is constant, it's
not being affected
by the heat transfer.
So if it's reversible, we
have the little d, not delta,
little dQ.
So that just becomes Q
over T, so maybe this
is how we'd end up trying to
measure the change in entropy
of the room is with some type of
system like that, of Q's and T's
amount of known heat transfer at
a specific temperature for it.
And what can you use this for?
So I'm giving you this
example with water.
It's a pretty simple
So if we take ice at
STP, so if we take ice
at 1 bar atmospheric
pressure here,
it's going to melt at 273.15
Kelvin or 0 degrees C.
What's known is that it'll
absorb 1,435 calories per mole
to melt. So that is because this
is a constant pressure process.
Phase change here is a
constant pressure process.
If we're looking at going from
pure ice here into a liquid,
and if the phase change is
P is equal to a constant
there, what we're going
to be able to do is we
can define the
enthalpy of melting.
So this is also table values.
You can look up to this.
Remember when we did
for vaporization,
we had the liquid to vapor.
We had an enthalpy that was HFG.
The difference between
the enthalpy when
you're a vapor and
you're a liquid,
you have this for vaporization.
At our conditions, it's 2,200
joules per gram or 2,200
kilojoules per kilogram.
It's a lot for melting.
When it's melting, this value
is about an order of magnitude
less.
It's still substantial, but
it's about an order of magnitude
less.
That's about 333
kilojoules per kilogram.
And if you then want to say what
is the entropy for this process,
so we can write back
up here, we have our Q.
So we have this Q is being equal
to T, to the temperature when
we transfer it.
As we know from melting, the
ice doesn't change temperature
when it's melting,
so this mixed region
is going to be a constant
temperature process, too.
So we have the T,
which is 273 Kelvin,
and then we have
the S2 minus S1.
And then here, if it's
capital S's, it'll
basically work like that.
And so you rearrange
this, and you'll
have this delta S as being equal
to the Q divided by the T, which
from what we know
before, if we have
the mass of the substance
times the delta H divided by--
or times the H value
that I have there,
and I'm going to be able to
write the change like that.
So that's how you
would go about that.
So the relationship then in this
case for the melting process
is the change in entropy is
equal to the heat absorbed,
the latent heat absorbed
during that process, which
for capital S is then MH and
then divided by the temperature
that we had.
If this wasn't capital S, but
it was little s, so if this
was done on a on
a per mass basis
and you substituted the values,
then this delta little s
would be equal to this
333 kilojoule per kilogram
divided by the 273.15 Kelvin.
And according to
my calculations,
I have something like 1.22
kilojoules per kilogram Kelvin.
So that's the link
between heat transferred
and the entropy
change of your system.
Okay?