All right, I got 210.
So today we're talking
about energy. All right.
So cycles,
internal energy,
heat and energy
transfer by
heat and work and work
transfer processes.
So where we left
off last time,
we're talking
about states.
If we connect states
together, we can
make a process.
If we string them all
together and make it
into a loop, right,
we call that essentially,
um a cycle, all right?
And that's really what
mechanical engineers
are like chiefly
concerned with, right?
So taking heat
into work, working
to heat like that.
Yeah, if you want to
see this cycle here,
most of my lecture
slides from here on out,
I'll have my notes
and work that as
examples available
through the data hub.
So if you click
that link, it'll
pull up a Jupyter
notebook.
It has usually my notes
and then also
calculations,
and you can recreate
plots like that,
all right?
This one just happens
to be an important one,
especially for
aerospace engineers.
So this is pretty
much the basis
of jet propulsion,
but also how we make for
mechanical engineers,
how we make electricity
from, like, natural gas.
So how this comes in and
produces power
there. Okay? Good.
And then this also gives
an introduction to
some of how we compute
the properties.
So you may or
may not know,
but the old school way of
taking things like
temperature and
pressure and computing
internal energy,
and the other properties
involve tables.
If you want to see
these, each of
the homework
problems has a PDF,
you can click on it.
I think there's no less
than like 17 of them.
There's the SI, there's
then the imperial units.
It's a lot, okay?
You know, when I
was taught and
raised my old
man's a carpenter,
so he taught me
to use the hand
tool before the
power tool.
So the hand tool,
in this case is
the paper tables.
I encourage you to have
a look see what
that's like,
and then probably
the next from there
at that point, that
state onwards,
your future processes
will involve
no paper and essentially
what I would call,
like a thermodynamic
calculator,
in this case, Pi Killor
and really grateful to
Professor Frank Locke,
who's taught this
course for many years,
who took all of his
knowledge that he had in
MAT lab and put this
into the Python.
So you're the
first ones to
benefit from you know,
him being a nice
guy in doing that.
So if you click through
that, you should be
able to see kind of
the basics of it.
And then this week
in the discussion
sections,
the GSI should also
be taking you
through how to
do property calculations
with electronically.
Alright? As Clar.
Cool. That's one thing.
The second thing
I want to say,
this has come up in
the homework problems
in that is it's
very important.
So if we do all
the homeworks
online and all that,
it's like, great,
but it's still very
important for you,
right, to be able to
explain your logic, right?
So how do I want to
see that, right?
First, whenever
you do this,
you're going to
take notes, right?
You're going to write
a problem statement.
The first thing you're
going to do after
that is to draw a
schematic, right?
You're gonna draw
your schematic.
You're going to show
me boundaries, right?
You know, that's
what we learned from
the first part,
you're going to draw.
Tell me what
you're assuming
ideal gas behavior,
so on and so forth.
Any physical laws.
So conservation of energy,
the first law of thermo.
Calculate your
properties, right?
So that might be Pi here,
you know, calculations
and reasoning, okay?
And when I grade something
and I still grade,
like a bunch of
your problems
on your quizzes
and your finals,
because I want to
see if you really
know, you might get like,
if a problem is 15 points,
I might give you
one point for a
right answer.
And the other 14 are
how you think, okay?
It works the
other way too.
You might give me
a wrong answer,
but if you look
like you can string
processes together and
you have the
right thinking,
I grade that, okay?
So if you ask yourself,
why in my homework, am I
writing out my
work on the PDF?
Because the whole point of
the homework is to get you
in game shape for
an assessment
and for a quiz.
So it's practice, right?
And how you do that on
the homework is going to
be a one to one for
how quizzes do, right?
We're going to run this
through Pie Learn, right?
You're going to show
your work on paper
that's going to be in
front of you, right?
It's going to be like
that, all right?
Cool. Also, our
accreditation depends on it.
Okay, um which just
got extended for six
years, I was told today.
It was wonderful.
Okay, so that's a
bit about that.
Now, back into
the whole part
about internal energy.
Remember before we talked
about energy can come
in many forms, right?
Actually, it's
one of the things
that we still don't know.
There's a great,
like, quote from
Richard Feynman
about that,
but it's like
a weird thing
where it doesn't really
come in, like, packets.
We only know it from
formula, right?
The most common one is,
like, kinetic
energy, right?
One half mv squared,
you know, like
it's a math thing,
and then out of that
you get energy.
It's of you
know, it's like
you go and you
weigh it, right?
Um, and you're
going to have that.
You have chemical energy.
So we talked
about inertial,
you have kinetic energy,
you know, nuclear, right?
It's kind of like
all over the place.
So it's a very seemingly
simple but actually very
complicated subject.
So we say in thermo,
all we really want
to care about
is really this
internal energy.
And that internal
energy for
a simple system really
only depends on
something like,
let's say, temperature
and pressure,
right, two sort of
properties there.
And I didn't say too
much about the mechanisms.
The closer we got to
the mechanisms of what
internal energy is was
these ideal gases.
So remember the
ping pong balls or
the billards right?
The balls bouncing.
What type of energy
did that possess?
What type of energy does
an ideal gas store?
Say it again?
Translational, right?
So translational.
But some molecules
that are polyatomic,
meaning they have two.
Not only do
they translate,
but they spin, right?
So they can have
rotational.
Some of them can
have vibrational
energy associated
with them,
and things like electrons
can also possess
spin energy, right?
So you start with
the ideal gas,
and the more
sophisticated you get,
you can have different
mechanisms of storage,
right?
But at the end
of the day, Um,
you know, so it's
a molecule moving.
It's, you know, it's
vibrating, right?
It's rotating.
But all of these
can contribute as
mechanisms to the
internal energy, okay.
Okay.
One thing, all right?
And again, that's
talking about the state.
Now, you can
ask yourselves,
so that stores energy,
you know, via
those mechanisms.
How does it transfer them?
So how is energy exchange?
So, something that's
like hot, all right?
Where does that energy
that I see, you know,
in terms of them
moving, how does
it, you know, transport?
It's a fair question.
When we get to the second
law in this class,
what you're going
to recognize
is that things
that are hot,
you know, things that
possess sort of a lot of
thermal energy are
going to move from
the regions of high
to low, all right?
You take like a balloon,
you got like high
pressure in it,
the high
concentration moves
from high to
low, all right?
Um, and then it'll
be the same thing sort
of in the simulator.
So if you go through
and you create like
one partition that's,
like, cold, right?
So let's say
they're moving
if kinetic energy is,
you know, one
half mv squared,
so they have low mass or
really low velocity,
and then the other
one is, you know,
maybe higher mass or
really high velocity,
you can go in and
look at how it moves.
So, you know, does
the hot region cool?
Does the colder one
actually increase in
temperature until they're
essentially at the same
temperature, right?
And at that
point, you're at
equilibrium, right?
The only equilibrium you
really learned
until now is what?
C 85 who's taking C 85.
So what is
equilibrium in C 85?
You know, sum of F is
equal to zero, right?
So in thermo,
right, the uh,
um, you know, we have
thermal, basically
thermal equilibrium.
Everything at the
end of it is at
the same temperature.
It means that there's
no longer heat being
transferred there.
You can go on and look
at questions like
what does this
basically depend on?
But for a translational
gas, like I said,
this will depend on the
mass of your molecule,
the more that you
have, the more energy,
the square of
the velocity.
So it's very sensitive
to that. The total energy.
So the total internal
energy here is also
going to depend
on the number
of particles
that you have,
and the direction
of heat though.
So what does
that depend on?
Yes.
And anything else?
You can speak louder.
Name and Zach?
Okay. So we say it depends
on temperature and the
fact that they're
in contact,
okay? Yeah. Okay.
Does it depend on
anything else?
So the direction.
So I would say
the internal energy
definitely depends
on the mass of it,
but the direction.
So the direction
of heat transfer.
Would you say that the
direction of heat transfer
depends on the mass?
Make an argument for me.
One has more energy
than the other. Yeah.
So it's an
interesting concept.
It turns out no.
I can have something
that's like,
think about an ice cube.
If I take a
very, very tiny
ice cube and I
put it on Earth,
very large earth here.
You know, if we're
not with the polar
bears, well,
let's say we're in
sunny California,
heat then from California
is going to be
transferred into the
ice and melt it.
If I reverse it
and I say now
that maybe I have a
really hot cup of water,
then there and the
surroundings are like,
you know, colder
than essentially,
right, the heat will flow.
So all that's needed.
The take home message here
is it's just a temperature
difference, okay?
When you take MU
one oh six or 109,
you'll see there that
essentially it's
only the temperatures
the gradient that's
involved, okay?
So your point where
you mentioned
the fact that
the containers
have to be in contact.
That's a fair point.
Here, I obviously
removed that.
If you read your textbook,
sometimes they leave.
All right, these two
things in contact,
but they don't let
the mass transfer.
So this is basically like
a thermally conducting
wall, right?
So you have a thermally
conducting wall.
The term for
this is called
diathermal, right?
So you'll see in some of
your homework problems,
sometimes they say, like,
and two partitions are in
contact via a
diathermal wall.
That's what that means.
Basically, you can
transfer heat through it,
but you cannot transfer
mass through it, okay?
Other questions?
Okay. And there
is a homework problem that
addresses Miles'
point about the size.
So it's a good question.
Okay, good.
Um, All right.
So again, until now,
we're considering systems
like the one that I
just mentioned where all
that we're exchanging is
we have systems that are
basically closed,
all right?
So what does closed mean?
So closed in this class
means that I don't
bring mass in
or out, right?
So if I draw a box, right?
So let's say this
is, you know,
I have a piston
cylinder here,
I have this um,
you know, box.
I could go in and
draw my boundary.
So I could go in and
draw and say, Okay,
this is the boundary
of the system that I
would like to analyze.
All right.
So this is a side view,
a cross sectional
view of a cylinder,
and then a piston
head, right?
So it's just like your
bike pump from before,
so it can
compress it, gas.
The gas can expand and
transfer workout, okay?
If I look at that
system, so I
don't bring mass
in and out of it.
The only way, You know,
that in this class,
we're going to look
at energy exchange
is through or the
only way to exchange
energy with a
closed system is
through heat
and work, okay?
All right? And
a common way
we're going to look at
the work part of it,
especially with
cylinders is
expansion and
contraction processes,
all right?
Yeah. And if you
want to know it's
a fair thing to
ask yourself,
like, you know,
sometimes you
might see a system
where, you know,
we're doing work
and we bring in,
um, you know,
like a resistor, you know,
into this thing,
and we apply,
like, a potential, right?
We hook that up to,
like, a battery or
something, and, you know,
we apply a potential,
and I would ask you,
you know, is that heat
or is it work, right?
So if I turn that on and
I start to transfer
energy into this
control volume,
I'm not transfering mass,
I'm transferring energy.
You could ask yourself,
is that a work transfer
or heat transfer
process, Right?
And the way to
know if it's
a work or a heat transfer
process is to
actually just ask,
is it a heat
transfer process?
All right? And what did
we already say
that you need to
have in order for it to
be a heat
transfer process?
Say someone not named
Miles or your name?
Zach. Not Miles
and not Zach.
So what did we say
that we needed for
a heat transfer?
That's it.
If there's a
temperature difference,
it's heat transfer.
If there's no
temperature difference,
it is not heat transfer.
This is a closed system.
So the only other way
to transfer energy
is via what?
Work. Work.
Is this a heat transfer
or a work
transfer process?
Work. Oh, my gosh.
Crushing it.
This is so great.
I could go home.
That's it. That's the
name of the game.
Heat and work.
You need a Delta T
in order for
it to be heat,
and if it's not heat,
then it's work.
In a closed
system. All right.
Okay. So Thank you.
Yeah. All right.
And what's
going to come up
a lot when we
look into engines and
stuff later is we're
going to start to,
like, idealize some of
these processes, okay?
So again, we
talked about heat
as a way to
transfer energy,
and we talked about,
you know, work.
And, right, if
we think to our,
like, first law,
so our first law,
was the change in
internal energy
of our system, right?
The difference
there, right is
the difference in the heat
transferred in minus
the work transferred
out, okay?
And there's like
two cases, right?
So what is if I showed
you this formula,
um, You know, well,
I guess I have
it on the board,
so I'll just say
it, all right?
But one case is
that we have
no heat transferred with
the control volume, okay?
We call that adiabatic,
adiabatic, ar?
All right. So that's
an adiabatic process.
One, all right? Okay.
You may recall
that we wrote
these little deltas there
because work transfer and
heat transfer are what
are called path
functions, right?
We need to know, we
need to think about
all the details,
how the pressure,
how the volume varies
throughout the
whole thing to
be able to write
that there, okay?
Internal energy, though,
on the other hand,
is a property, okay?
Properties don't give
a shit, right, about path.
They're just a
point. I use
colorful language when I
want to drive home
a point, right?
So That was a
dad joke too,
because it was a point.
All right, fine.
So you have here
the DU with it,
right? So this
difference, right?
This only depends on
the start and
the end, okay?
Now I'm saying I have
no heat transfer there.
I have, you know,
this path function
that's there.
Once I get rid
of this one,
right, what do you think
happens to this
little delta here?
And what does it become?
So I have on the
one side something
that only depends on
the start and
the end, right?
I got rid of the other one
that was a path dependent.
So this becomes Yeah, DW.
Okay. All right. We'll
go into a second.
We'll have some derivations
and look into it.
But basically,
you have this
as, you know, thing
that happens.
You can also go
the other way where you
have something with
no work transfer,
all right?
And let's say
only, you know,
heat transfer
associated with it.
There's not like
one term for it,
but a very common one
is a process of
constant volume.
So you might have
constant volume heating.
That's how all
your engines run.
Auto cycle runs on
a constant volume
heating of the cylinder.
Um, and in that case,
there is no work,
and there's only
heat transfer.
So you have basically the
opposite situation
there, okay?
Okay, final thing
about notation.
So when we write
something like this,
when we talk about a
heat heat transfer.
So I don't say,
like, heat,
I say heat I try to
not say heat. Heat
is not a thing.
So heat transfer, um,
I He transfer there.
I'm going to talk.
I'm going to write this
as first quarter one, two,
I've actually
like state one,
and I'm going
to state two.
So a difference
between state one
and state two, right,
that process is going
to be a first quarter,
two or let's say a
W one, two, right?
There is no W one,
there is no W two.
Yes, please. The
equation the negative.
Oh, that's a good
catch. Thank you.
I mean I didn't make yes.
Okay. Other questions?
In here example
of a resistor,
wouldn't the
resistor like he
transfers heat transfer to
the But through
the boundary,
let me think about
the boundary, right?
So if that basically is
inside of there, no.
Yeah. So if I have
something like outside
my boundary that's hot
and then the
inside is colder,
then through that I'll
have heat exchange.
Yes. But I could imagine
a scenario where
you might draw
a boundary
differently, right?
And there, maybe that's
resistors outside
of your boundary,
maybe out here making
things really hot,
then you would have
heat being
exchanged there.
Okay? And another one
we'll get into
is like paddles.
We have that in an example
today where we
basically spin
a paddle and mover.
Okay. Other
questions? Okay.
So first quarter
two. The final one
for this slide is
that a lot of
times so for these
problems here,
we're probably
just going to be
talking about Q and,
first quarter two,
one, two, like that.
But later on, when
we get to things,
like I said, the
Braden cycle,
the jet engines there,
we tend to deal
with rates, okay?
So we're going
to talk about
the rate of heat
transfer, all right?
Um, and we're not going
to follow the beautiful
Leibniz notation.
We're going to
revert to, you know,
Newton, and we're just
going to put a dot, okay?
And the meaning of the dot
then is that, right,
it's joules per second
or watts there, right?
So when I write that, this
is essentially right the,
you know, dq dt,
all right? Okay.
Yeah, exactly.
So here, right? So we have
some heat in. It's the
amount of heat in.
You know, typical
problem, I
have things like
mass involved in it,
some amount of
time, right?
And so then,
right, if I had
that amount of Q
over that time,
I come up with that Q dot.
The final one
that you see on
here is sometimes
in the problems,
they're going to
write the amount of
heat transferred on
like a per mass basis.
So they might
say something
like Q, like little Q,
and all little Q is
is big Q divided by,
let's say, the
mass, right?
So if I have
some amount of
mass that's
inside of this,
um, control volume, right?
Then it's just
going to be the big
Q divided by little M,
gives you a little Q,
and then the
same for work.
Sometimes you'll
see a little W,
and that's just
big W divided by
the mass involved
there, okay?
This will make more
sense once you
start to get into the
homework in that.
All right.
Okay, so let's analyze
the work transfer, though.
So let's focus here for a
second on the compression.
Let's say the compression
of I should
keep this back.
Hold on.
All right, the compression
of our cylinder here.
So in this problem, we
have, this
piston cylinder.
It's being moved
down, right?
So amount dH, okay?
The surface area of
this can this
be seen? Yeah.
The surface area then of
this cylinder is S, right?
So we're going to
call that as S.
And so there's a
pressure, right?
Basically, there's
a pressure
inside of here P, okay?
So the force acting,
so the force that we
need to push down
on here is then going
to be equal to this
pressure, right?
Or let's say, you
know, um, you know,
the pressure that's
inside here times
that surface
area of the um,
of the cylinder,
okay? All right.
When we move, right,
since the surface here is
perpendicular to the
direction that
we're moving,
this area S times dh
represents a
volume, right?
So the dv here, right,
is equal to this
S times times dh.
And so the work All right,
dw here is then equal
to the P times,
um, uh, well, I can
write it this way.
I can write P dv,
I can say P dv,
and then if I substitute
the dv into here,
then I'll have,
um, P times S
times dh, right?
All right. We can
recall then for
this system,
all right,
this amount of work
we can represent
right as being
equal to the
integral, let's
say, from state A.
So if this is at
this position, maybe
this is state A,
and then state B is when
we move it down from
A to B, then of PdV.
All right? Cool.
All right.
Good. What I'm showing you
here on these plots are
a couple of different
variants, right?
So the challenge,
really, the challenge
in this kind of, uh,
um, of integral here,
and I guess I could
substitute this in here,
so I could go A to
B of PS d just
for completeness,
but I want to focus
on this for a second.
The challenge of
integrating this
is that pressure and
volume are
normally independent
properties, okay?
So what can happen
is if you think
about the ideal
gas equation,
pressure and
volume are linked.
And if I think
about this problem,
as I compress this,
so I decrease the volume,
what do you expect to
happen to the pressure?
The back of the room.
It increase, right?
And so, you know,
in order to
execute this then, you
have to be able to,
you know, write
pressure as
a function of volume
here, all right?
Say with me, okay?
There's different
cases for
how that might happen.
So if we assume,
for example,
that what's inside of
here is an ideal gas.
So PV is RT, we could
say, all right,
let's first of all,
just focus on the case
where pressure
is constant.
If pressure is constant,
I can pull it outside
of the integral,
and then it's just
PDV, all right?
So how does
that look like?
PDV constant
pressure process.
On a PV diagram,
it's just a flat
line, okay?
Um, and the work
that's transferred is
essentially just
the area beneath
that line because
P is constant,
it's Delta V. So
essentially P Delta
V there then is
just the shaded
rectangle below that line.
Right? One.
Next case that could
be interesting is,
again, let's say it's
still an ideal gas.
We keep the
temperature constant.
So it's isothermal.
If I keep an isothermal,
this is then what my
process is going
to look like.
I could write the pv RT.
I could go and say Pv is
equal to RT or
this is the specific
gas constant.
This says units of joules
per kilogram per kelvin.
I could say P is equal
to RT divided by V.
I could substitute
that into there.
Temperature is constant,
so I can pull that
out of the integral,
and what you're going
to be left with is
essentially the
integral of DV over V,
right, which is
the natural log.
So I'm going to
have a natural
log times all that
constant stuff,
and you're going to
get this line, okay?
Cool. The last one
that you have here,
the green line is the case
where we don't have
any heat transfer.
I'm not going to go into
deriving that today.
We'll get more
into the future,
but it's a really
important case.
It's a really
important case, right?
But the take home
message of this,
so why I'm spending all
the time, is that, again,
this whole point
of being able to
execute this
integral is that
you need to know
how pressure
depends on volume
for each part of
the art of the
process, right?
And if you get
it right, right?
So if I have if
you're able on
a PV, you know,
diagram to start
at something like
point A and go to point B,
if you know, you know,
that's pretty bad.
That's like a
parametric plot.
You know, but if you know
basically this whole path,
then the work
is nothing but
the entire area under
that integral, all right.
Questions about
that? Cool.
Great. All
right. So again,
that's about the process
there, something
like A to B.
If we then go, you know,
full circle, so
I could say,
okay, let's stick with,
you know, things that
are constant pressure.
So this isobaric case
of work transfer,
let's say all my heating
is done, right,
isochorically.
So that's the case where I
don't do work transfer,
and I'm only transferring
heat in and out.
So the du is just
equal to dc.
I can end up with
a rectangle that looks
like this, all right?
And why is this important?
So if I think about,
let's say the process
of I bear compression,
you know, if I think
about this is A to B,
C to D, so here,
what I have at the
lower pressure is I
have, expansion
process, right?
I have some work
below that's done.
I have C to D here, some
compression process.
I could take the
area under that.
What's important to
know about a cycle is
then the area that's
shaded in between, okay?
So if you take the
entire integral
and you end up on
that cycle to
where you start,
it's the shaded area
on something like
a PV diagram that's
relevant, okay?
We'll call that. You know,
in the future, we'll
get through it.
But essentially, it can
tell you about the
network, right?
Because again,
this process
here on the bottom would
be the network
transferred in, or out.
The one below here is
the amount transferred in,
and then the
difference is what we
call is the network, okay?
In your car, that's
like go, right?
So that's like, you
know, what you
get out of it.
What's more subtle and
not exactly
clear, you know,
here at the moment is that
when you do a full
cycle like that,
the network that you have
out must be equal to
the net heat that you
transfer in, okay?
And the reason is
that you need to
end up at the same
initial state.
You can't have any
change in energy.
So whatever you
have out must be
equal to ultimately
what's transferred
in, okay?
That'll become clear.
Yeah, I can't
emphasize this enough,
but heat and work are
just transfer mechanisms.
These are not properties
that should be made
clear because
these things are,
you know, properties,
but that whole area
under it is what
represents the
work, all right?
Cool.
Again, these things
happen at boundaries,
like I showed you,
um, you know, there,
especially with
the cylinder.
This is kind of
an obvious one
where this is happening
at a boundary and
it's pushing it down.
These boundaries
can shrink.
So these control
volumes that
I show you here,
this dashed lines,
just like I did
with the blue,
it's just for
completeness, right?
I could show that
this is then the
new, um, you know,
blue boundary after,
um, you know,
moving it down,
these things can
basically shrink
and expand, you know,
with them, but work in
heat then are
always happening
at at a boundary, okay?
And I emphasize, you know,
that they path, right?
The way to visualize path.
Why is it a path function?
Because this is
the path, right?
Yeah. I tried to
make that also clear
here that the
point is that,
you know, until we
know, you know,
complete information then
about the path, right,
we're going to say
for the path
functions that
they're basically little
delta, all right.
I think the book is
pretty consistent on this,
but if you go on the
Internet and read,
all right,
not everyone is super
consistent with
theta with the Delta
notation, all right?
Okay. I can show
this one again.
So just to remind you
a little bit about sort of
these differences
in the past,
why we care
about the path,
you know, consider this
expansion process.
So here we're
starting off with
the same temperature
and the same volume,
and what I want
you to focus on
is the work
transfer, all right?
Here you have reversible,
no heat transfer in,
so reversible adiabatic,
and on the right here,
irreversible and
adiabatic, right?
All right. And so, again,
you basically have
the same conditions,
but you have differences
in the final
state, all right?
So you have differences
in the temperatures,
differences in the volume.
And as a result of that,
you have differences
in the amount
of work transferred, okay?
Someone raising their hand
or no? Phantom hand?
Cool. All right.
Yes. All right.
So just to
really, you know,
uh, be a broken
record here, right?
So here we have same
initial state, same final,
just like I showed
on the other plots,
right with these different
process A process.
B, right, in process
A, with the green,
you have less area below
it versus process B,
where you have
more area, right?
So in one of them, you
have more work transferred
out of your system
than the other
case, right?
Cool. Yeah, I
think I said this.
Yeah. So here,
you know, again,
so we did this with
the Delta Vs, right?
So volume rate
is a property.
So we can write
it that way.
Whereas, you know,
with Delta W,
when you integrate
it, it's W one,
two, and not Delta
Delta W. All right.
Um, let's get to
an example because I'm
getting a little
bit bored.
So, um You know,
here, right?
So when you set up
a problem, right?
And we'll get
to the one in
a I'm going start to
draw the one here,
and then it'll
help us, right?
So the first stage
here look at
this problem is,
you're going to
draw this box,
this beautiful box that
someone put a
propeller in.
I guess it could be a
fan, you know, do that.
So we have this
beautiful, you
know, propeller.
Okay, so I'm following
this part right.
When I analyze this
thing, all right?
So I'm going to draw
then within here,
this, um Let's
control volume.
With that.
So basically with
the control volume,
I'm drawing the
boundaries.
You know, with that,
in this problem,
I'm saying that I have
some Q out, right?
So I have some
heat that's being
transferred, you
know, out of that.
I'm told that
I'm transferring
some work into that.
So we have some
work that's
being it's basically being
transferred, you
know, into that.
We're told that we have
here, like a fluid,
a known fluid, and
they tell us about
our states, right?
So we have this process.
So it's state one, Okay?
I'm told that
I know U one,
U is equal to 800,
you know, kilojoules.
And I don't think I
have any other information
except that the
Q out is 500,
you know, kilojoules
and my n is
equal to 100
kilojoules, right?
So how do you analyze
this problem?
So you draw this
control volume here.
And this is going to
be essentially, you know,
any changes in
energy into here,
we're going to call
as Delta E S, okay?
All right. All right.
So this is, you know,
when I teach this
before, this is
like your bank
account, okay?
You can have credits.
You can have debits.
This one sure
looks like a lot
is going out and a lot
less is coming in.
That's what happens
when I go to Safeway.
So, you know, so you have
a lot more out than you
have, you know,
in there, okay?
And just like
accounting, again, yeah,
we're interested
in the credit.
So for the credits
that come in, right,
we're going to call this
as E in, all right?
And then this is going
to be subtracted
by E out, all right?
So I think that's
pretty straightforward,
the amount that you have
the change in
what you have
here in this
control volume is
equal to the energy
we transferred
in minus the energy
that we transfer out.
What are the ways that we
can transfer energy in?
Work in heat. So
we can call this
as like, I don't know,
Q in Q in plus W in
minus Q out plus
W out? Okay.
Do we have any heat
being transferred
into this?
No.
There's no heat
transferred in,
Is there work
transferred in?
Yes. Is there heat
transferred out?
Is there work
transferred out? No.
What you rewrite this
then as saying, Okay,
the change in the
system is then going
to be equal to W
in minus Q out?
Cool. All right.
That looks good.
How do we deal with
the energy of this
system though?
Okay. So we can go
with the initial.
So the initial would be
what like E one, right?
Okay. Say it again, sorry.
Yes. Yeah. And then
it's state two plus.
I'm not sure to follow.
So let's talk
about this. So if
I just say about
the Delta E system,
and if I wrote E one here,
what would one
naively write here?
E two, right? Okay.
And how would we
represent let's
stay with E one.
So what do you think
E one is equal to?
Exactly. So more
specifically, right,
in our case, E one is
equal to E one, right?
And you could say,
Professor, why is that?
I could say refer
to lecture one A.
Or what I could say is
that in this system,
You know, the
only energy that
we can store is like
thermal, right?
I don't have a lot
of kinetic energy.
Probably actually,
if you look at
a kinetic energy is
like kinetic energy
means, I don't know,
throwing a rock
or, you know,
the fluid is only
basically possessing
internal energy.
But it could be that
if we pump this
really high,
maybe you might have
potential energy
or kinetic energy, right?
But right now, it's
only, you know,
we don't have,
you know, E.
No, we don't have
potential energy.
KE or PE, we don't
have that, okay?
Cool. What about U E two?
What would E two
be equal to?
U two.
You two, right? Not
the band. All right.
So here you have then U
two minus U
one, all right?
And if we
rearrange this or
if I write on a
different part
of the board, basically,
right U two would
be equal to
U one plus W in
minus Q out, right?
And we know one is
800 kilojoules.
W in is 100 kilojoules,
Q out is 500
kilojoules, right?
So I have 800 plus
100 is 900 -500.
So that should be
400 kilojoules
is equal to
two, all right?
That's pretty much
the class, okay?
Like, everything else
is just going to get
more I mean,
it'll get cooler.
Like,
we'll definitely get into,
like, neater things,
but, right, that's
pretty much it.
Like this is, again,
thermo accounting, right?
I have this
control volume.
So the change in the
amount of energy
stored here is
equal to how much
I put into it minus
how much I take
out of it, okay?
Um, all right.
You'll also notice
here that I started to
write things like
Qn, Wn, Q out,
and W. That's because
I spent a long time in
a German speaking country,
and they love things to be
perfectly accurate.
All right?
So just writing, like,
Delta, you know,
E is equal to Q minus
W implicitly
means that, like,
in that case,
so what is Q,
Q, If it's positive
means heat in.
If Q is negative,
it means heat out.
If W is positive,
it means work in.
If W is out, it means
work is positive. It
sounds exhausting.
I'm like, my face hurts
talking this much.
So I am going to generally
be very explicit
about Q in,
W in and that, okay?
What does this
mean in terms
of sine convention?
It means that
these are always
positive
quantities, right?
So if I'm writing it
in this way, right?
So this is energy in,
right, that's positive.
This is energy out, the
negative is there, okay?
So that also simplifies,
you know, with it.
Yes, please.
You find a way to get
work out of this?
We can start a company.
I'm I'm at a loss.
So most of the time.
No, it's not true. I mean,
I'm just saying that
this is a thing.
You know, if
you want to get
work out of a propeller,
you know, how
do we normally
get work out of
a propeller?
Yes, please. Yes,
you move a fluid.
You basically hit it,
right? Like, you know,
I got a little more
of the turbines.
You move a fluid, it
hits that, and then
it moves, right?
That's generally how you
want to learn
more about that.
You take AI 146.
I usually I taught
that last spring.
So yeah, you
move the fluid,
and then from
that, you can
extract work from
the kinetic energy
of the air, right?
So that moving
energy of the air,
you transfer that into
the blade, and, you know,
you spin, you know,
a generator and
get that, okay?
And that's foreshadowing
what's to come.
But in that case,
you need air
to be moving in, right?
Now, I can't bring
air in, right?
I got a I got
a stuffy room here with
a fan spinning, okay?
Yeah.
It's also an interesting
thing because if
you think about
this problem,
this is what
you would have.
Well, on a hot day, right,
you'd have more Q
in, right to it.
But if you just
basically spin
a fan in the room, right,
you're heating up
the room slowly
because you're transferring
work into that,
and over time,
it might make
you feel cooler,
but over time,
if you had no way to
get the heat out,
that's not an that's
not a winning
solution, okay?
Alright, cool. Other
questions about this?
We're crawl. Pretty soon
we're going to be
walking. All right.
Yeah, that's what I
mentioned before.
Again, when we represent
an entire cycle
on a PV diagram,
and we take the shaded
area of that there,
that was the net heat in.
I could make an
argument about it with
this one if I put
this to what's best.
I put this here and
I put this one
to the side.
Okay let's erase this.
All right. And
so we have here,
we wrote our Delta E,
um, you know,
system is equal
to E in minus E out.
We said the E
in is Wn plus
Q minus W out plus Q out.
We said for the E
system that this would
be, um, there, okay?
So, okay, that's good.
So that's a fact.
I'll write that.
If I have this
as a PV diagram,
and let's say I have
this state to this state,
to this state,
to this state.
So this is one,
two, three,
and four, okay?
And it's a cycle.
I'm going to start at
one and I finish at one,
just like a
track, all right?
You run around it, you
end up where you
started, okay?
I love that sport,
but, you know, it's
kind of weird.
Like you just like syphis,
you just, like, keep
pushing a rock
up, alright?
The point, though,
is that there is
no change in the system
in a cycle, right?
Because you're
going to have you
one minus, You won.
It's zero, right?
So then if I
rearrange this,
then I can define
something for you,
let's say W net
is equal to W
out, minus W in,
and let's say Q
net is equal to
Q in minus two
minus Q out.
So if I rearrange this,
I put that to
the other side.
So this equation,
I'm going to
have W out minus
Wn is then equal
to Qn minus Q out,
which is just W net is
equal to Q net. Okay?
So I can write that
or you can just,
like, look at your
plot and just say,
I'm going to color.
Like, it's, you know,
kindergarten
and you color.
You know,
mathematically, it's
the same as what
I'm saying here,
alright? Cool.
So then this only
applies then when
we're talking about
heat and work interactions
with a closed system.
So no mass, no mass
there, alright?
So, that's it. So
you should be able
to talk about a cycle,
internal energy,
go to a party
and talk about
heat and work transfer,
work transfer processes.
You're going to
blow them all away.
So I'm going to
close it here.
If you have any
questions, I'm up here.
Thank you very much.