Alright, I got 210.
Let's get started.
So today, energy analysis
of closed systems.
So quiz one.
It's coming like winter,
all right, in some
parts of the world.
Basically, right, you're
going to take this
at the computer based
testing facility.
Click that link.
You can learn about
it. It's wonderful.
You'll be able to
start registering
for this on the 25th.
Look to Quiz one page.
This is one stop shopping.
So all the stuff you want
to see, details are there.
So you're welcome to
email me or the GSIs,
but please just,
have a look at
that before asking
because it might be
able to answer
your question
much quicker than I
will be able to reply.
We have four problems.
I'm not going to read them
here, but yeah,
essentially,
this is what you'll
be asked to do today,
we're going to talk
about Adbtic expansion
in one of the
problems, okay?
Module one review
is posted today.
So if you want to
generate, like,
practice quizzes and get
into game shape with it,
you'll be able to do that.
So just go to
the P one module
and review how this works.
When you click
on it, right?
It's going to generate
these four questions
that are for you.
You can take that, and
then you can go up
and click it again and
generate new ones, right?
So for those who are yeah,
like quizzes, that's
what you can do, right?
And the way the point
of this is that this is
exactly how it'll look
like then on
the assessment.
So the way you
look at this,
also the workbooks
and all of that,
it should be like one
to one with it, right?
Okay, so after
today, right,
we're going to be
able to do PDV work
for kind of commonly
encountered things.
You know, you're going
to be able to say that
basically the first law is
conservation of energy.
And then, again,
I'm going to
continue with
practicing how to
do general energy balances
to control volumes.
This kind of
repetition, okay?
Okay, so why do we
care about that?
Um, Oh, sweet. Okay.
That playback isn't there.
So now you get to use
your imagination.
This worked last
year. D's here.
He could tell you if
this video worked.
Anyway, so piston
basically piston
or PDV work, this kind
of boundary work.
It's pretty much how we
move everything
still, right?
We have electrification,
but everything that's
like terrestrial,
so that means like,
not an airplane,
like long haul trucking,
internal combustion,
all basically
involves, right,
this expansion and
contraction with it,
right?
So engines, compressors,
and things of that,
um you know, nature. Okay?
So these little devices,
the pistons and
the piston side,
that's what we've
been looking at
and why it's important.
Okay. Maybe I'll try
it in the browser.
Are we brave? I think
it's noisy, though.
Okay, Howden, I don't
know what Howden is.
Yeah, there we
go. Let's see.
Do we have sound?
That doesn't
give me sound.
That's terrible.
It's only on mine. Okay.
And it's fun music.
Anyways, yeah, so you can,
like, have a look and see,
there's lots of, you know,
neat things out there.
But, you know,
this is sort of,
you know, super
important for movement.
You know, it's
kind of like
how an engine
takes a step.
Also, if're like, really
into if you're
like a real, like,
big nerd like meaner and
steam engines, like,
you can go see this
stuff at, like,
Tilton Park, right?
So they have, like, legit
operating steam engines.
I think they run on oil,
though, not coal with it.
But if you want to, like,
really geek out
about trains
and all that, like,
you can go and see,
you know, essentially
the piston movement
and stuff they have there.
Okay. Surely, you have
better things to do on
a Friday than that.
Um Yeah, so again,
we're talking about the
moving boundary work.
Some clarifications,
though, right?
So in cars, you know,
in that, these things
tend to move quickly.
You know, if you
ever, like, read
like a tachometer
on, like, a vehicle,
like internal
combustion, right,
you're measuring
essentially, like
thousands of RPMs, right?
It means like a movement
like that is
probably going,
you know, ten times
in a second, right?
At least sort of ten
times in a second.
And that is
definitely not,
right, equilibrium.
However, it's not
too bad, right?
The assumptions that
we'll make are basically
not um, you know, too bad.
And really, the
goal of thermo
is for us to kind
of see what is,
like, the right direction.
So even if you make
these assumptions,
you know, with the math
and the physics there,
we get to really know
if we're kind of moving
into a right, you
know, direction.
But for the purposes
of this analysis,
we have to start
somewhere.
So we start with kind of
quasi equilibrium with it.
Okay? All right, um,
So how do we, like,
classify this?
So there's a couple of
different terms
that'll come up.
One here that we see is
this term sort
of polytropic.
I'll get into
a second what
that, you know, means.
But, you know, when
we're thinking
about work, right?
So this sort of
boundary work
or expansion work that's,
you know, that's
there, right,
is the integral of what?
PDV, right? So basically,
you have P dV, right?
And the name of
the game here,
in order to do this
integral is we need
to know pressure as
a function of
volume, right?
So we want some
function here,
that's essentially,
right, the function
of the volume,
and then we do a
substitution, okay?
So this polytropic
is nothing
but let me make
sure I'm not getting
ahead of myself too quick.
All right. It's sort
of fair game now.
All right. Right? So we're
basically going to write
something like this.
We're going to say
pressure times
volume with volume to
the N exponent is
equal to a constant,
all right?
Now, this is
polytropic, okay?
Who can tell me
off the top of
their head maybe
something that looks
like PV equals something?
Sure. Name and
what's the answer?
Exactly. So what, though?
When would that be useful?
When would the NRT
equal to a constant?
Isothermal Isothermal.
So the isothermal case.
Exactly. The exponent is
what then in an
isothermal case.
N equals one.
Uno, right? Eins.
So N equals one, and
you have that, okay?
So that's one
of the cases.
We'll talk about two other
we'll talk about
another case later on,
which is where we have
no heat transfer,
adiabatic, okay?
And they're going to have
sort of a different
constant, okay?
But the sort of general
formula of PV to
the N equals a constant
is this polytropic,
you know,
polytropic process.
What I'm showing
you here is
the case of N
equals to one,
and that's your
isothermal case.
So as was mentioned there.
All right.
Okay. So if we
take this way,
we can do the
substitution.
So if we do the
substitution
there for the
polytropic, right?
So the boundary work
is then equal to
a constant times
an integral
from state one to
state two, right?
So I'll rearrange
this, right?
So basically, I
have a constant.
So P is equal
to a constant,
then divided by V
to the end, right?
So then what we'll
have is D V divided by
V to the end, okay?
That should be
an N. It's an N
there, right? All right?
And if we know state one,
so if we know state one,
which a lot of
times we do.
So what does that mean?
It means basically
if we know P
one and we know
and we know V one,
we can substitute that
for the constant, right?
Because you basically
you would have a, uh,
um, a C that's equal
to p1v1, right?
P1v1 to the N,
and if, right?
So that's fine.
So we can do the
substitution.
And if we have
isothermal, right?
As was just mentioned by
your classmate, right,
we'll have N equal
to one. All right.
And so if we do With
that N equals one,
I'll just write it out
just for clarity, right?
So boundary work
is then p1v1.
That's the
substitution for C.
We then have the integral
1-2 to two of
dv divided by V because
that's also there.
And so what you're
going to end
up with then is p1v1,
natural log natural log
of V two divided by
V one. All right?
Cool. And then that's
the plot, right?
So that's
essentially the plot
that you have there,
and where that right
What is the
integral of this?
What's the integral of
any variable dx
divided by X?
Natural log of X, and
in this case, right,
plus a constant, or
if I integrate
it 1-2, right?
So let's say it's 1-2,
then this would be X two
divided by X one, right?
Okay. So natural log
of V two divided by V one.
Good. Any questions
about that? All right.
And what's one way that
you could double
check yourself
on this area, right?
So use color.
Kindergarten.
I love coloring.
Okay? So you just go
in and there you need
color and you'll end up.
And then that area under
the curve then
should be equal
to what you have what
you have here, okay?
Great. So that's one case.
That's the isothermal
the isothermal case.
All right.
So I can move I guess
we can see with this.
Okay, the next one that's
important is the
isoberic, right?
So the isoberic case
is where we have
a constant, um, right,
a constant volume or
a constant pressure
expansion,
you know, process.
So, in that case, right,
if we define this as
the control volume,
we can do an
energy balance.
So we can do an energy
balance on that.
So the change in
the energy of,
let's say that
control volume.
So this dashed region
is equal to the
energy, right,
that we transfer in
minus the energy that
we transfer that we
transfer out, okay?
What are the
ways that energy
can change in
control volume?
Name? Cody and.
Right? So he would be
a transfer mechanism.
I would say, sorry,
we're transferring
energy in
and we're transferring
energy out.
So, what are ways
that we would
quantify changes
in the energy
of that control volume?
Energy, internal
energy, kinetic energy.
And because this is
a closed system,
will we have changes in
changes in mass or no?
No. For now,
I'm not going to
get too far ahead.
I love to foreshadow,
but that's a little
too far for me.
That'll be Week five.
All right. So we have
changes that can
change in energy
control volumes,
change internal energy,
change in kinetic energy,
change in
potential energy.
And then this is equal to
the ways we can transfer
energy in and out,
which is work,
W in plus Q in,
right, minus W out
plus Q Q out,
all right? Cool.
I won't have anything
to do with this, you know,
in, you know,
in these cases.
And obviously, if
we had sort of
heat transfer processes
and stuff involved,
which usually is the case,
when you do something
isoberically, you
could analyze it.
What I would like to
focus on, though,
here is the work
it's just the work
transferred out process.
I like to define I
like to define that.
And in the second
half of the lecture,
we'll get into
the combined heat
and work processes and
those changes in
internal energy.
Okay? So we'll
focus on the W out.
And in this case,
right, the only way
that we can have work
transferred out
of this system
is due to the
expansion, right?
So we can have the W
out here is again,
equal to the integral
from state one
to state two of P PDV.
So it's a constant
pressure process.
What can I do here?
No, this is not Jeopardy.
I'm like watching
Jeopardy.
I saw the same guy
answer the question,
like ten times in a row.
Your name? Hussain.
Say it again?
Hussein Hussein
The P, right?
So basically,
it's isobaric,
so it doesn't have a
dependence on volume
integral of one
to two of dV.
So then this is what?
This is pressure V
two minus V one.
And that's very
easy. I mean,
that's that's prek
stuff, right?
So basically, you
then just shade right
the area then
under, right?
Basically, you
shade the area
then under that, okay?
So that's isobaric.
So we did what?
Isothermal? We
did isobaric.
Um And what I would
like to do now
is go to another
important case,
which is the adiabatic.
Are there any
questions about this
before I do adabetic?
All good?
Okay. Based on your
answers on that,
I think you guys get this.
All right, let me erase.
Let me erase.
All right.
Okay.
Cool. Yes, please.
What is a
polytropic process?
Polytropic. I don't know
enough Greek to
say what it means.
I mean, what it
means is this PVN
is C. So an ME 40,
this is what polytropic
means to you.
Well, I mean, so now
I'll give you
cases, right?
I give you basically
physical versions,
right?
So, you know, so,
you know, what is when
N equals zero,
what is that case?
Which is? How do we
call that isobaric, right?
When N equals one
we had Which was?
Isothermal Isothermal.
Okay? So I'm going to
give you the last case,
which is adiabatic, okay?
And then I'm going
to think and
figure out if I know
any other ends.
But I know 01,
and then what I'm
going to tell you,
I think for air is
like 1.4, okay?
Cool. Other questions?
That's a nice
question. I'll think.
You maybe think
over the weekend,
you know? Okay. All right.
Um, Okay, so
idiabatic All right,
so we have our right,
we have our
schematic there,
and I'm already
showing you,
right, kind of what the
process looks like.
In this case, I'm
doing a compression
process.
So I have adiabatic.
What I'm showing here is,
why am I showing you a
compression process?
Because I plotted
it wrong.
What I have here
is the expansion.
But basically, right,
this is compression.
If it went BA that
would be the um,
that would be the
expansion, all right?
And what I want to
prove to you, so
in this problem,
is that, um, PV to.
Yeah. So basically PV,
what I want to prove
a problem statement
or show, maybe
I'll say show.
Proof feels like
a strong word.
Show that P V to
some constant Gamma is
equal to a constant
C, okay? All right?
We've already worked
with this, right?
The N equals zero,
the N equals one, right?
So what I'm saying
here is that this
is basically
the N equals Gamma,
N equals Gamma
case, all right?
I'm not going to draw the
schematic since
it exists there.
What am I going
to assume, right?
So I assume that
we have ideal gas.
So we have an ideal
gas inside of
the inside of that
control volume.
We have no heat
transfer, all right?
And that's what
adiabatic means.
So in other parts
of the course,
when I say adiabatic,
I mean no heat in or
out of my control
volume, all right?
We're going to neglect
Delta KE and Delta PE.
And we're going
to say that
work is transferred.
Through expansion.
All right, so I don't have
any wires or anything
like that in there.
We're just talking
about expansion, right?
So P dV.
All right.
Okay.
Yeah, so what are
the physical laws
that we have involved
with this, right?
So what laws are
we talking about?
We're going to talk about
the conservation
of energy.
All right. A ideal guess.
Mm hmm, mm, mm. Okay.
So with this,
we can go on.
So what we'll
start with is,
we'll start with our
conservation of energy.
That's usually how
we begin with this.
And then after that, we'll
apply some ideal
gas relation.
And then from that,
if you wanted,
you could start
to substitute
properties and
insert to produce
plots and stuff
like that. Okay?
So our conservation
of energy, right,
is we have a Delta E CV.
So the control
volume I'm talking
about here is the
dashed red line.
So the change in
the energy of
that control
volume is equal to
E N minus E out, right?
The way that
this can change,
right is we'll have
Delta U plus Delta
K plus Delta P.
So changes in
internal energy,
kinetic energy
and potential
is equal to the ways
that we can transfer
energy in and out
of its system, which
is just work in heat.
So I'll W in plus
Q in minus W,
minus Q out, right?
Do I have another color?
I do. All right.
So this is out, right
from our assumptions,
and this is out.
What else is out?
Yes, please? I'm sorry.
Yes. Thank you
for catching
that. You got my back.
I appreciate that.
Comments on this?
Okay, so what else goes?
Actually, would that
have even have mattered?
No, right?
Because you don't have
any heat
transferred, right?
And if we assume
this to be, right?
If we assume this to be
an expansion process,
what does it mean
for W in and W out?
Louder.
W is zero.
W is zero. Exactly.
All right.
So then if we assume
that it's expansion,
then we only have work we
only have workout, right?
Cool. All right, so
then our Delta U, right
from this, right?
Our Delta U is equal
to the negative
of W equals to the
negative W out,
right? Do, do, do.
Okay, so we can write
this in differential form.
So I can say
that d, um, um,
d is then equal
to Delta W, um,
the negative of, uh, uh,
Delta W, um, out, which,
with our assumption
of this only being
boundary work is
basically the equal
to the negative of P
dv, all right? Okay.
Um, So that all
looks fine and well.
But what we need to do to
make this work is we need
to deal with
this internal energy
term here, okay?
And the way that we
can deal with this is
we can recall the changes
in internal energy for
any control volume that's
at constant volume.
So forget this. Changes in
internal energy for
a constant volume is
equal to CV dt, okay?
So if you remember
the definition of
the specific heat
at constant volume,
right, this is d dt
for constant V, okay?
And that's right.
And the way that we
introduced this,
right, is we had said
that, you know, basically,
when you analyze
a control volume,
where you don't allow
the boundary to move,
the relationship
between internal
energy is equal to Cv dt.
All right? That's
definition. Bless you.
Okay? So what this
means is we can
rearrange this,
and I want to write
this as little U.
So D, little U dt because
this is a little C,
is that d so change
internal energy of
the control volume
there is equal to
CV little Cv
times dt, okay?
And what I will be able to
do up here then is to
substitute this in.
To here, I can write the M
little d is equal to
the negative of P dv.
And then I can
substitute into
that little d,
the CvdT, right?
So then I have M, Cv dt
is equal to the negative
of P dv. All right.
And we'd like to get
rid of temperature now.
So basically,
now we'd like
to get rid of temperature,
and this is where we
use the ideal gas
for the ideal
gas law, okay?
So I can write the
ideal gas law,
right is PV is equal
to M times RT,
where R is the
specific gas constant.
And I can write
a differential,
a D on both sides like
that, okay? All right.
On the left hand side, we
got to use a chain
roll, right?
So this is basically
going to be V dp
plus P dv.
This is equal to
M is a constant.
We don't have
mass in or out.
The constant
is a constant.
And so what you
have left is then
r dt, all right?
And we can rearrange.
So if I just put the
m to the other side,
I can have dt is
then equal to V dp
plus P dv divided
by R, all right?
So if we combine
this and the equation
I have over there,
maybe I'll go full screen.
What that have?
Okay? So if I combine
this and this,
I can write that M
Cv times up here,
V dp plus P dv
divided by R, right?
So that's nothing but
cv dt from before,
and then that's
going to be equal to
the negative of P dv.
All right? Okay. I'll
spare you the details.
You can click through
the link and see, like,
sort of the full steps,
but I'd like to
organize this in
the following way.
So I want to
write that I have
CV plus R divided by
Cv times dv divided by
V plus dp divided
by P is equal
to zero, okay?
And again, this is
just rearranging
with this.
If I take the
integral of that.
And if we assume that
the specific heaps
are constant,
so we could write
here, constant CV.
All right. What you're
going to have is
that CV plus R
divided by CV times
the natural log of
V plus the natural log
of P is equal to
a constant, okay?
Because that's what
this is, right?
I pulled this out.
This is a natural log.
That's a natural log.
Um, This here we
can call as a
constant Gamma.
So we'll call CV plus
the gas constant
divided by CV as Gamma.
And one of the properties
is a natural log
is right I can put this to
the power of that, right?
So I can write
natural log of V to
the power Gamma plus
natural log of P
is equal to C.
And another nice
thing about
logs is that
when I add them,
I can multiply
them, right?
So here I can write
natural log of P,
V to the Gamma
is equal to C.
If I take the exponent
of exponential of
both sides, right?
I can add basically PV to
the Gamma is equal to
the exponential
of a constant,
which is basically
equal to
some new constant, right?
The exponential
of a constant is
basically a
constant, right?
Basically constant.
And that's it, okay?
And so PV to the Gamma,
equal to a constant
is a specific
case of one of
these polytropic
processes where we have
PV to some N
equals a constant,
in this case, the N is
equal to Gamma, okay?
This Gamma, we sometimes
give it a name.
We call this the.
Anyone know? If you
had to give it a name,
what would you call
it as the first word?
A constant.
Say it again. A constant.
An A constant? Okay.
We're creative
in here today.
Other names? Adiabatic
adiabatic index, okay?
Yes. Okay? And actually,
this CV plus R is then
actually the
specific heat,
okay, at constant
pressure.
We'll get into
it in a second.
But this Gamma, you
can look up and
see because the world's a
confusing place, you know?
In some textbooks,
this gamma
will actually be
written as Kappa, okay?
Sorry. But, like, if
you look in the book,
I'm pretty sure it's
Gamma as a as a value.
I wish they had
more letters in their
alphabet, okay?
It's a beautiful language.
All right. All right.
Any questions about
that? Yes, please.
What did we do?
What did we just do?
You basically came up
with an expression for
a work transfer process
where you have no
heat in or out, okay?
And what I'm
telling you is
that there are
systems where
that's important,
where it's important
that I know
a state and I
expand it without
having any heat in or
out, and it produces work.
And this will help you
to string together
points when you
analyze cycles later.
So knowing if I have
an expansion process
that's at constant
pressure,
knowing that I have
a expansion process
at constant temperature,
and knowing that I have
an expansion process with
no heat in or out, these
are kind of three,
I want to call
them, almost
axiomatic in
analysis of work
transfer processes.
Okay.
I mean, no, because
you can watch
your video. So
three, right?
You have constant
pressure,
constant temperature,
no heat addition.
Got it. And in
all of them,
you have work transfer
through a boundary
moving, okay?
Yes, please.
Depending on which
process that equation for
every single one of them.
I mean, it depends
on the process.
You got to say, like,
what it is,
isothermal, right?
So isobaric N is zero,
isothermal N is one,
adiabatic, it's
equal to Gamma,
which in the case of
air, I think is 1.4.
Yes, please. On this side?
This side's got it.
It's like the right
side of my brain.
Okay, cool. Alright. Good.
Okay. So here's what
I want to do
now that I put
you all to sleep in
that is analyze.
So here you have a case of
PV with three
different processes,
A, B, C, and three
different work processes.
So the first question
that I have for you
is which one
transfers more work?
If everything is done in
quasi equilibrium
and isothermal,
which one of
these corresponds
to an ideal gas?
And three and
most importantly,
can you, for an
isothermal process,
tell me how much
work is done, okay?
And to remind
you on the quiz,
we're going to do some
stuff with adiabatic.
This is an isothermal
variant, okay?
Let me launch this.
Right, so an
expansion process
like that might
look like this,
let's say, V one
to V two, right?
So we start at the
high pressure,
and we go to a
lower one, right?
Okay, so that's with work.
And those videos
that I showed you,
like the
reciprocating, right?
So the pistons expand,
but we basically got
to bring them back, okay?
And if we want to
get work out of
that kind of a cycle,
right, we need
to basically
return to the
initial state, okay?
So what I'm showing you
here is a process where,
right, I have an
expansion of work,
V one to V two,
right, which is,
you know, kind
of like what we
computed in
this case here.
I have V two to V three,
where I, um, You know,
I have an isochoric
process where
I reduce the pressure.
Maybe I'm cooling, right?
Maybe I'm cooling
isochorically there,
and then I
compress, right?
Then basically I compress.
I go up to V four,
and then at
constant volume,
I increase the pressure.
Maybe I'm adding heat
isochorically, okay?
The most of the internal
combustion engines
you see on
the road and like
that basically run on
that process, right?
Iochoric key
addition, okay,
you know, with that.
So anyways, the
take home message
out of this is that
that still takes
work, right?
So go from V
three to V four,
I need to transfer
work in, okay?
And I have to
pay for that.
So if you do a cycle,
the network you
would get out of
it is the area under
the curve from
V one to V two
minus the area under
the curve from the
V three or state three
to state four there.
So the shaded
green area has
actually done the
net work, okay?
And we're going to use
that a lot, right?
We're going to give
you these cycles,
engines and Brighton and
beautiful stuff for arrow.
It's the area then
between these curves,
which is then going to
be the network out,
okay? Good. What else?
So if I told you that
the shaded green area
is the network out,
what else do you think
the shaded green area
is in a in a
cycle like this?
The net heat in, right?
Because ultimately,
you need to end
up at your original
state, okay?
And from the
first law, right?
We have the Delta
U, right is,
you know, all the
work in the heat in
minus all the work
in the heat out.
So to get back to
the original state,
I can't have
any difference
in the energy, right?
I want to go back to
the initial state.
So whatever I take out of
that control
volume, right,
let's say in work,
network transferred
out has to
be equal to the net heat
transferred in, okay?
Think about that
over the weekend
since you all
gave me homework.
Okay. Are there any
questions about that?
Okay, if not, I am
2 minutes early,
so enjoy your beautiful
enjoy your
beautiful weekend.
And I'm up here if
you have questions.