All right, I got 210.
I'm going to get started.
So today we're
talking about
Exergy another E.
So after today, you're
able to define
the concept of
exergy destruction as it
relates to entropy
generation, right?
Remember that's we spent
the last five
lectures doing.
And then you should be
able to define Exergy,
which is the maximum work.
Basically, you can
get out of a system,
right, from a
specified state, okay?
Yeah, so It's like this.
One of the
longstanding goals
of thermodynamics
was to figure out
how much you could
squeeze out of a
system, right?
Like, how much if I
have this much heat
or whatever
coming in, like,
how much work can I get,
you know, out of it?
That's one thing you
should have in your mind.
The second important
part about this is if
we think about getting
maximum workout,
we're probably
going to be dealing
with reversible
cases, right?
So isotropic cases of
work transfer
as we go from
one state to the other.
That kind of other
state that we go
towards is kind of
like a ground state.
We're going to call that
like a dead state, right?
If you spend a
lot of time on
the Internet like myself
and reading, okay,
you'll hear things
about like heat death,
you know, of the
universe, right,
where everything becomes
eventually the
same temperature,
and we have no Delta T.
We're not there
yet, all right?
So we need a delta
to drive things.
But there's a dead
state involved, right?
And if through a process,
We have some
irreversibilities,
which we had said before,
we're essentially,
you know,
we talked about
isotropic efficiencies,
essentially, you
know, something that
is not necessarily
reversible.
The process of
doing it maybe
generates some friction,
some heat, basically,
some entropy is created.
That is associated with
exergy destruction.
All right?
So what I told
you, entropy,
entropy is maybe
a little bit
like the glagraph is
half empty, right?
A bit of Schopenhauer,
you know, like,
pessimistic thinking.
Exergy is a little bit
the other half of that.
Maybe more
optimistic, like,
you know,
how much work could
I get out of it?
Not how much am I
destroying? Okay.
All right. But I think
before I really get into
the math of Exergy,
I think it's helpful
I thought about
this today,
and I thought it
would be helpful if I
first started with
entropy generation.
So going through a
process of analyzing
entropy generation
for another system
we haven't spent
time with a nozzle.
And through that analysis
of entropy generation,
I'm going to relate
this directly
to Erogey destruction,
which is going to
be Ero destruction
is equal to entropy
generation times,
let's say the
environmental temperature,
which we call is the
dead state there, okay?
And then we'll
wade in, right?
So we'll kind of
gently go into
the exergetic
waters this way.
All right. And then
you can tell me
if that's any
less confusing
to last year's cohort.
All right, so we're
dealing with a
nozzle here.
So a nozzle looks
like this, right?
So the purpose of
a nozzle is that
you want to take
a fluid stream at
some velocity and
accelerate it to a
much faster velocity,
right?
So that means
we're going to
have some gas flowing
in, some going out.
We can call this the
entrance as state one,
and the exit for
the purposes of
determining properties
as state two.
And as usual,
if you want to
follow along with that,
you can do it there,
but I'm going to close
this off because there's
a reflection on the board,
okay? We're
dealing with air.
So our substance
here is we have
air that's entering
and exiting.
Um, It enters at
200 pa and 65
degrees Celsius,
and the velocity
that it's entering
with is 35 meters/second.
It exits at 95 kp
and a velocity of
240 meters/second.
That's pretty
quick, right?
And we have
some heat loss.
There's some heat
loss from the nozzle.
And we're told that
this Q is on a
per mass basis,
and it's three
kilojoules per kilogram.
And the surrounding
temperature
T maybe I'll give
it a variable T
surrounding for now is
equal to 17
degrees Celsius.
And what we want to
determine, determine
We'd like to determine
is the T two,
that's the exit
temperature.
B, we would like
to determine the E.
It says X org destruction,
but I believe that I'm
also talking
about entropy.
B, basically, we'll talk
about X destruction.
Exergy destroyed, I think,
we'll call it maybe
exergy destroyed.
And the variable for that
because why the
heck not is X.
Confusingly, the
variable for
exergy on a per mass
basis here is little X,
just like our vapor
quality was X.
I don't make the
rules, right?
I'm just the messenger.
And this has units,
in this case is
kilojoules per
kilogram, all right?
There. Great. I'll give
the answer already.
So the answer that
we're going to get out
of this is going to
be 34 degrees Celsius,
and the exit you
destroyed here
is going to be
36.9 kilojoules
per kilogram.
I'll just go through
the analysis of how
we arrive at that.
All right, first step in
thermo is we're going
draw a boundaries.
So we'll draw a
control volume
around the bonzle here.
Okay, looks like that.
And what assumptions
do we have, right?
So we have a
control volume.
So we've got mass
entering, right,
carrying energy
in and out.
Because this
is air, right?
We could choose
to use Pi Killor
to compute differences
in things like enthalpy,
but we could
also treat this
as an ideal gas, right?
So I can use CP Delta Ts
also to compute the
same enthalpy changes.
We cannot neglect,
so we cannot
neglect changes in
kinetic energy, right?
We're not going
to do that here
because the whole point
of this device is to,
to take enthalpy
and convert it into
velocity into
kinetic energy here.
We will, however, still
neglect changes in
potential energy.
It's a steady flow
process, right?
So there's no
change, right?
So our Delta M CV,
the change in
the mass of the
control volume is zero,
and the change
in the energy
in the control
volume is zero.
And also the change
in entropy in
the control volume is
also equal to zero, right?
Single inlet,
single outlet.
So our m.in
because of this,
dm dt of the control
volume is equal to m.in.
Right, minus our dot out,
which from this, right
is equal to zero,
right, which basically
implies that our.in is
equal to our dot out
is equal to m dot.
So we got everything
set up there.
Okay, um, we can
write our conservation
of energy.
So we did our
conservation of mass.
Our conservation
of energy,
is the, um, um,
right, the rate of
change of energy,
the control volume
is equal to
e.in, minus E dot out.
Um, From the steady
flow assumption,
E dot N is equal to
e dot out, right?
So we have w.in plus
q.in plus our dot N,
which we just call dot,
enthalpy at state one
plus the velocity at
state one squared
plus g one is equal to
our dot out plus
our Q dot out,
plus our dot out,
which I'll just.h2,
enthalpy at the exit
velocity squared
at the exit, plus gz two.
All right. What goes away
here is we don't
have heat in, right?
We have heat out.
So this is gone.
There is no work transfer,
so there's no shaft work.
There's no shaft work done
in or out of that device.
So that's gone. We
do have a heat out.
We're going to
neglect the changes
in potential energy as
we were told to do.
And we have a Q dot.
We have a Q dot out.
And what
we're searching for it
through this equation,
we need to determine
state two.
We know the pressure
at state two,
but we don't have any
other information.
And so we're going
to use this equation
essentially to solve
for the enthalpy
at state two.
And once we know the
enthalpy at state two,
with that pressure,
we're going to
be able to
determine T two.
So with rearranging here,
specific enthalpy
at state two
is equal to H one plus
velocity one
squared divided by
two minus velocity
two squared,
um, divided by
two and minus little
Q out, right?
And just to remind
you, little Q out,
in this case would
be capital Q
dot out divided
by m dot, right?
So this divided by
that is by
definition this,
and the units of it are in
kilojoules per
kilogram, right?
Cool.
And so there's two
ways to do that.
So one is that we could
just use Pi color
to determine,
so we know state one.
State one from state one,
we know P one, and
we know T one,
which means that
I'll know H one
and one S one from that,
so I could substitute
the H one into here.
I'm given the velocity
at state one.
at state two,
and I'm given the key
transferred out per
mass from the nozzle.
So it means that I would
know right from this,
I would know
then state two.
So from that, right,
I would know H
two and P two is given.
And so what it means
is that I know T two
and also S two
if I needed it.
Totally valid approach.
Another way we could do
this is we could
start off by
writing H two minus
H one is equal to,
right, W one
squared divided by
two minus velocity
at state two
squared divided by
two minus Q out.
And for an ideal gas,
we can take
the specific heat at
some temperature,
assuming that the CP
doesn't change a lot
over the
temperature range,
temperature at state
two minus temperature
at state one is equal
to the right hand side.
We can reorganize,
and we can write
T two is equal to T one.
Um, T two is
equal to T one
plus velocity one squared
divided by two
minus velocity two
squared divided by two
minus little Q out,
and all of that
divided by CP,
okay? Totally
valid, right?
Because we can do this for
changes in enthalpy
for an ideal gas
or can be related to
changes in temperature
through CP, okay?
So these are the two
ways you could go to get
to state two, right?
Which would answer
our first problem
and the answer I've
already given you there.
Are there questions
about this?
Clear? All right.
This should be a cake
walk, all right?
Good. Um, All right.
Now we come to the
entropy generation
and for entropy
generation,
again, we stick with our
same control volume,
the same green dashed
line that I had before.
The rate of change of
entropy in the
control volume,
DSVDT is equal to the
rate that entropy
enters the control volume
minus the rate
that it leaves it,
plus the rate That it's
it's generated, okay?
And the ways that
we can carry
entropy into
control volume,
we could have heat
work, no, right?
Work is not a way
that we're going to
bring entropy in.
Heat is a way we'll
bring entropy
in and flow, right,
a fluid, right?
I can take a
fluid, and that
can possess entropy,
and that can and
that can come in.
There's a steady
flow process.
So from my assumption
I said before,
I don't have any
change in entropy
of the control volume.
I have a balance.
The rate that
is coming in is
the rate that
it's leaving.
And so this means that
it's zero, you know,
analogous to what
we had for the rate
of change of energy
and also of mass.
Um, again, we
need to get to
the formula that
we're interested
in is going to
rely on Gen.
So what we're going to
do is we're going
to say that
capital S dot gen is equal
to dot out minus s.in.
All right. What
are the ways that
entropy is leaving
that control volume?
Name? Andrew.
Andrew? Yeah, we
have Mass leaving.
Okay, so we have an MDOT,
right a Mass Flory,
and we have a little S
to a specific entropy
at state two.
How else is
entropy leaving?
Heat, right?
Name? Z. Zach.
It's always nice to
claim it after
it was right.
Okay, right?
So that's leaving.
So there we have a Q out.
So we know some
heat's leaving,
but that's not
exactly entropy yet.
Where is that heat
being transferred
to, right?
So we have a
reduction in entropy
because it's leaving
the it's leaving
the system.
And where is it going
to? Surrounding, right?
Yeah. So we have here a Q
out that's then divided
by excuse me, a T zero.
And how is entry
P coming in?
So the other fluid.
So basically, you
have also an dot,
and that's times
S one there.
Cool. So we can
rearrange this?
We just go dot,
then S two minus
one plus this Q out
divided by T and T zero.
And this is our
dot dot gen
will look like
that. Mm hmm.
If I divide both sides,
so I need to think
carefully about this.
Hold on. M dot.
This also has an M dot.
I apologize. I apologize.
This should be plus
dot times that.
And then therefore, dot
should also be
there because this
is per kilojoules per
kilogram and
then per kelvin.
So this is the same
units of little S,
and that also needs to
multiply it by dot.
All right. Boo boo. Okay.
We can write this in
little S notation.
So if I divide
both sides by dot,
little dot,
what I'm going to
be able to write,
maybe I'll put it
up here is that
little Gn is then
equal to two
minus one plus Q out
divided by T zero.
And the definition, this
is something I'm going
to tell you now.
So this is
informational, and then
we'll come into
the meaning
of it in a second.
But the connection
between entropy
generated an energy
is the following.
Little X destroyed
destroyed is
equal to little S Gen
times what's
called the dead
state temperature,
essentially the
temperature of
the surroundings.
The temperature when
everything else
has gone to equilibrium.
All right? Not
heat death yet.
Okay. But T zero there.
All right. All right.
And so how do
we get to SGN?
So we know S two.
So if we followed
the Pi color
approach, right?
I could get little
S two from that,
right from knowing
state one.
Little, I'm sorry,
little S two from
knowing state two,
Little S one from knowing
state one Q is given,
and T zero is
also given as the
surrounding the
surrounding temperatures.
So we'd call T
zero equal to
T T surrounding, right?
What's another way
that we could get to
this change in entropy
across a nozzle for air?
If I know the
temperature and
I know the pressure
at the inlet of
my nozzle and I know
my temperature and
the pressure at the
outlet of my nozzle,
is there any formula
we can use for
an ideal gas to compute
the difference
in the entropy?
Yes, please. Name?
Nat. Something like that.
CPDT would be the change
in enthalpy,
though, right?
So CD is what I had there.
Other name? Brian.
That's incredible. I don't
remember from shorthand,
but it sounds.
So it won't just be
that because I have
changes in temperature
and changes in pressure.
But the formula you want
to be looking up are
the so called TDS
relations, right?
Remember, we derived this.
So we had TDS relations
that we derived
from the first law,
and we made assumptions
about the changes
in internal energy
being right CV dt and
so on and so forth.
And the point is that we
were able to
relate changes in
entropy to changes
in temperature
and pressure,
pressure and volume,
specific volume and
temperature, okay?
So if you look at
the TDS relations,
you could also
follow that approach
for an ideal gas
to compute that.
Again, totally valid
approach, right?
Okay. And he's
going to look
it up later for
you all and
remember the
second half of
the formula.
Questions about this.
Okay, so that's exergy.
That's pretty much
it. All right.
So this is the
destruction part of it,
but we can also get
into into the other parts.
But this is really
then the link of
the entropy generation and
ultimately
exergy analysis.
And I would consider
this analysis
to be a modern,
basically a modern
thermodynamic analysis.
So if you think
about where things
are and why is it modern?
For devices like this,
kind of the performance
is maybe obvious.
Like, you look at that
and you think, okay,
that's kind of faster,
that's slower.
But the energy systems
nowadays are a lot more
hybridized, right?
They're a lot more
hybrid, okay?
They're more complex,
and as a result, why?
Why are they more
complex? They're more
complex because
we receive the
energy intermittently.
Nothing is steady, right?
So, you know, we have
day and night,
we have seasons.
One, Two,
we use our energies at
different times for
all sorts of things,
buildings, you know, cars,
you know, manufacturing,
so the loads are
complicated.
And so you end up
with these
complicated systems,
and being able to
say what is the
best is not obvious, okay?
So what you need to
do is you have to
come up with a
framework where, again,
you kind of treat and rank
energy forms equally.
Heat and work.
You can put on, you know,
essentially the same
conversion there, right?
The same, let's say,
quality in a
sense to them.
And this is what
exergy does, right?
It's a way of being able
to say that I can compare
apples to apples and
not apples to oranges.
The first law is tells you
things are apples
to apples,
but it's not true.
The second law tells you
that work and heat
are different,
and what EG tries to do is
to correct for
the fact that
they're different,
that heat is worth less
than work, alright?
Good. Alright, let's
go in, though.
Do I want to do
this example
yet? I could. Yeah.
Let's do this one,
and then I can
go through some
definitions.
So the context of this
is that here we did
this for a steady flow
analysis of a nozzle,
a system I really
didn't spend much
time with before.
And what I want to do now
is the entropy generation
and the exergey
destruction
then of this system,
right, a closed system.
And with these
two, you will have
enough seen enough
examples there
to kind of tackle
both types
of systems when it
comes to exergy.
All right.
I also have to say that
I really like
the textbook.
the textbook,
except for this part.
So if you read
the textbook and
they do this analysis,
I find it downright
confusing.
So what I'm going to do
today is an example
that they have,
but like my way in
the way I've taught
you before, okay?
And if you come to
my office hours
and you tell me,
I don't get why the
book did it that way,
I'm not going to my
answer is going to
be do it this way.
Do it my way.
Okay, so what do
we have here?
So we have our
favorite piston, okay,
that contains water at
100 degrees C.
We have heat.
We draw our boundary here.
The piston is kept at
constant pressure. And
it's being cooled.
So there's some
amount of heat that's
transferred out
between state
two and state one,
and this heat is
transferred to
a surroundings,
which is 25 degrees C. T
surrounding here is code
for dead state, okay?
So you have your dead
state temperature,
which is here.
All the rest of
the terminology
you've heard before,
water means no ideal gas.
You're gonna use Pikere.
Condensation here.
So as we transfer
heat out,
some of the water
is condensed.
That's code four
isothermal, right?
I said it was isobaric.
That's, you know,
the system allows
you to do that,
but phase change
processes are
both isoberic
and isothermal.
So the constant
temperature
there is going
to mean that,
like, you know,
maybe that's useful,
okay? This work transfer.
So because he's
being transferred
out and the pistons
moving down,
works being
transferred in, okay?
A keyword here
is frictionless.
What do you think
frictionless
means for this?
What's that code for?
Okay, I'm going to
start on this side.
A brave soul in
the back there,
Paris. Reversible.
Yes. Okay, reversible.
And when I have a
reversible system,
okay, but the
thing is that
I have heat being
transferred out.
So when I have heat
being transferred out of
a system where I'm
reversibly doing work,
what did we call that?
So it's like the work
transfer process
is isotropic,
but there's a
change in entropy
due to heat, okay?
So I have heat being
transferred out of
that control volume,
so I have a change
in entropy,
but I have no change in
entropy associated
with the work process.
So the word
reversible is in it.
I'm going to make you
all read the book.
I'm going to have
a lecture, and
it's going to be reading
time, all right?
You're going to
have free choice
and there's going to be
one choice internally
reversible, right?
So what formula do I write
when I have something
that's internally
reversible?
Oh, man, ds is equal
to dq divided by T,
right? Internally
reversible, okay?
Why do I do this? Why
do I care about this?
The whole reason why
we do that is because
if the work transfer
process is isotropic,
I can determine
the change in
entropy of that only
with heat transfer, right?
So we write all
of this because
not because I
like letters,
you know, I love letters,
but I don't write
all of them.
I wish we had more.
I don't write
all of that
because I want to.
You do that
because then I can
compute changes in entropy
only with the heat, okay?
The other part
that's like code in
this problem is
these isothermal,
when we do the
integration,
it's going to make
this very easy, right?
I'm going to be
able to integrate
this and take the
temperature out.
So a process
like this that's
isothermal makes
that a very easy
calculation in
terms of a change
in entropy of this control
volume, all right?
Okay, so with that setup,
Let's dive into it, right?
So we've already
drawn our schematic.
I don't need to indicate
anything else there.
It's a closed system,
so no mass in or out.
The properties,
if we needed to
determine them,
we'd use PiKLor.
And this problem,
actually, we don't need to
because we know the
initial temperature,
we know the final
temperature.
And for this type
of calculation,
I don't need to
know things like
enthalpy and internal
energy there.
So there's enough
information from that.
It's quasi equilibrium,
all right?
We have no changes in
kinetic and
potential energy.
All right? The only
kind of work we're
having here is this
internally reversible,
um, you know, compression,
which is here,
and we have heat
lost heat loss to
the surrounding.
Do do.
Okay, so I'm not
going to start
with an energy balance
here because I do not
need to. All right.
For other problems,
you would need to,
you probably would need to
determine a final state.
Here I know the
final temperature,
so I don't need
to do that.
So I'll simply start with
an entropy balance
for a closed system.
Entropy balance for
a control system is
equal.in minus S dot out
plus dot gen is equal to
the change in the entropy
of that control volume,
which I'm going to call
as Delta S system.
All right. We have no
change of mass, right?
There's no mass in or
out of that, okay?
This is the trick to
this problem, okay?
So if you start down
this and you draw
it for that,
just a single control
volume, good luck.
You're going to have
to do weird stuff.
So what I recommend doing,
and this is essentially
what the book does
is that we'll have our
piston and the piston.
So our piston
cylinder device.
I'll draw one
control volume,
which in this
case contains
the water. All right.
And then I'm going to
draw another, right?
So I have heat being
transferred to
the surrounding.
And the other
control volume
that I'm going to draw is
essentially the part of
the surroundings that
gets heated, okay?
So I would go here and
do something weird,
or maybe I'll draw
a control volume,
which looks something
like this, okay?
Yeah, maybe it looks
like this, right?
So I'll have
something that
looks like that, right?
And this should trigger
a response in you.
The fact that I'm drawing
two control volumes,
one where heat's
being lost,
and another where
heat is being gained.
Does anyone remember what
exercise I did for that?
I took a hot
piece of iron and
I dropped it into
cold water, okay?
Every single quiz and
midterm I have ever
given has had an entropy
generation problem
and an entropy
change, okay?
And they all
look something
like that. All right?
So here, I have
something hot,
entropy he's being
transferred out of it.
That means entropy
is decreasing,
and then heat's being
transferred to
something else,
and the entropy
is increasing.
And because this is
hotter than this,
the net change, right?
And so heat being
transferred out of
something as hot as
a smaller change in
entropy than heat
being transferred
into something
at a lower temperature,
which will have a
higher one because it
goes by one over T, okay?
So this is the trick.
You basically draw, All
right, maybe I need
to do it right.
So, like, you basically
draw a second,
right, control volume
around the first one.
What the book calls
this part of it,
the book calls this,
like a boundary.
Allright? I don't
know, like a boundary.
So they draw
some boundary,
and they say, okay,
then somehow the,
you know, the heat,
and blah, blah, blah.
I prefer precision.
So for me, I'm going to
draw control volume
of the water,
and then I'm going to draw
a control volume around
this piston cylinder where
the heat's being
transferred
into it, all right?
Okay. Super.
Now, all right.
Um, overall change,
right? So the
overall change.
So if I talk
about this as,
you know, we can
talk about this
maybe as the water,
and we can talk
about this one as
the surrounding,
just like we did
before, the change in
the entropy of this
combined system, right?
So Delta S system,
which is essentially this
control volume of water
plus this control volume
of the surrounding, right,
is equal to the change in
the entropy of the
control volume,
plus the change in
the entropy of
the surrounding.
So what you're going to do
is you're going to
analyze, right,
the change in the
entropy of the water,
and then the change in
the entropy of
the surrounding,
just like we did
before, okay?
And the formula
you're going to
use for it is this, right?
The work transfer
process is
internally reversible,
no entropy change.
So the change in
entropy is only
dQ divided by T
because it's an
isothermal process,
that T comes out of
the integral, right?
So that's just going
to be Q by T, right?
And essentially, it's
the same, right?
And the T is going to
be the temperature
of the water, which
doesn't change.
And then the other one
is going to be the
temperature of
the surroundings.
Which? What
assumption do you
think you're going to
make the surroundings?
So I'm going to
transfer heat into
the surrounding.
What do you think
you're going to
treat it as?
Thermal reservoir,
you like
life being easy,
and me too, right?
So you're going
to transfer in it
and it's going to
be a reservoir.
So isothermal
water, right?
Constant temperature and
thermal reservoir,
constant temperature.
It's going to
be like a cue
by minus a cube by.
Is it where you're headed.
All right. So we've
dealt with this.
So we said, Okay,
Delta system,
I know from this on
my way to determining
my entropy generation.
Along the way to
determining that,
we can first determine
our Delta as water,
which is actually
what we need
in part A, okay?
All right. And so this,
we can write it explicitly
as, right, the integral,
and it's going to be
the integral from state
one to two of dq,
right, divided by T of
our let's say W for water.
And then this is going
to be the integral
1-2 of
dq divided by T of our
surrounding, okay?
All right. So again,
our Delta system.
All right, the
temperatures
you can take out
of the integral.
Both of them are
constant, right?
The water is constant
because it's
only part of the
water condenses.
That's code for the
quality changes,
but I'm still saturated,
so constant temperature.
All right? And
so that's going
to end up being a Q.
So we have a Q
water, right,
divided by a temperature
of the water,
and that heat is being
transferred out.
So what sign
should this have?
So, you know, if I call
this QW out now
for the water,
what sign would you
put here to indicate
that entropy is
decreasing in the water?
Negative. Negative, right?
That's a negative
you put there.
Okay. And that'll
be plus the Q
surrounding in divided
by the T surrounding.
And because heat's
being transferred
into that, and this is in,
this is going to
be a positive, and
that'll indicate
entropy is increasing.
Now, I said before I
didn't need to do the
energy analysis of it,
but the nice part about
taking those two
control volumes,
drawing them big enough so
that it's
adiabatic, right?
So if I basically
draw that
surrounding one
large enough,
there's no heat in and
no work into it, okay?
There's no heat and
there's no work into
the combined
control volume,
just like with the hot
iron and the water.
And so what that
means is that
there's no change in
the internal energy.
The net result
from the first law
is that Q of
water out is equal to
Q of surroundings in.
That's the other
trick. Again, going
on that previous
example is by,
you know,
drawing
that other control
volume large enough.
Adiabatic, no
work transfer,
no change,
right, no change
in the internal
energy of that.
So the heat that's
transferred out of
the water must be
equal to the
heat transferred
into the
surroundings, right?
But you're smart,
so I didn't
need to do all
that, right?
And we did it before.
Okay. Yeah, so the
overall, like I said,
so this is your right,
this is the change
in the system.
We know it's given
us 600 kilojoules.
That's 100 degrees Celsius
converted into
Kelvin, okay?
So 373.5.
The Qn is again
600 kilojoules,
and the surrounding is
about three is 25 Celsius
than in Kelvin, right?
So that's done.
All right, let's come back
to our formula,
though, right?
So the other right,
when we did our
analysis of
Delta S system for
the control volume,
that was equal to S in
capital S in minus
capital out plus
capital G. If
we look here,
and this is for
now, right?
This is for the
combined control
volumes, right?
So this Delta S system is
the green area plus
the boundary area
plus the water.
Is there any entropy
being transferred into
the combined system?
No. Is there any entropy
leaving the
combined system?
No. So the change
in the entropy of
the system then is nothing
for this adiabatic case.
The change in the
entropy of the system is
equal to the
entropy generated,
which is then our
part B, okay?
So Part A was essentially
determined this,
which we've done.
Part B was determined
this Which which
we've done.
All right. And part
C is what then?
What formula do we
write then for Part C?
Next. I times.
Yeah, so RX destroyed
X, X destroyed here.
I could write a
lot destroyed
is equal to Gen,
which in our case is the
change in the entropy of
the combined system
times T zero,
which is the dead
state temperature.
T zero here is equal to
T surrounding.
And that's it.
So my numbers, so
the change in the entropy
that I had for water,
um So Delta S
of water there.
Where did I put? Delta
S of water is equal
to -1.61 kilojoules
per Kelvin.
The Delta S of the system,
which includes
the reduction
of the entropy
of the water,
but the increase
in the entropy
of the surroundings
is equal to
0.40 kilojoules
per Kelvin,
and then our Xrogy
destroyed I have equal to
120.6 kilo joules. Okay?
So this part was not
actually in the
exercise in the book.
These can be
validated against it.
And again, the way
that I've shown this
is complimentary
to the way
the book has done it,
but I think actually is
a more correct way to do
it based on how we've been
set up before
with breaking
this into those two parts.
Namely, the reduction of
the entropy in one
part that's cooled and
the increase of
the entropy of
the part that's heated.
Are there questions?
Good? Seriously?
All right.
Yeah, and again, I think
the key insight is
to really break
it down into two and then
treat them as
one, alright?
Okay, um, Yeah,
so in general,
if you encounter a new
source of energy,
you know,
maybe some new you go
up the Berkeley
Lab and you
find something weird
and warm up there,
you know, you want to
know what the work
potential is.
How much energy
could you extract
that is useful from it?
The answer to that
question is exergy.
It is also
sometimes called
availability, right?
There's different
names for it,
but it's a
longstanding goal.
So Gibbs, when Gibbs
was doing thermo,
this was one of his
goals was to figure out
what's the maximum work
I can get out, all right?
He didn't call it exergy.
Or available energy
is another term.
Um, This is not
like the properties
we've done so far.
So if you want to define,
let's think about
work, right?
If I wanted to
define work,
right, that was
a path function.
What does that mean? I
have an initial state.
I have a final state, but
that's not enough
to specify it.
There's a path to it.
I could have
reversible paths.
I could have irreversible
paths, okay?
And depending on the
path that I take,
I'm going to get
different amounts
of work out of
it, all right?
Um, Yeah, so in analysis,
what we do is we specify
the initial state.
And that's not a variable.
So that's
basically a given.
And the work output
is maximized when
everything is
done reversibly.
It's kind of an obvious
statement, right?
I do everything perfectly,
and that's the best.
You know, not exactly like
Berkeley you
know, you know,
you know, Berkeley
studentn't get that,
like, you know,
essentially,
but that's the idea.
So you maximize it
when everything is
done in a reversible way.
And the system must
go to a dead state, right?
So if I think about
potentials, You know,
if you think about
like, you know,
what would be, you know,
the maximum, you know,
work out of a turbine,
it's when the
pressure difference
across it is
highest, okay?
What makes it a high
pressure, right?
I just put a ton of
heat into the thing.
I make it really
high pressure.
What makes it have
a low pressure,
you make it cold.
And that's what
you do, right?
You take river water or
you think, you know,
lake water or
whatever, and you
run them through
the condensers.
That's how you ensure
that the steam
is condensed and
kept cold and
basically the
lowest pressure
that can be done.
And you can't really go
below the dead
state, right?
You're rejecting
heat you know,
in those examples of
the rivers and the lakes
and that or the oceans,
right, you're
rejecting that into
the park that's the
lowest temperature,
right?
And that's your
your dead state,
a right Okay.
Um, And so what
is a dead state?
I mean, in a
sense, you know,
it's like trying to
define what is dead, okay?
So, like, a dead state
here is if you look
at your surroundings,
the way that I think of
it is like equilibrium.
If I let everything,
you know,
in here kind of come
to equilibrium,
and then I measure
the temperature,
the pressure,
and the specific volume,
those would be the
dead state, right?
So the dead state
in Berkeley is
different from
the dead state in
Chicago right
now, for example.
I'm getting pictures
from my in laws.
It's cold, you
know? It's like,
so there it's
different, right?
But, you know,
for your system,
that's essentially it.
In general, for
oxygen analysis,
and for the
purposes of this
class, your dead states,
unless it's
otherwise stated,
25 Celsius in 1
atmosphere, right?
And the system will have
no X org when it's
reached that state.
So along the process
in your system,
if you measure your
temperature or
pressure and you're at
that state, you are dead.
You are at the dead
state. There is
no difference in
a Delta T, right?
So heat transfer,
there is no difference
in pressure to drive
a turbine, right?
That's the idea. Okay.
So what does that mean?
So just like when
we did the
analysis today for
the steady flow system
that was open and for
the closed system,
right,
we write write things
a little bit differently.
The energy for
a closed system
looks like this.
So what is it? It
is internal energy,
okay? I'll start
with this, right?
So we have
internal energy.
You have specific volume,
and you have the
entropy, right?
And let's say velocity
in potential energy,
but these we really
don't deal with too often,
you have internal energy,
specific volume,
and entropy
at some state, right?
And what you're
driving towards,
is a dead state.
So these are
all subtracted
by their counterparts
at the dead state.
So you have the
internal energy at,
let's say,
25 Celsius in 1 atmosphere,
specific volume.
At 25 Celsius
1 atmosphere,
the pressure there,
the temperature there,
and the specific entropy.
And let's say if there's
a dead state velocity,
whatever that
means, you know,
think maybe zero, okay?
Or a dead state at height.
Again, maybe the ground.
All right, in that, okay?
So we'll work
more with it.
I know I'm killing
you with, like,
introducing new things,
but it'll make sense.
We'll do some examples,
and I promise.
And if it doesn't
make sense,
then don't do it this way.
Just do entropy
generation. All right.
For an open system, again,
just like when we went
from closed to open,
instead of dealing with
internal energy, right,
we went to enthalpy
because we wanted to
take we wanted our
work term to
be shaft work,
and so we put the
flow work in.
It's the same thing.
So the energy then
is for a flow system.
So the flow can
possess an energy.
That's the enthalpy
at that state,
the entropy and
the velocity
and let's say the height,
and then it's minus
its dead state parts.
This is pretty useful.
So this formula is
used then, you know,
I'll do an
example next time
and data center analysis,
how you do, like
an exergetic analysis
of that there.
But the flow Eergey
in this way is
actually something
that is used and we'll
use we'll use a
lot next time.
Okay.
Now, all right.
So that's kind of
just definition.
I said before
that one point
of Extra G is
to be able to
rank heat and work to
compare apples to apples
when it comes to
heat and work.
The way that
you make heat,
you convert heat transfer
into Extra G is
the following.
I take Q, and
I times it by
this one minus T
over T. What does
a one minus T over T
remind you of
in this class?
In efficiency.
What efficiency?
Who said it? Name?
Ad. Yes. It looks a
lot like Carn, okay?
And that's the whole
point of Carnal,
right? Karal was, right?
Work out divided by
heat in is equal to
one minus the
cold temperature
divided by the
hot temperature.
All I've done here is
I've said, essentially,
let's say maximum
reversible work
is equal to the heat,
let's say
transferred in times
one minus the
cold temperature,
which is what?
Dead state divided by
the temperature from which
it's coming, all right?
And this is how
you rank heat.
You think like Carne and
I can now with this,
I can say, Hey,
now I'm able to
compare apples to
apples with it.
You think about something
like the sun, okay?
The sun is very hot
with like 5,800 Kelvin.
This would be an
approximate formula
for the sun. Don't
get me started.
But the point is that,
you know, you know,
even 300, you know,
divided by 5,000 is a
small number, right?
So for transferring heat
from the sun,
that's, like,
a very high
quality of heat,
right, it has a
very high energy.
It has very high
work potential
associated with it, right?
Sadly, at the moment,
we waste a lot
of it, right?
So, but that's it.
So this is how
we're able to
rank make him there.
If we look at it, so
if you were to say,
and we'll do this,
we'll talk about,
you know, we'll have
some steady
flow of system.
We'll have some heat
and work and
mass coming in.
That overall
will constitute
an energy, right,
a rate of energy
transferred in,
there will be some
energy that's
transferred out
in the form
of heat work in mass.
A lot of times
maybe it's heat in,
heat and mass that are in,
and a bit of heat out
and hopefully a
lot of workout.
And in that process, if
we have irreversibilities,
there will be
energy destruction.
And the point is from an
optimization
point of view,
that's something you
would like to minimize.
You'd like to minimize
the destruction of that.
Okay, so, inevitably,
the question that
will come up to me,
is this on the quiz?
It is not. However, I
will say two things.
The first is that
it's on the homework.
Yes, and there
will be maybe
more of it in
Module three,
because I love this
stuff, and it's useful.
For the thermodynamic
project,
because this is a
modern analysis,
this may prove useful.
If you're interested in
more sophisticated things,
you know, it
can be helpful.
If this is
something you want
to go into into
the future,
if energy and that type
of stuff something
you want to do,
learn it. Like, learn it.
I have a lot of
notes and stuff.
I teach energy
conversion principles.
Let's use
the data center
class next semester.
We'll be using
things like this
in that class.
It'll tell you things
like waste heat.
So if a process and
to produce heat.
Literally,
all of the problems we
have today is that we have
data centers that are
giant toasters, okay?
They're great and
making toast,
but they also make
things warm, and
we don't do anything
with that heat.
If you do extrogen
analysis,
you can assign an
economic value,
not just like,
Hey, it's useful,
but you can do conversions
based on the
temperature of
your heat and
turn that into
dollars and then go
to someone and say,
like, you should do this.
This is sensible,
okay? And make money.
Get a job and
make money, okay?
Yeah, so we'll get into
this. There are a
lot of examples.
You can read about
these things again.
I can talk about it.
You can read it there,
but it's not just this.
So with that, you can
define exergy destruction.
You can say
what exergy is.
I'm going to
close it. I have
got like 1 minute up
here for questions,
and then I got to go
get my wife, okay?
Thank you. Have
a great weekend.