All right. I got 210.
I'm going to get started.
Today we're moving out of
power cycles and
into refrigeration.
Before I get started, that
means that we've
closed Module two.
So it means you have
an assessment
coming Quiz two.
Please see the
quiz two page,
your reflexes to email
and contact me.
I love that.
However, to make you more
informed on your
question to me and
the GSIs and the readers
who worked very hard,
read this page.
I promise you, 90% of
your answers are there.
Reservations,
self reservation
start tomorrow.
I have extra office hours
next week at lunchtime
in the I room.
And I recommend you
look at Module two review.
So there's
previous midterms
that we've done in
this class that
are there. We'll
keep adding them.
And just to remind you,
you're expected
to be able to use
the Jupyter Ab
Workspace Module PiCor.
So really look at
Homework nine,
see some stuff in there
because that's
an expectation.
It's an expectation
of this
class that you're
able to go in
and basically
define a function
that is a turbine, right?
Cossors giving
inputs and outputs
and stuff like that.
Okay, in terms of
your problems,
you're responsible for
entry regeneration,
your two power cycles,
and then fundamentals.
So the way you
should see this is
relatively easy,
you know, good,
and that two pointer is
probably the hardest
problem, okay?
So great.
So actually today, you're
going to be able
to introduce
concepts of
refrigerators and
heat pumps and measure
their performance and
analyze the ideal vapor
compression refrigeration
cycle, Maya.
Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday, Thursday Friday.
So it's the dates on
the courses dates.
It says the two dates.
Other questions?
Okay, heat pumps.
So the plot that
I'm showing you
here is from a
couple of years ago
showing you the number
of units sold as
a function of time for
heat pumps and
gas furnaces.
And three years
ago, there were
more heat pumps sold in
the United States than
there were furnaces, okay?
And today's lecture is
going to sort of
reinforce why.
Um So why is it important?
Well, one, I mean,
in electrification,
if you have renewable
sources that power it,
essentially,
you're not using
natural gas then
to heat, okay?
So it's a decarbonization.
The second thing is
that it just makes
economic sense.
What I'm going to show
you today is that
the heat that
I transfer into a
building to heat it,
I have one unit
of electricity
to move three units
of heat, okay?
That's what we're
going to see.
So there you would
say, okay, well,
what if I just ran
and transferred
work into a resistor
and got heat out of that?
That's one for one, okay?
That's not good.
Right? But it's still
done, you know,
and with heat pumps,
especially when they
get cold outside,
sometimes that's all
you can do to do it.
But anyways,
that's a three to
one that's organ
analyzed today.
How's that
possible without
violating the first law?
Okay, so what does
it look like?
It's a relatively
simple system.
Um What's the general term
for this is called
vapor compression,
a vapor compression cycle.
So what does that
mean? I have
a compressor that is here.
What is it compressing?
It's compressing a vapor.
I have a vapor that's
coming in here.
I'm compressing that.
That's being sent then to
a coil where it condenses
and releases heat.
So heat is
transferred out here.
You get a condensed state,
that goes through a
throttling valve,
an synthalic process,
so a big pressure drop,
and essentially
you get then
that fluid ready to boil.
Where then it
absorbs heat.
So this operation here
is as a heat pump.
So what are you
pumping, alright?
Essentially,
you have this system,
which is outside,
and you're taking
in heat from
the outside where
it's cold, okay?
So you're taking
in heat from
the outside where
it's cold in,
and you're pumping it into
an indoor space where
you're transferring
that heat
at a higher
temperature, okay?
So it's kind of weird.
I'm taking heat from a
place that's cold, okay?
Pumping it in and actually
warming, but it
works, a right?
Um, The more
commonly seen one,
and this is one
that's been
implemented in
this country for
basically like 100 years
in homes and stuff,
is what you would call a
refrigeration
system or HVAC,
so heating ventilation
and air conditioning.
So the air
conditioning part
of this is shown here.
So how does
that look like?
Exactly, you know,
just swapped.
So essentially, this is
your indoor coil, right?
So this is your house.
Let's say that
you want to cool.
And then this is
the outside where
you want to pump the heat.
So same thing, same drill.
I have a vapor that comes
in on my compressor.
I pressurize
that, it warms.
I condense it on
this coil and you
blow the fans.
If you look
like a rooftop,
if you see what's
called central air,
you'll see these
units on the side
of the house that blow air
over basically big
radiators that are there.
So you're
transferring the heat
from that warmer fluid
to the warm outside air
goes through a
throtting valve,
big pressure
drop in cooling.
You boil that.
This is what you would
then have inside
of the home.
So at this point,
you'd have here
this evaporator,
which is there,
which is absorbing
heat from
the house, let's
say, evaporating.
So the exit here, you're
a saturated vapor that
goes back into
the compressor
and so on and so forth.
Okay. But the point
is that with
this technology,
so the air
conditioning side
is very well established.
Carrier hear the
name carrier, right?
He was a pioneer in
developing this.
I uh, you know, in this,
if you want to ask
yourself why it's
called air conditioning
and that cooling,
it's an interesting
question, okay?
So conditioning comes from
how people used
to treat yarn,
okay? It used to
be conditioned.
You leave it
in a room, and
that conditioning had
to do with humidity.
So a big part
of this, which
we're not going
touch on yet,
but I'm alluding to
in the future is
the conditioning,
which is actually
basically the regulation
of the humidity
in the air.
Okay.
Today, I'm going to
just talk about how
you move the heat.
Later on, we'll
get into how
you actually control
the humidity.
And that gets into
comfort and what
comfort is,
and it's a long
history and it's
an ongoing debate as to
I would say,
what's optimal?
What is comfort? Okay?
Yeah. So anyway,
so this is, again, a
more familiar system.
And then, well,
not in this city,
the weather is,
like, perfect.
But if you go
everywhere else,
then, you know,
you need either it's too
hot or it's too cold.
And you can
switch this and
then turn it into
a heat pump.
Okay. So the second case
where definitely you
still have it here,
and it would be common is
that same system
as I've shown
you for the cooling mode.
So essentially
air conditioning,
in a sense, applied
to a refrigerator.
So refrigerators operate
the same principle.
It's still vapor
compression.
The noise that
you hear them
with the fridge is
the compressor,
and it's the same
drill, okay?
Where you're
transferring heat
out of is the
enclosed space.
So that's the heat you're
absorbing into the cycle,
and then where you
reject it is basically
in the back of it.
So if you look in the
back, you'll see,
like, long coils and
radiators there,
and you have the
cooling the warmer heat
or the heat being
rejected to,
um, with the
temperature with
the fluid as a
higher temperature
than into the
ambient, okay?
Yeah, so that's it.
So I'm going to
go through I'll
derive now sort of,
you know, how we talk
about the performance.
So the way that we rate
the performance of
these systems is by
a coefficient of
performance, right?
The main thing, right?
Why we call it
coefficient of
performance and not like
a theral efficiency
of ether is that
a CO soon ea, right?
What's allowable
there, like zero,
less than equal to one
for a thermal engine.
And for a COP, okay,
this is always
greater than
or equal to one, okay?
So it's not an
efficiency in the sense.
It's still a ratio of
a desirable quantity
divided by what we
have to pay for,
but its number is
bigger than
bigger than one.
Excuse me while I
get a new marker.
Okay. Is this
better? Much better.
Okay. All right.
So just to then
to start and take us
through the analysis
of the cycle.
So we'll draw it again.
So here we had
a compressor
where we were putting
some work right into this.
This was going up and then
passing through
a condenser.
So I had some Q dot
out, which was here.
This is then going through
a throttling valve, right?
So here, this then goes
into your
evaporator, okay?
And then back into
the compressor.
In terms of the state,
so the way that
I've labeled
the states is
that at the exit
of the compressor
is State two,
the entrance is state one,
exit of the condenser
is State three,
and the exit of our
throttling valve
or expansion valve
is state four, right?
Just like all the other
steady flow analysis
that we did, right?
We're neglecting, it's
a steady flow device,
so the change in mass
of our individual
control volume.
So if I j control volume
around my compressor.
I do it around my
heat exchangers.
expansion valve,
and again, my
heat exchangers,
as I showed
this here, this
should be a Q dot.
All? This should be aq.in.
All right, so the change
in mass of each of
those control volumes
is equal to zero.
The change in energy
in those control
volumes is zero,
and the change
in entropy in
those control volumes
is also zero, right?
The steady flow
assumption.
Right? And what
we'd like to do
right in this
analysis is we'd to
determine the COP
for a refrigeration.
Cycle and a heat pump.
Just make sure
that's still
visible a little bit off.
Okay. All right.
All right.
And then we want to
determine and then
determine the COPs
assuming reversible.
All right.
So we assume that
both those cycles
then operate in a
reversible manner.
So this will be
the strategy
for analyzing a more
realistic system,
and then this will
essentially be how we
determine the
maximum efficiency,
which is the Carnal.
So we'll do a
carnal efficiency,
but now for a
refrigeration
and a heat pump and
not a heat engine, right?
And resume
reversible operating
between two thermal
reservoirs.
Okay. All right, to do.
Yeah, and so we can
talk for a second about
the properties before we
get into more of the
energy analysis.
So one of the most
popular refrigerants
that's out there
is R 134 A, okay?
So when you're determining
properties in this system,
you're not working
with water, okay?
And the reason why
you're not working with
water is because
water does not boil.
Well, it can, but it's
not great for boiling
at room temperature,
or lower or higher,
where you would need it.
You need other fluids.
You need other
fluids that are more
volatile at these
conditions,
and this is one of them.
These are fluorocarbons.
Another very widely
used refrigerant
is CO two and ammonia.
If you eat French fries,
which I love, and
my kids love,
ammonia is probably maybe
the largest
refrigeration systems
on this planet
run on ammonia.
The reason why
we don't use
them in whole foods and
stuff is because it's
Kind of dangerous, okay?
It needs copper.
It's not super good.
So in those cases,
you might pair up
ammonia with CO two.
So you might
call this like
a top cycle and
a bottom cycle,
like we did before
for the Rankin.
We'll get to how we
can pair up things.
But these are pretty
important ones.
If you have, like,
a small fridge,
like a beverage fridge,
they don't run
on any of these.
They actually run
sometimes on butane,
like lighter fluid, okay,
those things are
also volatile,
but they don't
use those in
very large
quantities. Why?
Yeah, exactly. So
what Kai said, right?
If a beverage fridge
is kind of explosive,
I don't know.
So anyways, but
these are the ones,
but you'll primarily
be in this class using
PCalor to determine
the properties of
RO 134 A, carbon dioxide.
And then I don't
actually we'll have
to see with ammonia.
I don't recall for
doing it, but I think
R 134 A and C
two are two of
the most common ones that
we work with. You
don't really care.
You just declare
substance equals this,
and then it does the
lifting for you.
Okay. But anyways,
you'll use
PClor to determine
these properties.
Do do do, where are we at?
All right. So
if we get into
the specific devices now.
So if we get into
our energy and
entropy analysis
of these devices,
like one to two
is a compressor,
and a compressor
works with vapor?
A pompas for a liquid,
a compressor is for vapor?
And we don't work
with multiphase.
You're basically
compressing a
vapor with this.
This is adiabatic,
it's an adiabatic.
And we have, it's a
reversible, right?
We can say for now, um,
We can say, you know,
in the first step of
the analysis to get
to state, you know,
two S, right there,
we can say that
little S one
is equal to little S two.
What's the logic
behind that?
We have an adiabatic
process that
operates reversibly
emits steady flow.
So we have no gen,
that means.in is dot out,
in as one equals
dot out as two,
m.in ism dot out.
So you'll end up with,
you'll end up
with that, right?
Um, Good.
So that's for
our compressor,
for two to three on
the condenser, right?
Condenser. Condenser here.
It's isobaric, right?
So our Delta P across
any heat exchanger,
we're going to assume is
zero unless
otherwise told.
We have no shaft
work, right.
Our W dot is
equal to zero,
and the exit states here.
So the exit state like
our buddy we talked
with Ben before,
the exit state of this is
going to be a
saturated liquid.
So X three is going
to be equal to zero.
All right. Three to four
is your expansion valve.
So three to four
is expansion.
Valve. And this is
adiabatic, right?
So we have adiabatic,
and there is
no work, okay?
And then for
our evaporator,
so then excuse me,
four to one here,
evaporator.
Evaporate evaporator.
Again, it's a
heat exchanger,
so your Delta P
is equal to zero,
and you also have no work.
Obviously, the point
of it is you want
to absorb heat, okay.
For all of these things,
we also neglect, right?
We're neglecting globally
for all of this.
Changes in kinetic energy
are zero and changes
in potential energy
are also zero, right?
Okay. For your
compressor then,
that means that
your w.in is an
m.h2a minus H one,
the actual one.
Again, I'll write
down how we use
isotropic efficiencies
if needed.
For our condenser,
our Q dot,
out of the condenser is
your M dot times H
three minus H two.
I'm sorry, the other way.
So the condenser
heat is going out,
a state two A has the
higher enthalpy H
two A minus H three,
your expansion
valve, so we
neglect changes in
potential kinetic energy.
You have no heat transfer
and you have no
work transfer.
So what does this mean
for this process?
What about the inlet
is equal to what
about the outlet?
Say it again, Cody.
Exactly.
It's a nice enthalpic
process. Thank you.
H three is equal
to H four there.
I And then our last one
is then with
the evaporator.
So our evaporator then,
our Q dot N is
equal to M dot,
right, because
it's evaporating,
it's absorbing heat.
So what you'd
expect then is
that the enthalpy
at state one
is then greater
than the enthalpy
at state four,
m.h1 minus H four.
If we If we
come back to this H
twoA, for a compressor,
the isentropic
efficiency of
a compressor is defined
as the minimum work in
needed to compress divided
by the actual work.
So the minimum would
be H twos minus H one.
The actual one would be
H two A minus H one.
In general, if you
were given that
problem here,
this is a piece of
information that
would be given.
You determine H twos,
by one piece of
information to get
to it is that you
assume that the
specific entropy
at state two is equal to
the specific entropy
at state one,
and then you basically
solve for HA.
The light condition
would be given.
Mm hmm. Okay. All right.
Now we've got this.
This is my these
are my properties
here, my efficiencies.
So if we come
now to the COP,
so for the COP,
this is, right,
the ratio of, you know,
what I want to what
I have to pay.
So for a
refrigeration cycle,
what I want is Right?
So if it's cooling
something, right,
the desired
output is that I
want to maximize QL,
what I'm going to pay is
the network in, okay?
So this would be,
right, your Q dot.
And in this case,
this Q dot is what
is absorbed by
the evaporator.
So this would be in
our case here, q.in,
right, is the
heat absorbed
by the evaporator.
And then the network in
is just w.in, right?
The reason why
we don't have it
being a networking is
because we are
working with
an expansion valve, right?
We're working with
an expansion valve
here because
it's convenient.
If I didn't use an
expansion valve here,
what other device could I
use to expand my fluid?
So I have a compressor
that is compressing what
is kind of like the
inverse of a compressor.
A turbine. That's
exactly right.
So you could go
in and you could
replace this
with the turbine
if you wanted to.
And then instead of
this being w.in,
this would be
aw.net in, okay?
And the reason why we use
an expansion valve
is because it's
cheap and turbines
cost money, okay?
And we want a
cheap, you know,
fridge or whatever, okay?
But if you wanted to,
you could go in
and look and maybe
see if there's
opportunities for
maybe if you wanted
to boost the
COP even more,
it might make
sense then to do
that expansion process
with the turbine.
Okay, so what does
this look like from
what we've defined?
So our q.in is at our
evaporator, right?
So that's our M dot times
H one minus H four.
And then our w.in
here is from
our compressor
that's M dot HA
minus H one and
let's go away.
And so that's the COP then
for a refrigeration cycle.
You can do the same
thing for the heat pump.
So the COP for
the heat pump,
all that's
different is that
the desirable quantity
is not the q.in,
but it's the Q dot
out of this cycle.
So you have here
a Q dot out.
And that's the
heat rejected at
the higher temperature
divided by your w.in.
And so your Q dot out
is in the condenser,
that's dot H two
A minus H three,
and that's dot H
two A minus one.
Okay, get rid of
the end dots,
and you have it.
Okay? All right.
And the reason why this is
not a violation
of the first law.
It's instructive if
I come back to here
is if I drew
a control volume around
the entire system,
capturing how energy is
coming in and going out.
All right. So The way
that energy is
entering here,
so I write the first law
applied to this
control volume,
I have w.in plus q.in
is equal to Q
dot out, okay?
And so for you
to be able to
absorb something like
three units of heat in,
okay, for maybe like
one unit of work in,
it means that the sum
of those two
things must be
equal to the heat you
transfer out, okay, there.
So you'll have to
put more heat out,
but this is basically,
um, right, the trick
that we're dealing
with here, okay?
Um, Yeah,
and so you can rewrite
w.in also in another way.
I can say that w
dot N is equal to
q dot out minus q.in.
We'll use that
in a second.
All right. Mm hm.
All right.
So this is it.
So when you're
analyzing the vapor
compression cycle,
this is for the heat pump
or for the refrigeration.
This is the way you
do it, all right?
I've included
the whole part
on the isotropic
efficiency.
Like, that's it, all
right, for the
loop, right?
It's analogous here to,
like, the rank in
like we had before.
This is what you would
have for refrigeration
and then for heat pump.
Now, what we
can look at is
answering the second part
of our question, right?
So, this one is All right.
This one is done, okay?
Here was the COP
for the heat pump,
here is the COP
for refrigeration.
Now what we'd
like to do is
the Carne analysis, right?
So the COP for the
refrigerator is
equal to the
right, the q.in.
And this is at the
lower temperature.
What I'd like to
call this now is
Q dot L. This is how
the book describes it.
And our Q dot out
here that I'm rejecting
to the hot side,
I'd like to call
Q dot H. Okay,
so the desirable thing
in refrigeration is
an output is the Q
dot L, and the input,
as I wrote for the
first law here,
so this would then be
Q dot H minus Q dot L.
I'd have Q dot
L divided by
w dot N is equal to Q
dot L divided by Q dot.
Q dot minus Q
dot L, right?
Dividing top and the
bottom by Q dot L,
what you'd have
is one divided
by q dot H divided by
Q dot L and minus
one. All right.
And just like with Carne,
we would like to
transform these
into temperatures,
and that's what we're
going to do right
now, all right?
So for any cycle, right?
If I take the integral,
dQ by T here,
this must be less than or
equal to zero, okay?
In the case when
this equals
dq divided by T is
equal then to
zero for a cycle.
So this is basically
the integral
right around the
entire cycle.
When this is
equal to zero,
this is when it's operating
reversibly, okay?
Good. Are you with
me? All right.
For our process, Right?
Our heat exchange is
happening from two
thermal reservoirs.
So, if it's a thermal
reservoir, right?
I can pull the temperature
outside of the integral.
And what I'm going to
be dealing with is
a heat addition and
a heat removal.
When I'm doing
heat removal,
right, that's going
to be negative.
When I'm doing
heat addition,
that's going to be
positive, right?
So here, I have Q dot
L divided by T, okay?
I guess we'll write
that as rate format,
but we can do
this as a Q dot L
divided by T
because that's
right this is being
transferred in, right?
So my convention
will be that way.
And then this is from T L.
So imagine here in
this process that this
is a thermal reservoir
that's here that's a TL,
and then imagine
that I have
a thermal reservoir where
I'm transferring
heat into,
which is at H, right?
So then this is
basically going to be
Q dot H divided by my H.
And because this is
a reversible cycle,
that's going to
be equal to zero.
Can rearrange this?
If we rearrange this,
we can write this as
a Q dot H divided by
a Q dot L is equal to
a H divided by a tl.
What that means
then for the COP
of my refrigeration cycle,
so this is equal to
one over now with
the substitution,
H divided by l minus
one. All right.
You can do the
same thing you
can do the same analysis.
You can write the COP for
the heat pump in
the same way,
except instead of dot L,
it's dot H. And
what you'll
have then is one
minus Q dot L
divided by Q dot H.
And you go through
this, same process.
The COP for a heat
pump operating
reversibly is
then equal to 1/1
minus L divided by
H. So what does this
look like here?
All right. So what
I'm showing here
is just for the case of
the heat pump, right?
So I have here the
Carne efficiency of
the heat pump
as a function
of the outdoor
temperature, okay?
So in this case,
that's TL, right?
The horizontal line is
when it equals to one,
when I have a COP of one,
and the red line is
what I'm writing
here, okay?
Again, it never gets
to I don't know.
This is pretty
rare. Here, okay?
So if you're in,
like, Berkeley and in
the winter and stuff and
you're looking
at, you know,
whether a system like
this makes sense,
at 0 Celsius, you
have a COP that's
greater than ten, right?
So one unit of
electricity in,
I move ten units
of heat, okay?
Of course, that's the
upper limit, right?
That's a
theoretical thing,
but this kind
of tells you,
you know, you're
cooking with
something special
here, right?
Um realistic systems that
operate in the
neighborhood,
I think of three
to 54 COPs here,
which we'll do in
the next analysis.
We'll go in and
look at a real one.
But that's the
promise of it, okay?
When you try to pump heat
in from things
that are colder,
at some point, it
becomes very difficult.
So in real operations
of heat pump systems.
So in my beloved Midwest,
out there in the winter,
there are times when
the temperature gets
so low that it's
impractical.
And fortunately,
at that point,
you switch over from
pumping heat to
essentially running
the electricity
through a resistor
and heating that way.
Okay, so there are
cutoffs and with it,
but in a lot of
locations that
are more mild but
kind of chilly,
these things make
a lot of sense
to install, right?
Just economic sense
before you get into
decarbonization or
any considerations
like that, okay?
Are there any
questions about this?
Okay. If not, we
will continue.
Dick do, dick, do.
I I can leave this up.
This one, I can
also leave up,
and this one can go away.
Okay. So in this problem,
what we have is we're
working with R 134 A.
Okay, we're working
with R 134 A.
Again, just a refrigerant.
The R stands for
refrigerant.
R 134 A, you're
told that you have
a condenser pressure
condenser pressure
that's equal to 800
pa. And you have
an evaporator
temperature evaporator
temp that's equal to
-20 degrees C. We want
to determine What do
we want to
determine the COP
of this system and
the total
power total power
required to service
a 150 kilowatt
cooling load.
All right.
So here we're saying
cooling load.
Sometimes with
these systems,
when you speak
about, like,
chillers, they'll
talk about tons
of chilling.
And all that means
is that, like in
1 hour at that
cooling load,
you can produce,
like, one ton of ice.
You have a very nice
homework problem
that deals with
ice production,
slury production
there. Yeah.
But here, we're,
you know, we're
keeping it simple
and calling
it a a cooling
load. All right.
Um, Okay, so again,
this is our
system, so we have
aw.in the compressor,
our heat out through
the condenser,
isothalpic
throttling valve,
heat heat absorbed
by our evaporator.
This cooling load here,
right, is essentially
than that, right?
This is basically we're
looking for, you know,
we have a Q dot
L that's then
equal to 150 kilowatts.
Um, what's the total power
required to do
this, right?
Essentially, what
we're looking
for is on aw.in.
So we're searching
for the w.in,
and to do this,
we need to know the
Q dot L divided by
w.in or Q dot
L divided by Q
dot H minus Q dot
dot L. A. Mm hmm.
All right. And so
we're going to
go through now is
essentially the
states, right?
Because we have our
governing formulas there.
We've already
derived, then
the COP of the
refrigeration cycle.
So the answer to
the first part
is here, okay?
So that's what we want.
And the answer to
the second part is
our q.in, right?
So this is a Q dot N,
which is our Q
dot L, okay?
All right. And
so the name of
the game is we need
to determine, right?
So to go along with this,
we need to determine
the states there,
and we also have to
determine our MDOT.
So from the beginning.
So state three,
we can start from
state three.
Okay. So state three
is at the exit of,
give me a quick
second here.
So yeah, state three
is at the exit of
your condenser.
And just like we
said before, for
the rankin cycle
in a condenser,
right, the exit
state should
be a saturated liquid.
So we have an X three,
which is there,
and the pressure
is given, right?
So the pressure
was given in
the problem as 800 KPA,
S R 134 is a
pure substance,
it means that you
know H three, right?
We know H three out of it.
For state four, if we
go to state four now.
Okay, so for state four,
this is going across
the expansion valve.
So H four is
equal to H three.
All right. We'll pause
for a second on that.
We'll skip ahead now
to State State one.
So for state one, this
is at the exit of
the evaporator.
Again,
just like the condenser
at the evaporator,
you're going to
expect it to be as
a saturated vapor,
right, evaporation.
So that should
be equal to one.
And we're given the
temperature here.
So the temperature we were
told of the evaporator
is -20 Celsius, -20.
Celsius is then
evaporation,
and that could be
the temperature
right anywhere
along this, right?
This is essentially
a boiling process,
so you have constant
temperature and
constant pressure
through that device.
So here you have this
and you have that,
which means that you have
specific entropy and
specific enthalpy there.
And additionally, you also
have the pressure
at P one.
If you look back now from
state one to state
four of the
evaporator, right?
It's a heat exchaner,
a constant
pressure device.
What this means
is that P four
is equal to P one,
which we have there.
So we have states
three, four, and one.
Our remaining one
is then for state.
State two, we call
it state two S.
So for state two S,
in the isotropic case,
through the
compressor, little S
two is equal to
little S one.
I'm not going to write out
the whole entropy
analysis.
We've done this enough
times, but again,
it's an adiabatic
compressor
operating reversibly.
So, um, steady flow
of ice and no change
in entropy in there.
And because it's
reversible,
we don't have any
entropy generation.
A single inlet,
single outlet.
That's what you
end up with.
That's at state two S.
And the other piece
of information that
we would have is
that state two and
state three are connected
via a heat exchanger.
So then P two is
equal to P three,
which was given as
800 kPa, right?
And so from this, what
you'll have is you'll
have h2s from here.
Since this is the ideal
vapor compression cycle,
we're not given, you know,
we don't have
any indication
or we're not told
anything about
the efficiency of
our compressor.
And so what we
would infer then is
that the efficiency
is 100%, right?
So what that means
is that, this H two,
what this means for if
I have a compressor,
efficiency equal to 100%,
it means that H two actual
is equal to h2s, okay?
Or you can just call
it H two, right?
I'm being like, you
know, very detailed,
you know, with the
logic and how you might
see a problem in the
future. So it's ideal.
It means that
my isentropic
efficiency of the
compressor 100%.
So then the enthropy
at the exit of
that compressor is equal
to the isotropic one.
Okay.
Yeah, so at this point,
it's just plug and chug.
So to get to our COP,
so the COP There.
All right.
What we'd be
substituting in for,
right is our H H two A,
which is, of course,
H twoS and then the H one.
In this case,
what I have for
my COP is 3.83 as a
value with substitution.
And again, this falls
between what would
be expected.
So 3-5 is a good number.
There is work
that goes on now
that tries to bring
these things up to ten,
but they don't involve
vapor compression,
right?
So this is what you'd
have with this.
We also have is
there a question?
Yes, please. It's state
one? No.
It's a closed loop cycle.
So think like
Rankin, right?
In our Rankin systems,
we were operating
between what tens of
PA to tens of megapascals.
So we were going
all the way
between below
atmospheric pressure
to well above it.
It's the same thing here.
So don't have
an expectation
that the thing
has anything
to do with ambient.
Okay. I will note that
for something like
R 134 A in the
compression process,
you don't have to go to
crazy high pressures,
maybe like a couple of
times atmospheric
pressure,
there, but you have a
big pressure drop to
four to cause you to
boil and do that.
I don't know what the
pressure is here,
but I can't say that
it's atmospheric, okay?
And that's our 134 A.
If you do something
like carbon dioxide,
the pressure that
you have here can
be like 100 bar,
120 times
atmospheric pressure
for a system like that,
which then makes
them a little
more sometimes
difficult to
handle because
then you have
very large systems that
are at high pressure.
But there's no indication,
that this is
something like a
Brayton where the inlet
would be
atmospheric, okay?
It is interesting to
think about that, though,
to run a refrigeration
cycle on air.
Maybe a good final
exam problem, right?
It doesn't involve
property tables.
Seriously, I'm going
to think about that.
Okay. All right.
Other questions?
No.
Okay, so to get our
dot, what do we do?
We can look at the loads.
So we know the
Q dot L, right?
We're told information
about the Q dot L
there for the second part.
And so Q dot L
is equal to the
mass flow rate,
right into our evaporator
times Little QL.
What is little QL?
This is nothing but,
you know what I
wrote before.
This will be
one minus four.
We rearrange this. Our dot
is equal to Q dot L
divided by H one
minus H four.
So given it's 150 kilowatts
H one and H four,
we've determined from here
and here, H four
that we know.
And from this, you can see
for the mass flow rate,
what I have is about a
kilogram per second.
So 1.05
kilograms/second is
what I have. And
what's the power?
So the power now
to service this,
we can say is w
dot N is equal
to Q dot minus Q dot L.
Again, Q dot L is a
given given in
our problem.
Our Q dot H is then
going to be the dot,
which we just
determined, and
where's Q dot H,
that's going to be a minus
our three minus Q dot L.
Okay. And if
you substitute
the numbers in for that,
I have a power
requirement that is
approximately 39
kilowatts, right?
So our w.in here
is 39 kilowatts.
And again, just to
remind you that
39 is much less
than the 150,
and that's why
we bother with
teaching this and learning
about it and using it.
Okay?
Questions. Among the
simpler cycles, okay?
Good. That's how
it looks like.
So you can do some plots.
So the way Um,
so I show you here
a PV diagram.
Here's a pH in this field,
it's pretty common to
present these things on
pressure specific
enthalpy diagrams, right?
If we go three to four
through the
expansion valve,
you can see that
that process
is indeed isomthalpic.
Through that four
to one, right,
the enthalpy is increasing
because you're boiling or
you're boiling until
you a saturated vapor.
You compress it
isotropically,
and then you
condense, right?
You condense through here,
and then when
you're beneath the,
you know, during that, um,
the connotation is
happening inside of
a heat exchanger and
heat exchange isobaric,
you'd expect from
state two S here to
state three to be
constant pressure, okay?
So it's a pH.
And yes, if there
are no questions,
I will give you 5
minutes on this well,
4 minutes on this
lovely day, okay?
I'm up here if you
have questions.
Thank you, everyone.