Oh, it's loud.
Okay. Entropy today.
We're going to look
at entropy changes
for pure substances,
and we're going
to talk a bit
about really the
utility of this,
which is isotropic,
basically isentropic
processes there.
Um. I thought for a
second, of course,
you've all done your
pre work and reading,
and I know you're
all up to speed
and not concerned at
all about quiz one.
So the point is
entropy is a very,
like, weird thing, okay?
We don't measure
it. If anyone
tells you they really
know what it is,
you do not trust
that person.
That's like the first
rule of entropy.
Um, The way that I like to
think about it, and
this will become, like,
clearer when we get
into when we
get into, like,
power cycles is, you know,
you remember, like, here
we had the pressure,
you know, pressure volume.
You say, okay, I
want to be able
to, um, you know,
maybe, you know,
I got some state, you
know, that's here.
Let's say I can really
superheat, you know,
water vapor to, you know,
to this very high,
you know, superheat.
And then what, okay?
So basically, I can
take the boiler,
read it can really heat.
I can get you up
to this state.
And one of the
problems when
you're analyzing
turbines and
all these devices
to get power
out of it is
it's difficult
to think about wre to sort
of draw next, okay?
And entropy is
going to help us.
It's pretty much going
to help you to
be able to say,
Okay, I'm going to end up,
you know, maybe down here.
The way we're going
to represent this, though,
is not on what's
called the PV diagram,
but on TS diagrams.
Okay?
And again, you did
your reading and
all of that.
So what you'll
remember from
the Carne cycle is
that essentially
the TS diagram for
Karnea looks
like that, okay?
So I transfer heat
isothermally in.
I have a reversible
turbine, right there.
So isropic okay,
means like It's
constant entropy
from this state.
I take heat out here,
and then I transfer
work in reversibly
with a pump, okay?
So I've introduced a word
for you here, isentropic.
So this ability
that, you know,
we can have for
our work devices,
especially our
steady flow ones,
to move up and
down vertically
like that is
helpful, okay?
The other important
thing is the area
enclosed inside of here
is the net heat in,
which for a cycle,
what is that equal to?
Okay. Hand up, name.
It could be that. I'm
thinking like this,
but this is an
area, right?
So if I did an area
of a PV diagram,
let's say I gave you a PV
diagram that
looked like that.
What would be that
area? Work. Net work.
Okay? And what I'm telling
you here is that
this is net heat in.
So for a cycle,
in order for me to end up
at the same place
where I started,
what must the net heat
in be equal to? Name?
A.
Say it again. AV. Now,
work out. AV, right?
That's it.
Okay? We got the right
side of the room.
Point to them, okay?
Just kidding. You guys
all said good thing.
That's it. Okay? So again,
it's going to help you to
connect processes, right?
It's going to help
us, like, a compass,
guide us where we need
to go, one part of it.
And the second
part of it is it
may prove helpful when
we want to analyze
things like,
you know, the power output
of the device, okay?
Is that good before we
now really we into this?
Okay, so just remember
it's helping us.
It's helpful.
It's a friend,
not a foe. All right?
Okay. So, but first,
before we can use a
compass and walk,
we got to learn to crawl,
right? So here's crawling.
So I have two blocks.
Let's say here.
One hot, one cold.
Maybe I'll stay in view.
Sorry for those watching.
All right, I got
one hot block.
I have a cold
block, right?
So T one is greater
than T two.
And let's say that this
is a reservoir, okay?
So a reservoir means if I
transfer heat out
of it or into it,
the temperature does
not change, right?
This just means I have
a huge hunk of
metal, right,
that's hot and
maybe a huge one
that's cold, and they're
connected, right?
So I can transfer
heat in and out.
I'd like to draw a
control volume first
around the one
on the left.
And I would like to
draw another
control volume
around the one on
the right, okay?
Let me erase this.
All right,
let me actually read
the problem though,
because this is,
blah, blah, blah.
Two bodies are placing
contact to get some heat.
So what's the change in
the entropy of each body?
So each body here, right,
I'm going to talk about
the change in entropy
of this control volume.
I'm going to talk
about the change in
entropy of this
control volume.
I I'm going to
basically what
I'm going to show
you is that just like
internal energy,
I can sum them, right?
So if I take
entropy change
here plus the
entropy change here,
that's the
entropy change of
the combined
control volumes.
And from that,
I'm going to link
this to the concept
of reversibility,
which until now, I kind of
said, trust me on it.
Like, this looks
reversible.
With this, I'm
going to give you
a firm a firm formula,
right, to stand on.
You're able to say,
no, that is
reversible or no,
that is irreversible.
Okay, um Great.
So entropy.
So we can write that ds.
So the variable for
entropy is S, okay?
I'm going to write
the units of
capital S is equal
to what does
this equal to?
This is kilojoules
per Kelvin.
If I write it as maybe
I'll give it some
fancy things
to make it big.
If I write little S,
little S is equal to
kilojoules per kilogram
per kelvin, okay?
So that's the units
then of it, right?
So this is the intensive
property, like, you know,
we have the capital
U internal energy,
little U, specific
internal energy.
It's the same thing
here, entropy
and specific
entropy, right?
This is equal to, right?
This is equal to Delta
Q divided by T, okay?
So changes in entropy are
related to heat, right?
So if I bring heat in
or out of something,
I'm going to be
increasing or
decreasing the entropy
of that system, okay?
This is the first thing
you should remember, okay?
All right. That's the
first thing statement.
The second one, I
had said verbally,
but we can write it
out loud, right?
I can say that the
total change in
entropy of
the combined control
volumes is equal to
the change in
the entropy of
control volume
plus the change in
entropy of control
volume two, okay?
So let's focus first
on control volume one.
All right.
We can write our um
So when we look at
this as it's drawn,
I only have heat
leaving, right?
Basically heat
leaving the system.
So my cue out.
So again, this is for
say, CV one, okay?
My Q out of,
let's say, one is just
equal to the Q that I've
defined here, right?
So I'm saying
this Q is here,
and I don't have
any Q in, right?
So my Q in for
control volume one is
equal to zero, okay?
And we assume, right,
because we assume thermal
reservoir Because of that,
the temperature T one
is equal to a
constant, right?
If I take our formula
there, right?
I can then write
the integral of ds,
let's say from
state one to state
two is equal to
the integral of
dq divided by let's
say T one, okay.
And we can denote
I'd like to
denote that this
applies for CV one, right?
So this is applied to
CV one there, right?
Because this
is a constant,
you can take the
T one out, right?
So essentially what you're
going to be left with
just for completeness,
I'll write it out, right?
You know, the
integral then,
uh uh of dq,
which then is going to
basically Q divided
by T one there, right?
Hmm. Okay.
Um, I've noticed something
here that I would
like to correct.
So here, right?
I'm saying that this is,
I have a heap being
transferred of
a magnitude Q
from control volume one to
control volume two.
That's the magnitude.
What I wrote here
is that the Q
out of this is equal to Q.
Because this is
leaving, right?
Here, I'll have to, like,
say that this is
somehow I'll have
to give this basically
a sign, okay?
Um, Unlike what I was
doing before, right,
when I went with the
Q and the Q out here,
I have to say if the heat
is leaving this, right?
It's a negative. If
it's entering in,
it's then a
positive, okay?
So maybe for now, what
I'll write is Q out.
All right. And I'll
call that a CV one.
And then if I make
the substitution,
what this would then
be is the negative Q
divided by Q one, okay?
And that is Delta S.
Um, where's my thing?
I have Delta S one, okay?
So we got one
formula, right?
And what does
that mean before
I get to the
second one, right?
So if I'm taking heat
and I'm cooling, right?
Basically, I'm cooling
off control volume one.
I'm taking the heat out,
and I'm reducing
the entropy,
okay? That's important.
So if I'm taking
something and
I'm transferring
heat out of it,
in that part that's
being cooled there,
the entropy is
being reduced.
One. But we're still
transferring heat into
something else, right?
To analyze this,
we'll have
to do the next part.
All right.
Oops.
All right,
what's easiest here?
I'm looking at the board,
how much space I got.
Let's swap this.
Let's do it the other
way. Let's do
it like that.
Okay, so now we can
look at CV two.
So let's look at
control volume two.
CV two are Q
in of um of two is just
equal to Q, right?
So we're transferring
heat in that's
positive and into there,
and we have no Q out.
So our Q out
when it comes to
control volume two
is equal to zero.
Again, we're going to
treat we're going to
assume that the one
on the right that behaves
like a thermal reservoir.
And so what that
means is that T two
is equal to a
constant, right?
So that doesn't vary.
We'll do the same thing.
So if I apply this now
for CV two, All right.
They'll have this
integral from state
one to state two of ds,
and that's equal
to the integral of
dq divided by T two.
This T two can come out of
the integral because
it's a constant.
So I have one over T
two integral of Q.
And what this is
then going to be
is one over T two
times in for two,
which if we do
that substitution,
this is nothing but Q
divided by T two, okay?
So this is Delta
S two, right?
So there's a
second formula.
And all we're
going to do, okay,
so let's first reflect
on this before we
bring it together.
So here, right, I
have heat being
transferred in.
This is positive.
The temperature
is a constant.
This entropy will
increase, all right?
So this will
increase. And now
we're just going to
substitute here.
So I'll put it into
the right hand side.
So this is what?
This is nothing
but negative Q
divided by T one.
Plus Q divided by two.
I can sort this. I can
then just write Q times
1/2 minus one over
T one is Delta S.
Okay, so what do we do?
What is the
change in entropy
of each body?
There is this.
So body one decreases
by that amount.
By two increases
by this amount.
What is the change in
entropy of the system?
It is this, okay?
And is this process
reversible?
So for a process to be
reversible, what
do you think?
How would you describe
a reversible process?
For those who have
definitely done
reading, yes, please.
What was that last
part? The same entropy.
So I'm going to
build on that.
If the entropy does
not change during
the process,
okay, that is going
to be a reversible
process here,
for the purposes
of this analysis.
So if the entropy
doesn't change here,
it's going to
be reversible.
What do we think
about this?
Do we think that Delta S
is going to be zero or no?
Or what would it take
for Delta S to be zero?
What would you have to
have, Cody? T. Yeah.
T two equals to T
one implies
Delta S is zero.
What would that imply for
this system in
this experiment?
So if I had the
same temperatures,
what would happen here
or what wouldn't
happen here?
No heat transfer, right?
So when I have
that, there's
no heat transfer, okay?
If I'm going to
have heat transfer,
my entropy is going
to change, right?
So that's the first thing.
Now, the second
thing is that,
is this a positive
or is this a
negative value?
And?
Yes, please.
I like that. It sounds
like a smart
person said it.
Okay, good. Yes.
So this term here,
if T two is higher, right?
So this is the
higher temperature,
one over that is going to
be a lower number, right?
If I then, this is on
the colder side, sorry.
I'm sorry. I'm
sorry. I'm sorry.
Hold on.
He.
I got to write
hot and cold.
This is like my
problem. You get
up here and
mistakes happen.
I don't know how.
Maybe it's entropy.
Alright, so, right?
So this is basically
going to be
a smaller term T one
is going to be higher.
So your negative term
is going to be
smaller because
it's a higher temperature
than this one, okay?
So the take home
message is that Delta S
is either zero in
this problem when
nothing happens,
or it increases when
you actually allow
heat to flow, okay?
Delta S can be
negative, right?
For a specific control
volume, right?
Control volume one,
Delta S definitely
decreased.
But if I look at the
whole system and I
gather the sum of all
of the parts and
I add it up,
If it's equal to zero,
right, reversible,
which sure means
no heat transfer,
or it increases.
And be very,
very skeptical
in your analysis
if you end
up with Delta acids
in a process being
negative, right?
It means on their own
for that whole system,
it will not happen
spontaneously, okay?
Right? And that was, like,
a major achievement in
thermodynamics is
like the prediction
of things happening
spontaneously,
right? This can
tell you that.
It can either tell you
if it's BS or if it
won't happen
spontaneously, okay? Good?
It's not that hard, right?
Or it's very hard.
Okay. Um, Yes.
Alright, so
this is, again,
some fou for thought
and you'll get
some practice with this
and get to use it.
And at some
point you become
comfortable kind
of comfortable,
or you'll accept it.
So entropies are
entropy, you know,
again, just like, you
know, when we did
internal energy, it's
a property, okay?
So if you determine
the state,
if you know, you know,
the two independent
properties or
parameters of
a pure substance,
you have complete
information.
So just like I
could determine
internal energy,
enthalpy specific volume,
you can also determine
entropy, right?
What I'm showing you
here is not super
helpful if you're
doing like Pie Killer.
These are like little, you
know, tricks that
if you were,
you know, old
school and doing,
you know,
tables, you can see
things like this.
But in the book, when
you look it up, again,
just like with the
other ones, right?
If you're having
notations,
when it's like F, right,
that's like a liquid,
when it's a G,
right, then it's
rid of saturated,
you know, vapor
that are with it.
But the take home
message out of
this is that you
can you know,
with all the
other parameters
that you would determine,
you can also
determine entropy,
and you will
also, you know,
produce a lot of diagrams.
So you will
produce what are
called TS
temperature entropy.
Diagrams are
very important
when you're
analyzing, again,
power cycles, gas
cycles, there, okay?
And it's not a path
function, right?
So if you like,
come up with
a difference in
the entropy,
it's just a
difference, right?
You don't have to
worry. Like, you
have that, you have
the properties.
All the formulas
are very valid and
compute can compute
there, okay?
Cool. So I did one
kind of intro example.
I'm going to go
through another one
now to show you
a little bit on
that property
determination to
convince you that
that's possible.
Now, are there any
questions before
I dive into that?
Is this clear?
All right. Maybe
another way,
if you wanted to look at
this before I dive in,
is to reflect on the
fact that, right,
these change in entropy
are like the dc
by T, right?
So if you're
transferring heat
in from a reservoir that's
at very high
temperature, right?
Like, it kind of
tells you that it
has a quality to it.
All right? So
this is, again,
the second part of the
second law, which is,
you know, energy is
conserved as
the first law.
Energy has, like, a value
to it is the second law.
And so looking at a
formula like that is
one way to start
to think about it.
All right.
You all know that
there's like
a review session
today at four, right?
Dechry Hall? Yes, please.
So you? What Delta T.
The Delta T that
I just erased.
For the rate of entropy.
So I'm sorry, dq
over T, okay?
So this T, and this is
what we're going
to get into in
some of the
other examples.
When I take control
volume one is
the temperature of
this control volume
here, right?
So when I'm looking
at the change
in entropy, I'm
saying, okay,
how much heat, am I
transferring out of that,
and then what's that
temperature there?
And there will be cases
where things don't
behave as a reservoir.
Again, the last
problem we're going to
do today is going
to be illuminating
because you can
have cases where I
transfer heat
out of something
and the temperature
changes.
All right. And
that's going to have
an effect then
on this formula.
So you're going to
have to integrate.
You're going to
write Q essentially
as like MCP Delta T.
You're going to be able
to integrate that and
it's going to be
a natural log.
Now give it away.
You can go home
now. All right.
Cool. Other questions?
Good question.
I don't know if this red
is really an erasable.
That's pretty okay.
Do damn.
All right. So calculate
the entropy changes that
calculate the
entropy changes,
entropy change that takes
place during processes
for pure substances.
All right. So in
this problem, we're
shown here a TS diagram.
For water here, okay?
And what we're told
is in this problem,
we have a piston
cylinder device at
some initial pressure
and some initial
temperature,
that there's a mass of
water contained in there
and that we're going to
transfer heat
into it, right?
And based on how I look at
it and also how
it's drawn there,
this is an
isobaric process,
so constant pressure.
What's shown in the
diagram here is that
we're starting off because
it's a dome to the left,
let me ask you this
what state do you
think one is?
I told you what dQ
by T is when it comes
to changes in entropy.
So what would you
expect the phase
of something with
low entropy to be?
What did you say?
Art? Comps liquid.
Comssed liquid.
Yes, right?
Okay, so if I put a
lot of heat into it,
right, you're going
to end up with
something that will not.
So then it turns out
that at state two,
right, you'd pass through,
constant temperature.
You could infer
from that that,
that's a liquid vapor
region and then
into the superheated
vapor. Okay?
Yeah, so some facts
our P P one here.
So we're gonna
go with state.
This is a horrible marker.
I have more? State.
There we go.
That's better.
State one. Okay.
State one.
All right, so State one,
we have a P one,
which is equal to 100
and 140 kpa 140 pa,
and a one that's equal
to 20 degrees Celsius.
And we could double
check ourselves,
but based on how
that is, it appears
right in that
liquid region,
that's complete
information,
and you would know
about you'd
know everything
about that state, right?
You'd know U one. You
know, you'd know V one.
You'd also know S one.
Remember and
that's little S
that's kilojoules
per kilogram per
kelvin, right?
Cool. Do do do.
And if you did, what I
can tell you is that
the S one is equal to
0.296 kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin.
If you want it
just for fun,
we could also write
the enthalpy,
which is 84 kilojoules
per kilogram.
Great. All right,
can draw our piston
cylinder device,
start to do some
analysis of this,
some energy flow, and then
try to figure
out state two.
A, so I have this
piston cylinder.
I'm putting Q in.
Here's my control volume.
All right. Oh, and how
I got this, right?
This is Pi killer.
So if you click
on that link,
you can go through
and see how
that property
determination is done.
Alright, so we have this.
So I can say,
right, so the
mass is constant.
So we have the mass
that's inside of here,
which is equal to 1.5
kilograms, right?
So no mass in or out.
Um, The change in
the energy of the
control volume here,
it is equal to E
in minus R E out.
The way that energy
can change in
that, right,
internal energy,
kinetic energy plus
potential energy
is an equal
to Q in plus W in
Q out plus W out.
What do we
assume we assume
neglect KE and PE, right?
And we don't have
any work in,
and we don't have
any heat out, right?
So what this
implies, right,
is that Delta U
is equal to what?
Q in, which we
know minus W out.
What's W out here,
right? PDB, yes, right?
So this is the integral
of pressure volume.
It's constant
pressure, right?
So this would come out,
right, the integral of
dv from state one to two,
and this would
then just be
equal to P times V
two minus V
one. All right.
This is V. We could also
write this as
little V, right?
I could go mass, pressure,
little V two minus
little V one,
right, is equal
to the W out.
All right. So we can
rewrite that, right?
I can write and
I can rewrite
the two minus little
U one, right?
So that's the change
in the internal
energy is equal to my Q
in minus pressure
times the mass,
specific volume two
minus specific volume one.
All right. You can move
this all to this side,
right? So I can go.
U two plus PV
two minus U one
plus PV one,
and that's equal
to A. All right.
What is this? At state
two. What is this?
That's state one,
will be at state one.
And so then M times H
two minus H one
is equal to Qn.
Now we know Q
we know H one
because I told you so,
and we know the mass.
We don't know
H two, though.
So the purpose
of this exercise
is actually to
determine H two and
H two is equal to QN
divided by the mass.
Plus H one, okay?
And that makes sense,
right, because you'd
expect also if
a matting keyed
into something
that the enthalpy
at the second state would
be greater than
the first, right?
So that tracks, right?
And so if you do that and
you do the substitution,
what you're going to
see is that this H
two is equal to
2,510.7 kilojoules
per kilogram, right?
So now for state two,
What do we know about
the property at state two?
So we know H two,
H two we've got.
What else do we know
about state two?
Pressure Pressure, right?
So P two is there.
H two with P two is enough
to determine S two, right?
So if I have these
two properties,
it's enough to
determine entropy,
specific volume, so on
and so forth, right?
We need to determine
temperature.
So the T two from
this is equal to
300,382.4
degrees, degrees C?
Is this right? Yeah,
it feels right.
Yes. Okay. So that's
that. And then
the entropy.
So the S two is equal to
6.78 kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin, right?
And how do we determine
change in entropy?
So what do we know about
the entropy at state one?
State two. All right.
M, it's S two minus S one.
So our mass is
1.5 kilograms.
RS two was 6.78
kilojoules per
kilogram Kelvin
-0.296 kilojoules
per kilogram Kelvin.
And so I'd expect
something,
what, close to like nine,
ten, nine, 9.7 right?
Kilojoules per kelvin is
the change in entropy
of that process, okay?
So this is another way,
especially when
we do cycles,
that you're going
to be calculating
changes in entropy, right?
So the first one I
showed you before,
is I take something and
I transfer heat
into it, okay?
Or I let something
maybe get cooled.
I calculate the entropy
of the thing that's
being cooled,
being heated.
I sum them up and I
get a total Delta S,
right? That's
one approach.
Right?
You'll classify that in
problems when you
get with this.
The second way
that you'll see,
and this is especially
pertinent when
we think about
cycles is you're
just going
to look for
properties, right?
State one, state
two. I know that.
And the change in
entropy is going
to be nothing
but the M times
that Delta S or
the dot times that
Delta S, okay?
All right. And
if it's zero
for a process like
that, it's isentropic.
If that's like a work
transfer process,
that means that it's
basically reversible,
all right? Okay.
Any questions about
that? All right.
Maybe just to illustrate
what that looks
like in the
actual notebook.
Oop, let's skip
verification.
Live dangerously.
All right.
Authorize do do do.
All right. So all
that you see, right?
So I can define a
state here like that.
Water underscore one
dot S. That's it.
So we bothered with
this whole
business of, like,
two independent variables
determining properties,
all the other properties
for this reason.
We made all of
that effort,
especially on
the programming side
because it's going
to be like bordering
on trivial to,
like, compute these
things, right?
No interpolation,
no, like,
when I was your age,
it was suffering.
I mean, like, you know,
it was like, to do this.
This is so straightforward
and allows you to,
like, think about
more than that.
Like, you can look at
more difficult things
and do it, right?
So this hopefully
helps you
to appreciate that, right?
Just dots and you
have it, okay?
Good. Sweet. All right.
Good. So your turn.
So take this 5
minutes, a neighbor.
Let's see how much of
this you absorbed if
your entropy was zero
or if it increased.
All right?
And if you don't,
then we'll talk
through it, alright?
I'll circulate if
you have questions.