So we're going
to continue with
exergy today and
the application
of it, alright?
So, our learning
objectives,
so we're going to develop
an exerge control
volume analysis,
and we're going
to apply it
to a chip cooling.
So it's called liquid
cooling on a chips is
a modern form of how
we cool CPUs and GPUs.
We'll do one on
the turbine,
and then I'll do
one on the heat
exchange of the
power plant.
I'll wait until
I get excited,
and we'll wait
actually until
the next couple
of chapters
when we get into
power cycles,
and then you'll be
able to do that.
In terms of the quiz,
everything will
be uploaded at
the latest
tomorrow morning.
Hopefully tonight
we went through
an overall I think
I'm pretty satisfied.
All right, so
recycling waste heat.
So you may or may not
know you do know if you
read any amount of news
with data centers,
or demand for compute.
We have a huge amount
of pressure, you know,
put on the
electricity grid in
terms of running
computers.
Right? So you
take electricity,
which is the highest
form of energy, right?
So the highest form of
exergy is anything
I can do work,
right? They're
equivalent, right?
A W in would
also be an in,
right, when it
comes to that.
So electricity is because
it can be transferred
in as work,
right, that's the
highest form of energy.
You run it in, you
compute something,
all right?
And I represent
this as a poster,
because that's
all it is, right?
Essentially, you do
that, you compute,
but everything
that goes in to
compute becomes
heat, right?
It's transferred
basically as heat.
The way we used to cool
this is a lot
of air, right?
A lot of fans would like,
move air and blow it over.
Um, And then, you know,
in recent years and stuff,
people have, you know,
recent decades and stuff,
people have looked in
and figured out that,
hey, not only with air,
but this could also be
done with liquid, right?
And that really, so the
balance and people
would look at that is,
right, I have some
energy in to compute.
And from a first
law analysis,
if I don't want this
thing to melt down,
I'm going to take
all that heat off.
So people would look at
this, and in general,
when they analyze
these systems,
they think about
the first law
of thermodynamics,
like that.
I put this in and
it's heat and
I take it off.
Can, however, take a
second law approach.
You can use exergy, and
that's the purpose of
this example
is not to just
take a first law
analysis of this,
but a second law and
see if there are
opportunities to use
this, all right?
This isn't just fiction.
So this was done. So
my former building,
when I was at It Ha was
partially heated by
this thing called aquasar.
You can read it on
Wiki. But essentially,
what you would do here is
you'd have these
cold plates.
So this is like a blade,
a server blade that
you would take in and out.
You'd bring in
water, All right.
And he would be
transferred from
the hotter chips into
the water and then taken
and basically taken
back out, okay?
So that's nothing
terribly innovative.
That's what you would
do, you know, if
you were like,
Hey, that's hot.
Let's bring like
liquid to it.
But what was interesting
about this is
that they didn't run
the chips at room
temperature, okay?
So the point of
this device is
that they actually let
the chips run hot.
And so then you
transfer heat
into a fluid
that's warm, okay?
All right. So hold that
thought for a second.
And the nice part about
it is if you do that,
you'll take hot water that
makes it even
slightly hotter,
and then you can use
that, that water
that has utility
to it, okay?
Higher org, all right?
Okay. And you can do
carbon neutral compute.
So all these
challenges of, like,
water cooling and
all of that, fine.
But if you did this,
you wouldn't
have you know,
you'd solve a
lot of problems
if you thought, like,
with the second law.
Alright, so what
does this look like?
So if I was going
to represent again,
kind of a
simplified version
for the purposes
of this analysis.
So here's our toaster
here, so the
computer chip.
That's mounted to what's
called the cold plate.
So this copper
thing that you
see here is called
the cold plate.
I'm bringing a fluid in.
This is water,
in this case.
And then I have
the fluid that's
basically exiting here.
The inlet, let's call it.
I think I'm going
to call it state
one. Let me just clarify.
No idea. Okay, we're
going to call it one.
We're going to call
it two for this.
And we'll leave it up
like that for now,
but we can think
about a couple of
different control
volumes when we
actually to do
the analysis.
So what we'd like
to do, so again,
we're given what we'd
like to determine.
We'd like to determine
The following things.
the second law efficiency.
So what I'm going
to call is Eta
underscore Roman
numeral two.
We want to determine
the Xergy terms.
All right.
And the other
thing we want to
determine is to calculate
the second law
efficiency as
a function of
T one, right?
So as a function
of the inlet
temperature of the water.
So those are the three
things that we're
going to determine, okay?
Okay.
And I'll go through
some of the
things that are
given as it naturally
comes up here,
but, like,
there's obviously
for this analysis,
I'm not showing
you a pump.
So I'm just analyzing
this as a device.
I could, of course,
do a wider one
that looks at the
different components.
I'm going to make
some assumptions
about those and
put them in.
Okay? Again, our substance
here is water. Okay.
Mm hmm. What are
our assumptions we
can look at maybe we'll
draw can draw in green.
This is maybe
our control this
is like our control
volume here.
Like that. That's
our CV. All right.
Okay. All right,
so we have an assumption
of a control volume,
we've mass that crosses
the boundaries.
Properties, we're going
to determined with
Pi kilo because this
is going to involve water.
I'm not going to use, I'm
not going to use that
as an alternative
because I'm not
boiling water here.
A CP Delta T
might be a sensible
approach, right,
for computing the
let's say the work
that's transferred then
is heat into there.
It's a steady flow
process, okay?
So the mass flow
rate in is equal to
the mass that's
out, right?
The work, right,
that I'm transferring
electrically
here is then going to be
balanced then with heat
that's generated
and carried out.
With no shaft
work. And because
this is an
isobaric device,
the pressure, there is
no pressure drop
across 1-2.
Right? So let's start
off with our first one.
So the first thing is
that the definition of
what we call as the
second law efficiency is,
again, the ratio of
things that we
have to spend,
right, to things
that we like, right?
And in exergy analysis,
this is what we
call as Xergy Xergy
expended All right.
And that's in
the denominator,
and then in the
numerator, it's
orgy recovered.
And I'll get into a
second what we mean
by expended and recovered,
but it's not so different
from what we did
before when we were
talking about
efficiencies, right?
That would be like maybe
Q in and W net out.
A Xergy that could
be, you know,
recovered in a
lot of systems
maybe like a workout
term, right?
Here, we'll get
into the meaning
of what XRgy
recovered is, though.
Okay, before I
get into that,
we can look at
just a simple
example of a
heater, though.
So if I just go in
without as an aside,
so if I look at a simple,
I can do a simple
heater, right?
And so what a
simple heater
might look like is, again,
I have this maybe
a resistor,
you know, here, okay?
And so maybe this
is my you know,
control volume.
So I transfer
some work in.
So there's basically
a W electrical in,
and then I'll have a write
a Q out associated
with that.
So right, I'll
have a W in,
which is the
electrical, and then,
you know, a Q out of that.
So the second
law efficiency
of this simplified case,
so we can call this
heater or maybe toaster
and call it
toaster is, again,
we can deal with you,
we'll deal with
rate terms,
so the rate that we
transfer energy
in and the rate
that we transfer heat out.
So there's your udt
recovered, right?
There's your X dot
expended. All right.
So what do you
think that we're
expending here?
So in our toast or
our heater example,
what am I putting
in? Work, right?
So, and work is
the same, right?
So work is the highest
form of energy.
And what it means is
that it's also exergy.
So these are
interchangeable. All right?
So here I'll have a W dot.
I call it w.in. So
here's my w.in.
And then what I'm
recovering here out of it,
so what comes out
of this system
then is this heat, okay?
So I'll go X dot,
Heat. All right.
Surrounding this
heater, I have to
define some dead
state conditions.
So T zero is the dead
state temperature,
which we usually would
take as, like, maybe,
I don't know
what 25 Celsius
and a dead state pressure,
which is, you know,
1 atmosphere.
How do we define
the rgy of heat?
Does anyone
remember? How do
we state the
quality of heat.
So what is the
formula that tells
us the maximum work
I can get out for
a unit of heat in?
What is the most
efficient engine?
Karno.
Okay? So when you think
about this with heat,
you think Carn, right?
So the X dot heat,
in this case, then,
is going to be
this q.aq dot
out here times
essentially something
that resembles a
cardo efficiency,
one minus the dead
state temperature
divided by H, okay?
All right? Now,
I don't know.
And so that would
be the numerator,
and then our denominator
then would be
dot would be w dot, right?
Okay.
Yes. And so from
a first law point
of view, right?
So if I have a steady
flow system here,
so I have a steady
flow device,
what is coming
in is equal to
what is coming out there?
What do you
suspect you could
say about q dot out and
w.in? It should be
the same, right?
And so what you'll
see in this
kind of simplify it again,
toaster example is that
this is going to be one
minus the dead
state temperature
T zero divided
by the H. Now,
H in here is not defined,
TH would be something
you'd have to take e109
and figure out then heat
transfer to figure
out what it would be.
But what does this say?
What from this formula?
If I look at
the second law
efficiency for
this formula,
what's like a take
home message?
The more In name?
Zach. Zach. So Zach
said something
very astute,
which is that if
I run my toaster at a
higher temperature,
and let's say I blow
air over, you know,
or if I'm able to
heat up, you know,
air here if air
coming in here is
coming in at basically
a higher temperature,
then this is
going to behave
more efficiently, okay?
So the warmer is the
air that I bring in,
and then I transfer
heat into it,
the more efficient
is going to be
this process of electrical
work in heat out.
And this is done all
the time, right?
So you think
about every oven.
You know,
electrical oven
basically operates on
this, you know, on
this principle.
Of course, those
less eicient because
you're bringing
in cold air
and you're
heating them up.
So you're pretty much
killing all your excergy,
but you do get
nice cooked food.
But if you want this
to be more efficient,
then you should heat up
air that's already kind
of kind of warmer,
all right?
So that's an aside,
but that kind of
tells you where
we're headed.
So that's the
simple heater,
simple toaster example.
So for the case of
electronics cooling,
I want to make sure.
Yeah, I'm still
recording pretty well.
For the case of
electronics cooling,
it's the same formula.
So we have this.
Again, it's the ratio
of X dot recovered.
Divided by X dot expended.
All right. All right.
All right. So reflecting
on our example
with our toaster,
what is one type of exergy
or what do you think is
the exergy that we're
recovering here?
Zach?
Yeah, so you're going to
have there is your X dot,
we're going to
call it here is
X dot outlet, okay?
And so what is the outlet?
Right? Right? So
this is what's
leaving the system
here is at state two.
Hopefully, that's
visible. It is.
And so this is
the energy that
we're gonna recover.
This fluid stream that's
like leaving
here is going to
actually be the exergy
that we recover, right?
So X dot outlet, right?
Okay, what are
we expending?
So what forms of exergy
or what energy
terms do you think
that what are things
that we're spending here?
What are things
that are going
into the control volume?
At this side of the room.
David, first, since that's
what I saw, but it's
not fair, Kate.
It's actually
not a question.
Q times one minus over
T. You also mentioned
that xgy is equal to ST,
Exergy is equal to
STT. I don't
remember that.
Maybe I can hallucinate
a large language model.
I don't think I said
it though. I will
tell you this Xergy.
What is the
point of Xergy?
Exergy is like I
have some state.
What is the maximum
work I can get
out from this state
going to the dead state.
That's anything that's
reversible um, you know,
done in a reversible
way, you know,
there is going
to be work is
basically ergy
interchangeable, right?
Reversible work is exergy.
Heat, when talking about
sergy is heat, all right?
Work in heat from
the first law
are equivalent.
But from the
second law, we
know they're not, okay?
Um, and so the way that we
correct for that
is we use that
Q dot multiplied by
something that resembles,
in my opinion, kind of
a Karno efficiency
because kno efficiency,
right is network out
divided by heat in.
Okay? And so if I
had this efficiency,
I can simply say,
Well, you know,
I can convert kind of
that maximum workout
to the heat one, you know,
through something
that resembles kind
of an ET one minus T,
the cold temperature,
which is
the dead
temperature rather
of the hot
temperature, right?
A third thing is
that worked energy
heat energy.
We know that fluids can
also possess energy.
They also possess energy.
And all we do is we
take flow energy
and we minus all of our
terms by the dead state.
So H minus H naught
minus T naught
times minus naught.
So maybe this s term
that you're saying
is in that,
but it's a longer
form, okay?
Yes, please.
Presley, right?
Okay. Generated.
Okay, that's a fair
formula, right?
So the dead state here,
X dot destroyed
destroyed is
equal to g times
T naught, right?
So when we did
entropy generation,
if we multiply
entropy generation of
a device or a system
times the dead
state temperature,
we'll get the trag
destroyed, okay?
And that's useful because
then I'm not going to
use that right now,
but you could
use that if you
knew how much your
original was.
But that's the
relationship maybe
that David's mentioning.
David, that's
the TS thing.
Oh. Okay. All right.
Now, I don't
remember. Kai? Okay.
All right, so the point
is that we have an outlet.
Now what I'm asking is for
this system,
what are inlets?
What are things that
we're spending?
Yes, please.
Electrical work.
Electrical work, right?
So you could have
here an X dot, right?
I'll do X dot E, right?
Electrical. What
else? Not Kai,
not David, not Zach.
Not Presley.
You.
Say it again.
Mass flow, right?
You could have a, right?
So we can have
an exudt, right?
We had the mass flow of
the outlet, right
here, you know,
but we can have the ex dot
of the inlet, all right?
What's something I
haven't drawn here,
but you think you
might need to
pass a fluid through
that cold plate?
What causes a
fluid to move?
Yes, please.
What? Pressure.
And what creates
pressure besides me?
A pump, right?
You can have
an dot of, you know, okay.
All right, right?
So this is it.
So what am I what
am I recovering?
I'm recovering
hot water, okay?
So that's the excergy
of my outlet. All right?
What I'm calling here,
maybe just to be clear,
I'll call this as outlet.
All right. And
here, I'll call
this as inlet there.
Yeah, right? So
we have here,
outlet, and here
we have inlet.
And I'll compute
properties
at that outlet
as state two,
and that inlet as
the state one.
I haven't drawn a pump,
but let's say to
define the second law,
probably it makes
sense to consider
the pump moving
an incompressible
dense fluid,
so it's not going to
be a huge penalty.
And then this problem,
I'm just going to give you
a value that is there,
and you ultimately
want to maximize.
You want to maximize this.
Okay, so Let's
deal right now.
So with the
electrical sergy,
that's going to
be pretty clear.
So we're told that there's
100 watts of
electrical power
is used for the chip.
The chip. All right.
And what that
means is that
X dot X dot electrical
is equal to 100
watts, right?
Electricity is
ergy, right?
It's the highest form
of work that we can have.
So that we've dealt with.
Um, We can deal
with the pump now.
So for the pump,
we're told that
the power of the P dot,
so let's call that
as the power of
the pump is equal to
the pressure drop
times the volumetric
flow rate.
They say that this
volumetric flow rate
is one liter per minute,
which is kind of intense
if you think about
how small it is.
And from this analysis,
what we're told is
that it consumes that
this P dot is equal to
0.24 excuse me, 0.24.
Wow, I'm really okay.
0.24 watts. Allright?
Okay. And then this will
deal with our
pump term, right?
So basically,
our X dot pump
is going to be the
electrical work
that we transfer
in to do the pump,
so our P dot, which
is going to be
equal to 0.24 watts.
All right, that's fine.
Mm hm hm.
All right, so
we've dealt with?
So we've dealt with
the electrical term,
we've dealt with
the pump term,
and now we need to deal
with the flow term.
So our flow term,
does it make sense?
What does it make
sense to do?
This is kind of a monster,
so maybe I'll slide
that over like that.
So the general formula
for flow exergy, right?
So flow is equal
to the mass flow rate
of the fluid, right?
So let's say it's a
steady flow device.
So we're talking about
an outlet or
an inlet here.
M dot enthalpy of
the fluid minus
the dead state enthropy
so the enthalpy
at T zero and P
zero minus the dead
state temperature
T naught,
entropy of the fluid,
specific entropy
of the fluid minus
the specific dead
state entropy.
All right.
How do we analyze
this in practice?
The dead state temperature
should be given
in the problem.
You should know P
zero and T zero.
With that,
you're going to be
able to determine,
T zero, you'll then know,
and then the enthalpy
and the entropy
you'll get,
you know, PCLor that.
And for the specific
entropy and
entropy of the fluid,
it's the same as before.
You need to know
the state, right?
Just like we
practiced before,
you'll be able to
get the enthalpy and
the entropy by
knowing the state.
And the MDOT, again,
that would be something
that's probably
a given or determined.
Mm hmm.
Yeah. So let's
look at this.
So again, we could write
this as X dot inlet,
right, which is going
to be the dot, again,
a steady flow
device, right?
H one minus H
naught minus T
naught one minus
naught X dot outlet
is going to be equal to m
dot times H two minus H
naught minus T naught
two minus naught,
all right?
Okay. So let's
focus on state
one for a second.
So if we look at
state one here,
so we're told
in the analysis
that T one is
essentially going to be
an independent
variable for us, okay?
Or let me take a
so let me pause
for a second.
With this, we have
enough information
to define
our second law
efficiency. All right.
So we have our inlet,
we have our outlet,
which is here,
inlet and outlet.
Okay. And so what
it means is that
our second law
efficiency is now done.
The specific exergy terms,
we've done
electrical Exergy.
We've done pump exergy,
we've done inlet, and
we've done outlet exergy.
So we've basically defined
those terms. That's it.
And now what we're
going to do is
we're going to
vary the inlet
temperature, all right,
and we're going
to see how that
affects the
efficiency here
that we determine.
The second law efficiency,
how much much what's
the quality of
the heat that we
recover from this process?
So to do this, we'll
essentially say that
we know a T one,
four that we have to
define a pressure, okay?
And so what we'll do is
we'll define some P one.
And again, this P one
for the purposes of
a pump because water
is incompressible,
it doesn't really
matter that much.
But for properties,
you could say maybe 1 bar,
two bar of pressure
at some temperature that's
below that boiling point,
and that's going to
be valid, right?
You don't want to pick
temperatures at above
that boiling point because
then it gets well,
For the purposes
of this analysis,
we'd like to avoid we'd
like to avoid that,
but some chip cooling
is done with boiling.
But then this
temperature and
pressure are not
sufficient information,
right?
I have to define
qualities and
things like that,
if I'm going to get
into a two phase.
All right, so this
is state one.
And so from this again,
so from this, right,
we're able to know
S one and an H one.
Okay, slide this
over. Mm hmm.
Okay.
But now we need to
determine state
two, right?
So for state two, right?
We know, again, that P
two is equal to P one.
And again, because
we would like
to keep this
only for what we
call single
phase cooling as
a liquid cooling, right?
If we knew T two,
that would be
enough information.
But we currently
don't know T two.
What's one way you
think that you could
determine T two
in this problem?
The heat transfer.
That's right,
right? So we can
do an energy analysis.
We can take a
step back and do
our simple energy analysis
there in balance.
The rate of work
being transferred
in with essentially that
energy that's gone in,
right, increasing
the temperature
of the fluid at
the outlet, okay?
All right. So
let's do that.
So again, we can write,
um No, maybe I'll
zoom back out.
All right.
So we can apply a
steady flow analysis
to this combined to
this combined
control volume.
And so what that will look
like is under
steady conditions,
I have aw.in plus
aq.in plus an
m.h1 plus W one
squared divided by
two plus gz one.
Is equal to w dot
out plus Q dot out
plus m.h2 plus w
squared divided by
two plus g two,
and it will neglect,
as we said before
at the start of
the problem,
we're going to
neglect changes
in potential and
kinetic energy.
We do have aw.in,
but we don't have a Q dot
into that control volume.
We don't have a w dot out,
but we do have a Q dot,
and we don't have a
Q dot out, right,
because this is, right,
an adiabatic control
volume, right?
There's no heat
in or out of
what I've drawn in green.
So there's also
then no Q dot
out of that, right?
All of that energy
that I'm going to be
putting in should
then equal.
So w.in should equal
to m.h2 minus H one.
And that makes
sense. No, I
would expect the fluid
exiting the thing
that I'm heating to
have higher enthalpy
than the inlet, right?
So the electrical,
you know,
power that I put
in should be
the mass flow rate
of the fluid,
M dot times the
difference of
the enthalpy H two
minus H one, all right?
Now, this is a fluid,
and it's going to
stay as a fluid.
So one approximation,
you could make here is
an M dot cp T two
minus T one, right?
And so the way that we can
determine T two, right?
We could do it
the other way.
I could go in and I
can do property
tables with this.
I could solve for
what is this?
This is an H
two is equal to
w.in divided by m dot
plus H one, right?
So you can determine
enthalpy at state
two from this because
I'll have H two, and
then I'd have P two.
So with H two, P
two and P color,
then you could determine
then S two, right?
So, or H two, right?
And from this, you
can then get S two.
The other way to do
this is the following.
I could then go and say
that T two is equal
to W dot N divided
by m dot cp,
and then that's plus one.
That's the other way
to do that. Mmm.
Okay. Yeah, so with
either of these
approaches,
then I know right,
I'll know basically my
state my state two,
and I'll get the
specific entropy,
which my slide.
Um, right?
So here, right, X
dot electrical lin,
I know, that's fixed.
X dot pump is a fixed
X dot inlet, right?
We were able to
determine because
I knew state one, right?
So I could get
one and S one,
S zero, T zero,
and H zero,
I knew from the dead
state properties,
which is the same way,
maybe just for
completeness,
state zero,
right is basically
T zero and P zero.
And from that, I know,
H naught and naught.
By knowing state
one, I know H
one and I know S one.
So this is good.
By using the
energy analysis,
steady flow
energy analysis
of a control volume.
I can determine H two
by determining H two
and knowing that P
two is equal to P
one because it's
a heat exchanger.
I know S two.
So I come here, H
two, I know H naught,
I know T naught,
I now know
S two, and I
know S naught?
And now I have X
dot outlet, right?
Other way to go
is to do this,
determine T two, but
it's the same thing.
With T two and then
the pressure P two,
you'll also know as two.
Yes, please. I
why do we have to
include the dot if
it's not like quality?
Because I have
smart students,
and if I didn't
put it here,
your very next
question would be,
but isn't there a
pump profit and
doesn't it cost energy,
and it shouldn't be there?
Isn't that account
from the stock?
No. No.
So, again,
this is maybe you
could get rid of it.
So maybe now if
we wanted to,
you could definitely get
rid of it and stick to
the control
volume that I've
drawn here to be
strictly correct,
for that control
volume, right,
there is no X dot pump,
and it's a very tiny
value, all right?
But yeah, you could go in
and look at it, but fine.
For the purposes of
this, maybe we can drop
that and keep it
simple for the
control volume.
I have an X dot outlet,
an an electricity input,
and then a fluid input.
I think what
you're saying is
that if I
transferred the work
in so if I drew the
control volume, um,
larger there
around the device,
and I took up the
entire device,
there would be no there
would basically be
no inlet, right?
And then I would
argue that there is
no outlet then
at that point,
which then makes
this kind of and
that's fine. We can
go to the next stage.
And what you would
have is there's
another heat exchanger and
a reservoir, and we
transfer from that.
So I think your
thinking is right,
but I guess, trust
me, all right?
This makes sense. But
to be strictly correct,
like this is for what I've
drawn, I have an right?
I'm recovering
hot water out.
I am putting
electricity in,
and I am putting
hot water in.
So this is valid. So
let's stick with that.
So now, you know,
okay, fine.
Go on. It's a small
number anyways.
It doesn't
matter, you know,
again, you're pumping
like a liquid.
There's not big changes
in enthalpy if
you're pumping,
like a dense fluid,
okay? But heat, right?
I put a lot of heat
in and out, like,
that's going to produce
a big change in enthalpy.
Alright. But the point
is that you have this,
and what you can do is
you can plot
this, all right?
And maybe oops.
So if you go in and you
plot this,
All right.
And you look. So this
is the inlet temperature.
So if I have an
inlet, you know,
temperature that's
basically getting
close to the dead
state temperature,
I'm not going to recover
anything, right?
Because if I end up with
an outlet where H
two is equal to
80, zero, zero, gone.
Okay? So if you dump
this heat into air
at room temperature,
you will recover
no exergy.
Your second law efficiency
is going to be zero.
But this is how they
design data centers for,
like, all of time.
Seriously. You start to
increase the
temperature of
the fluid brought in
to cool the chip.
The consequence of that is
to have heat transferred
from the chip
to the fluid,
that means the chip has to
be run hotter, okay?
Electro engineers
don't like that,
if there's any
in the room.
I'm speaking for you now.
But the warmer that you
get it, the better
that it is.
And what's
interesting is once
you get beyond,
let's say, you know,
50, 60 Celsius,
you end up with
a second law efficiency
that's not
terrible, right?
It justifies
looking at it.
And the reason is that at
this temperature as well,
water that warm becomes
economically valuable.
Right? Like, you can
put $1 value to,
like, heat, you know,
brought in, right?
If I have a
reservoir, let's say,
a water heater, okay?
You can say pretty
well, like,
what that could be used
or building heating.
You go to our colleagues
in architecture.
The students there,
they can put
a number to that, right?
And that can force
you to think
about a design.
So in San Jose, they
look at, you know,
locating data
centers next to,
like, residences
for, like,
this reason is
because you take
a second law approach
and you look at this,
and actually it's not
totally doom and
gloom, right?
You could end up
doing compute.
It was already heat you're
going to use, all right?
And you think
about this more
intelligently and how you
design it and it
becomes useful, okay?
So that's second
law of thinking.
Most time first law,
electricity, again,
I got to take heat
out, but actually
it's an opportunity
if you know energy.
And that's why you
should know energy,
because it's modern
analysis, all right?
Cool. This is thermal
if you want to be here.
All right. I made a face.
I said exergy. It
makes them go.
All right.
Are there any
questions about that?
Yes, please.
I can't hear you
say it again.
Sure. That's what I'm
asking. That's a
great question.
So, where's the dead
state? Now, this is
a little bit like what
is dead, all right?
So go to Alright, no.
Alright. So I hold
back my dead
stories, all right?
So the point is that
what people do,
what they look
at, is they say,
All right, here's
my device.
Can I, like, quantify
my surroundings?
So, like, I have
this thing.
What's my
environment? Right?
Here I'm in this room.
My environment could be
the air in this room,
or it could be the air
outside, all right?
And most people would say,
It's the air
outside, right?
The conditions that are
basically, you
know, outside,
and, you know,
what we call
the environment,
you would call is
the dead state.
For the purposes
of this class,
we say T zero and P zero
are like 25 Celsius and
1 atmosphere or 20
degrees Celsius
and 1 atmosphere
is when in doubt,
like, that's
your dead state,
right? Does that
make sense?
Yes. I'm qualifying
it because, you know,
some people have
different like,
not all devices may
encounter the dead
state in operation.
And so this is
actually an area where
people still research
and figure out is really
the dead state for
this device operation
actually the outdoor
conditions or not,
alright?
So if you put
this into a very
hot if you put this
into a very hot room,
I mean, the utility
of this really doesn't
care about what the
room is, right?
It's where can
this be pumped
to then heat
something else.
If you wanted to live
next to you know,
the servers, all right?
That's within your
rights, right?
You could live next
to the toaster
and, like, stay warm.
But I can tell you, if you
ever go into one
of these things,
they are so loud, so loud.
Like, you need
hearing protection.
Just to walk into
a machine room,
it is in a word
unpleasant, Allright?
No one is in there with
these they're loud, right?
There's lots of things
happening, okay?
Yeah, but this Class T,
P zero is 25 C
in 1 atmosphere.
And if you want to
discuss with me more,
I'm happy to in
office hours.
Come to office hours.
Other questions
about this.
So I know it's weird.
I know this is,
like, weird to
write it in this way,
and it may take time.
Maybe none of you
will realize it in
this semester, you know,
but it is a way that
we can start to
analyze more complicated
systems, all right?
Hybrid systems,
thermal electricity and
ultimately optimize.
And that's where
all of it's going.
Everything in energy
is hybridization,
and you need approach
that can really do apples
to apples of
something that is
not apples to
apples, right?
And he didn't work
or not, alright?
Great. Thank you for that.
Okay. Um, do, do do to do.
I feel like the
Kansas City Chiefs,
I just burned off
like 40 minutes
in one drive
here, alright?
Good. Did do.
I lost my cursor.
Here we go.
This All right.
So what I'm going
to go through now,
I think probably
the one that's most
useful to see here is
the second law
efficiency of a turbine.
And when I
analyze this one,
think about isentropic
efficiency I
defined before.
So, you think
about isentropic
efficiency I
defined before,
that is the real
work out of
your system divided by
the reversible work,
right, when this behaved
isotropic. All right?
Now, think about
that while I race.
And I might have
mentioned it before,
but we're going to be
teaching a data
center class,
energy modeling
class in the spring.
It's open for
undergraduates.
It is a tech elective.
We put it in a petition
with engineering
Student Services,
so it'll be treated as
a tech elective
for those that
are interested in
these kinds of things.
All right.
All right to do.
All right. That is good.
Okay.
Cool. Okay. Question?
No. All right.
Yeah, so we have
here a turbine.
Let's see, it
looks like this.
We have an inlet. It looks
like that. We
have an outlet.
It looks like that.
Here's some shaft work
that's being transferred
out of this.
So let's say this
is maybe our inlet.
This is our outlet.
Control volume.
From that inlet.
So it's adiabatic, right?
So we have no q.in
is equal to Q dot out,
is equal to zero.
This runs on air. So
our substance is air.
And for state one,
We have P one is equal
to 550 pa and T one,
which is 425
Kelvin, 425 Kelvin.
So from this, we have
complete information,
H one and our S one for
state two, What
are we told?
We are told that
it leaves a P two,
which is equal to
110 pa and T two,
which is 325
Kelvin, right?
So it means we know H
two and we know S two.
And our dead
state temperature
that we're given.
So out here, and our T
zero is 25 degrees C,
and our P zero is going
to be 101325 pascal.
So that's our dead
state condition.
All right. Fine. So what
is the formula for
W dot out of a
turbine like that?
If I have this
as my M dot,
steady flow, and
I have this m.in.
All right, it's well,
we can call it
like this, right?
It'd be dot and then,
you know, W out.
All right, which
is our M dot times
H and H one minus RH two.
Well, that's
easy. So that's
our dot, dot out.
The second law efficiency,
what's the second law
efficiency going to be
equal to here
for a turbine?
All right.
So it's our real
workout. All right.
Remember, we're
going to, like,
contrast this with
what we had before.
So that's going to be
our W dot out there.
All right, it's going
to be reversible, right,
of a reversible,
reversible
work that's that's there.
And so what this is
going to look like,
right, is it is
going to be W dot,
out divided by essentially
the X dot, right,
basically our X dot,
right, our x.in, right?
So what is, you know,
looking at essentially at
at our inlet condition.
So the x.in, right?
This is a flow X org.
So this is dot times
one minus H naught
minus T naught,
one minus naught, right?
It's going to
be your x.in.
And this gets
substitute here.
Of course, the
other thing that we
didn't write here was
that we have
our state zero,
so our state zero is
that we know P zero,
we know T zero, and from
that we know H zero,
and we know S zero
from that, right?
So our W dot out, right,
which is the actual,
we determine
this way, the x.in, right?
So the reversible
work, right?
If we operated this device
isentropically between
this condition,
right, and the
dead state, okay?
So really what you're
doing here with this
x.in is you're saying
that I start off
at state one,
and I drive my system
to state zero, right?
And with this, you
can come up with
a second law efficiency.
If you substitute numbers,
I come up with 60.6%.
What is the
difference between
what I have
written here as
a second law
efficiency and
the isentropic
efficiency of a turbine?
What is different
in the analysis?
What if I said, you
don't have to do
quiz two if you answer
this super well?
Is that enough?
How do we define
the isotropic
efficiency of a turbine?
There's no wrong
answers now.
Now it's long enough
that any answer is
acceptable. Kai?
Isotropic efficiency
is the the efficiency
that would have efficiency
efficiency over
the work W dot actual
divided by W
dot isentropic,
which is.h1 minus H
two A divided by m
dot times H one
minus H two.
So what's the difference?
Ba Yes.
I like this where
it's going.
So what Maya says
is that in the
bottom, right,
we treat this process
as isentropic
between State one
and State two, okay?
State one and State two.
So this is between State
one and State two, right?
What I'm saying
is that when
you look at This,
again,
in the denominator of
the reversible work.
It's not between state
one and state two.
It's between that state
and the dead state, okay?
And that is the
difference between
isotropic efficiency,
which is good for
us in analyzing
a second law
efficiency there.
It's like I have XerGy
is like I have
this at state one.
How do I get all
the work out of
this given that that's
my dead state
that's there?
That's the maximum
reversible work
that I could get out from
this condition and
the environment
that I live in, all right?
Whereas, like
this here from
an isentropic
efficiency of
a turbine, you
have state one,
you have state two, or
you have state one,
and you know something
about state two,
like the pressure,
and then
you assume it's
isentropic.
So it's like giving
two pressures,
an upstream and a
downstream from
a turbine and a
temperature upstream,
you know, you can
determine HTS
from that, right?
Okay. Yes, please. You are
definitely assuming
that this is
an isotropic and it's
isentropic to
the dead state.
Okay? All right.
With that,
I'm going to close.
If you have questions,
I'm up here.
That concludes our
exergy section.