Uh. Alright, so today,
we're going to solve
energy balance problems
not only involving work,
but also heat. I
feel very loud.
Um, That's one part of it.
The second part
of it is that
we're going to
go just beyond
the fluids and then
also into the solids.
And then after
day it picks up.
So like, on
Wednesday, Thursday,
or Wednesday and Friday,
and then Monday,
we're going to do,
like real devices
and things
that matter, for
what happens.
Okay? All right. So again,
today sort of my cadence
is usually right.
Like, I do a lot of
theory and math,
and then I put it
to practice, okay,
which is pretty much
what engineering.
So today, we're going to
be putting some
stuff into practice.
Go through some problem
solving approaches that I
hope are then you know,
getting you into
good habits
for later on on
assessments, okay?
So, this one here,
we're looking at,
again, one of these
combined ones.
We have a process
here, we're
transferring work
in electrically into
a piston cylinder.
This is our control
volume drawn here,
and the system is
kept at constant
pressure, right?
And so what that
means All right,
as we transfer work in,
we may expect to
also have some
work transfer out, okay?
What makes it less
obvious if it's a work
transferred in or out from
that is that we
have a Q out, okay?
And I don't know
the magnitude
of Q out relative to
the work transfer that
I'm doing here. Okay?
And this question asks
us to determine
two things.
So the first is what's the
final temperature
of the steam?
And then what is
the difference
between these quantities
in the parentheses, okay?
And this U plus PV here,
again, is what not
really very useful
for this system.
It's kind of a trick,
but it's going
to become very,
very useful when we
get into things like
turbines and systems
that involve flow.
Okay? All right, so
here, what are we told
about the problem?
So we have our
mass defined.
We have a mass
that's here.
And remember, this
is a closed system,
so that mass doesn't
change, okay?
So we have a mass.
Let's talk about
state one.
So we have a
mass that's here
of 0.025 kg, right?
We have a P one
here that's given
as our 300 kPa.
What else do we know
about the initial state?
It was a good
weekend. Cow one.
It was awesome.
I was there.
Also, we honored some of
our great lecturers
at that game,
not just academics
or not just
athletics, also
academics there.
Okay, it's a saturated
vapor, right?
So basically, we start
off with saturated vapor,
which means the
quality is equal to.
One. There we go.
Like an extra point,
right? So there you go.
So we have a quality
of equal to one
there, right?
And with this, we
have sufficient
information to
define that state.
Good to go, okay?
About state two,
what do we know
about state
two? About state two?
We know the pressure.
We know that P
two is equal to P one.
So that's an
isoberic process.
Bless you. That's good.
And again, we
also know that,
the M one is equal
to the uh right,
we know that the mass
doesn't change
in the system.
And what we'd like
to know, right,
is we'd love to know
what T two is, okay?
And for us to be able
to do this, okay,
to get this right is
essentially to be able
to determine T two.
A, what we're going
to determine is
U two plus p2v2, okay?
I'll tell you that
that's a property
in a second.
But the energy
analysis that
I'm going to do
is that we're
going to determine
U two plus
P two times V two.
And with that information
and knowledge about
P two being 300 300 pa.
I'm going to be able to
tell you the state, okay?
So here, like I
said, I'm searching
for YouTube plus P
two times V two.
And with this, I'm
actually then going to be
able to answer what the
temperature is, okay?
Let me see. Am
I on my video?
Yeah, I'm good here.
Okay? All right, so
that's Essentially,
we'll we'll get started.
You see, am I
missing any points?
No. Okay, so now what
I'm going to write
is I'm going to
write essentially
the conservation of
energy applied to my
control volume
here, right?
So the area
contained within it.
So for that, I'm going
to say the Delta E CV,
where C andV denote
control volume is equal to
the energy that I transfer
in minus the energy
that I transfer out.
What are ways that energy
can change in the
control volume?
Yes. Kai Kai. I see.
Kai. Okay. See, I
practice this for
you and then you
practice your name
for me Delta U plus
Delta KE plus Delta B.
We'll see who needs
more practice,
remember it first, right?
So that's what we
have. Okay, right?
And then the way that
we can transfer energy
in right is I
can have W in,
work in, I can have
heat in, right?
And the way that
I can transfer
energy out of this
system, right,
is I can have W out
plus Q out, right?
Okay, right?
So our assumptions.
So if we were going
to talk about assumptions,
I'm doing things
in a little bit
of a reversed order.
But if we come to
some assumptions,
you know, here,
what assumptions
do you think you would
make in this problem?
I would say let's
go term by term.
So how do we feel
so I would say
for kinetic and
potential energy,
will neglect I will
basically neglect
Delta KE.
And Delta PE, all right?
I'll tell you when we
can't neglet that.
Systems where you
can't neglect that
are like rockets,
right, nozzles.
That's the whole
point, right?
I have a lot of energy.
I give gas, and I
want to go, right?
So that's when you
can't neglect it.
Delta PEs, you don't
neglect when you're
storing energy.
Think like pump
hydro, right?
I'm storing a
lot of stuff.
I'm not doing
pumped hydro,
and I don't see a
rocket in that, right?
So this basically
would be,
you know, two terms that
I'm getting rid of.
The other one that I
don't see here, right,
is a I don't see
a Q in, okay?
I do see a work
in, though,
in terms of the
electrical,
there is a
potential that we
may have, um, you know,
depending on
how much Q out,
there may be the
potential for
a potential W in,
but more likely than not,
you know, if I was going
to hazard a guess,
I would say that there's
the potential
for work to be
transferred out
via boundary work,
expansion work, okay?
And I can check that
a posteriori, right?
I could look at
that and say, if
I define this as W out,
how would I know
that this was then
work transferred in?
How would I know that?
It would be negative.
Exactly. So if you're
consistent with that,
then you would know,
and then you could go
back and say, actually,
you know, my bad,
that's what I
meant, all right?
Okay, so this
is what we're,
you know, so we'll
set it up like this.
So for electrical work
in, how do we write this?
Okay, so we have
voltage, okay,
which I'll write with
some different version
of V. Again, we run
out of letters, right?
So I have voltage times my
current times my
duration, time, right?
So that's going to
be that's in SI,
volts amp seconds,
that'll give you
joules, okay?
So we have that there
is a work in term for
a work for a workout
term, right?
It's an isobaric process.
So how can I write the
boundary work term here?
Delta P Delta V, right?
So P, let's just
call it as P,
you know, one for now
because P one is P two,
but I got to give us
something, right?
That's going to be V two
minus RV one, right?
Okay. I could also
write this right?
Let's say it's P one
times the mass, right?
You know, so if
I say here that,
one is equal to two
is equal to M, right?
So then I can write
P one times N,
and then I can
write V two,
little V two minus
little V one, right?
So the specific
volumes I can
write in that way, okay?
I can also write this one
as also being as
M times U two,
little U two minus
little U one, right?
Recall, this is like
energy per volume.
Okay. Am I
missing anything?
No, that all looks
pretty good.
We can go on and do
the substitution.
So if I wrote
right this out,
I can push this
to the edge.
It is like hot
today. Oh, my God.
Um, so right here.
So we can we substitute
that in, right?
So that's basically
M times U two
minus U one is equal to V,
which is where this
is voltage, I,
which is current times T,
which is times,
duration minus,
then, here's the
negative sign.
So it's a negative of P
one times the mass times,
um, V two minus V one.
And then, again, we still
have a Q out that's
minus a Q out there, okay?
And so to create, right,
so if I want to create
this term here,
what I'm going to
do is I'm going to
move My pressure
volume terms,
these PV terms, I'm
basically going to
bring them to the
left hand sign.
This I know, right? So I
know the electrical
work in.
I know the heat out
because it's given
there, right?
So if we do that,
great arrangement.
So I can write M times
parentheses U two
minus or U two plus P one,
V two, and then that's
going to be minus
U one plus p1v1, right?
That's the left hand side.
Again, all I've
done is I've
moved this term
over to here,
and then that's equal
to our V voltage,
I current T time
minus RQ out.
Okay?
Sorry. Okay. All right.
Yeah, so that's
good. All right.
So what I'm going to do
right now, and again,
we'll go through this
in lecture five A,
which is on Wednesday.
But this U plus P plus
V is tabulated, right?
This is something given
in your book, all right?
This here we call H two,
right, because
P one is P two.
And then this term
here, we would call
is little H one, okay?
And the word for
this is enthalpy.
Okay. Someone
did the reading.
Great. Now reading ahead.
I love that even
more. All right.
I Yeah, that's basically
your enthalpy.
And the point
is that this is
something that can be
used as a property, right?
This can be an
independent property
that you use
with pressure,
specific volume,
temperature, and then you
have complete
information, right?
This is one of
those other
independent properties
that exists.
It really isn't different
than any other energy.
It's still energy, right?
Internal energy, enthropy,
Gibbs free energy.
These are all energies.
So it's still
energy, right?
Go ahead. We're using
pressure independent
from. Is that
what you said?
Yes. If you know
enthalpy and
you know pressure, you
can define everything.
Again, we'll go through an
example on that either on
Wednesday or Friday? Cool.
We can rearrange
and solve for this,
H two is equal to
V voltage current
time divided by
M minus Q out divided
by M plus H one, okay?
So if you go in now
and we do those
substitutions,
you'd get that
value, all right?
And the point is that
for H one, right,
we know H one because
we know this, right?
So basically,
knowing pressure,
knowing quality, right,
we know we would know
H one from this.
And if you want to
see how to do that,
that's located here in
the notebook, okay?
I'm not going to do
coating on the whiteboard.
I All right.
But yeah, the point
is that the inputs
that are pressure
and in quality,
and then you would
get you'd get H one.
Now with H two, so
now we know H two.
Two, we call this H two,
and by having H
two and P two,
you're able to
determine you're
able to determine
T two there.
I have a value for H two,
so my value for H
two is this my
value for H two?
What am I printing?
No, I'm printing
my um I can
put some let's put
some terms in here.
Basically, um, D. Yes.
My H two here, if
you put that in is
3,009 kilojoules
per kilogram.
Again,
by knowing this
information
and knowing the pressure,
you determine T two and
then T two is equal to
270 degrees C, right?
Let's see. Cool. So
that's all good.
You could represent
this on a PV diagram.
So you could go and
create, like I do
in that document,
a PV diagram.
So there's your line
of saturation, okay?
So low values of
V are liquids,
of saturated liquid,
saturated vapor.
Where you start off with
is that this pressure,
right, so we have this
P one that's here.
You start off on the
line of saturation,
which is the
quality of, um,
right, which is the
quality of one here.
And you move isoberically,
then to state to
state two, right?
So the net result
of this basically
this process is where
you you'd end up,
and you would know
that again by
figuring out what
the H two is.
If the H two is
less than H one,
then this would
then be moving
in the opposite
direction, okay?
Cool. Any questions
about that?
Yes, please. Got
the pressure.
Yeah. The thing is that
you can use this
as an input.
I know, and you
can also do that
in your tables.
If you want to go
in and do tables,
you can also interpolate,
you look at the value.
But the point is that
right here, state two,
let's say state two
is basically do
state of water here,
P is equal to P
two or P one,
depending on how
you define it.
This is how do we give it?
This is in pa, so
you can declare
the units of
pa. Like that, and
then H, right?
So the H, you write
H equal to H two,
and just put
that in as units
of kilojoules
per kilogram.
And you can also
name it, right?
You go name equals two,
and then you would
have that, right?
And then the way
that you call it in
dot notation is
that, let's say,
in this case, S two,
do little H will then
give you enthalpy.
Again, all the
information is in
the notebook there,
but that's how
it works, okay?
And get comfortable with
this because we're going
to do other properties.
There's going to
be a bunch of
other dot, you
know, things there.
So right now
we're at dot H,
right? Other
questions? Okay.
Yeah, because we know H
two and we learned one,
then you'd be able to
compute, right, right?
You could look up the
internal energy, right?
So if you wanted to
know internal energy,
right, you can
go t two dot U.
If you want to learn
the volume, right,
this would be like
two dot little V
and so on and so forth
to pull those values.
And the same thing
then for state one,
t dot, you know,
U, P, you know,
and then you could also
do dot, dot V, right?
And it's instructive
for you to
multiply those out to
actually take those,
do the calculation
like that,
and then compare it
with actually what
the enthalpy values
would be, okay?
I highly recommend for
systems like this.
So closed systems
like that, like,
resist the urge to
jump straight to,
you know, Delta H, okay?
I would say start
from, you know,
the fundamentals
writing like, you know,
this, organize your
internal energies,
make your assumptions
about pressures,
move things over. Okay?
If you read the book,
which some of you have.
They for things like
constant pressure
processes,
will encourage you
to jump and say,
Hey, I could just write
Delta H here, okay?
I mean, you can
also do that,
but I find that when I
teach ME 40 to students
and they have,
Oh, I don't know when
to do internal energy.
I don't know when
to do enthalpy.
Don't think like that.
Just start from
the basics,
this to this, you know,
to this, and, like,
let it all evolve
out naturally
to where you can
form, you know,
mathematically,
your enthalpies and
then go into it,
okay? Otherwise,
it's confusing.
You have to hold
too much in your
you already have enough to
keep in your heads, okay?
Good? Yes, please.
Right I missed it.
How did you get one?
E one, this is easy.
Each one is I know
my pressure and I
know my quality.
I know two independent
properties.
If I declare this in PCLor
which you can do if
you click that link,
you put that in
and then you
just go st dot H.
You just would
write an St dot H,
and that would
give you enthalpy.
You know these two
and you have complete
information.
Okay. If there's no
other questions,
then I'm going
to move on to
the next one. All right.
I'm again.
Did anyone go
to the lecture
today from Admiral
Meyer or no?
One? What did you think?
That was a great lecture.
Yeah. Yeah, he was
basically right
a mechanical engineering
student like you.
What's up? Plus nuclear.
Yeah, I did nuclear,
but I think
his core expertise
originally
was mechanical there.
Yeah, it was neat.
Very inspiring.
Okay. Great, great, great.
I liked what he said about
if you want to go
fast, go alone.
If you want to go
far, go together.
I think that's the
thing one of the things
I'm going to keep
in my mind, okay?
All right, so going with,
final temperatures.
Alright, so this
one, again,
so the previous
one was with,
let's see, with water.
We'll do this one
with nitrogen.
Nitrogen's an ideal gas.
I'll solve this
one in two ways.
One essentially doing
the way that we did,
and then I'll show
you one assumption
you can make with an
ideal gas for this.
Again, we have work
transferred in,
we have heat
transferred out,
and the potential
to transfer work
from through boundary
work, right?
So my first step in
my thermal problem,
I'm going to draw a
schematic in a boundary.
So here's my boundary.
That defines my
control volume.
Um, And what I'm going to
assume here check my
video. I still good.
Okay, what I'm
going to assume
here is that I'm dealing
with an ideal gas, okay?
So we have an ideal gas.
That's an assumption.
We have quasi
equilibrium expansion
or compression.
All right. We're going
to neglect Delta KE,
and we're going to
neglect Delta P.
Kinetic potential
energy effects.
And we're going to assume
that boundary work.
Boundary work is
only through P dv.
All right? Okay.
Good. All right.
Then what are
we looking for?
Let me say that first.
So what we're
looking for in
this problem is the
final temperature.
So determine Final
temperature.
Okay.
Also,
the lecture hall there
was, like, amazing.
And I mean, this
is pretty nice,
but that one was
very, very nice here.
I hadn't been in the
Grimes building yet.
Okay. All right.
So again, you know,
from our
fundamentals, right?
So our Delta, right?
So basically the Delta E
and our control volume.
So within the dashed
line is, again,
our E in minus
our E out. Okay.
At some point, you
won't have to write
this every time,
but I'm just
doing it so you
can follow your steps.
Again, we over Delta U,
our Delta KE, our
Delta P is again,
equal to write
our Wn I'm sorry,
Wn plus our Q in
minus R W out plus our
Q out there, okay?
So we can neglect
potential
and kinetic
energy effects.
All right. I see right
that we have a Q out,
but I don't have
a Q in, right?
So the Q in is gone.
And again, our work in
here is just like before.
We have the
electrical work,
so we have duration,
we have current,
we have voltage.
So we have voltage,
which I'll write with
this kind of in
this kind of way.
Voltage times my
current times my time.
So that defines
the work in.
And for our workout,
Again, we're
told that it's
an isobaric process.
So our work then is
this P. So if I called
this if I called this as
P one equals to P
two equals to P,
then I'll just
call this as P,
and then I'll
multiply that by V
two minus V one.
All right? My Q
out um is a given.
Okay. That is good.
Um Where am I at?
Yeah, so just like
we did before,
so I can separate,
um, these things,
so I can go with
my M times,
my U two minus my U one.
So again, we have
constant mass?
So our M is equal to
a constant, right?
So I have the mass,
that's equal to my VT V
minus my pressure times
my mass times
little V two.
Minus little V one,
and then that's minus
my Q out, right?
Again, we can
organize that to have
enthalpy form, you
know, naturally.
So here, right, I'll
have U two plus
p2v2 minus U two or
U one plus p1v1.
The pressures
are constant,
so we'll just call that
as P, right there.
And then that
would be equal to
V T minus Q out.
Enthalpy two, I'll
move the boards.
Okay. All right, so
this is your H two,
and then this
is your H one.
And then we can,
you know, solve
for H two, again, just
like we did before.
Our H two here is
H one plus the
V. So voltage current
time minus Q out,
and then that whole
thing is divided by
the mass in the cylinder.
All right. And just like
with the vapor case,
you know, once I
know um, H two,
because I know P two,
I know the um I
know the final
state at T two.
So we can look at some
properties, okay?
Properties. All right,
so let's talk
about properties.
So, um, it's an ideal gas,
so we can determine
the mass.
Our mass is equal
to our P one,
which we can just call as
P since it's constant.
P times V one,
V one is given as
half a cubic
meter divided by
the specific gas
constant R and T one.
R, in this case,
for nitrogen is
296.8 joules per
kilogram times Kelvin.
Again, this is nothing but
the universal
gas constant,
and then divided by
the molar mass of
the substance,
and then you can
get to that value.
Okay, um, Is that good?
Yeah, so if you
substitute,
the pressures and the
volumes and all that,
which you'll have
is the mass is
2.2 kilograms.
That's your first step.
The Q out we have as
a given in joules,
the voltage, the
current, the time,
our W in, which was
our I times our voltage
times our time.
Okay, so our I
is two amps,
our voltage is 120 volts,
and the duration is
five times 60
seconds, all right?
And then this, if you
multiply it through,
then you'll have 7,272,070
2000 joules
of electrical work
that's transferred in.
If you want to use
again, if you want
to use electronic tables,
the way then to
get to H one,
we need to know
right here,
this H one to have that.
O H one would
depend on our
state one, our state one,
we know P one and
we know our P one,
which is basically
just P, and then we
know RT one there
with this, right?
And so if you
use these two,
you'd be able to
then produce,
basically from
this information,
you'd be able to
then know what H one
is as a value, okay? Cool.
So then, H one
you have, right?
This is our work in,
which we just
computed here,
our Q out, right?
This is given already
as 2,800 Jules,
the M is what we
just determined
here with our ideal
gas relation, right?
Then from that, if
you substitute
it and you'll be
able to get to our H two.
And so for state
two, All right.
What you know then
is, you know,
H two and you know
pressure, right?
And so with this
information, you'd
be able to
determine T two.
Okay? Yeah, so, you know,
pretty plug and
shock, okay?
I'll give you one
alternative way
to this, so let
me move this in.
Well, I guess
I should tell
you what the
temperature is.
So the temperature
is here 56.
So I have 56 degrees
Celsius, right?
So the one alternative way
to look at this
is to pick up
from our definition for
our energy equation.
So H two is H one
plus V voltage
current time minus Q
out divided by
M, all right?
And to recognize that
for an ideal gas,
so we can recognize
basically for
an ideal gas,
that the differential
of enthalpy,
so dH is equal
to CP, right?
So, specific
heat at constant
temperature, right?
And we could do this
substitution then.
So if we assume so if we
assume that Cp is
equal to a constant,
which, you know, for
temperature differences
of, like, you know,
less than than 100 degrees
Celsius different.
That's an okay assumption.
What you can do
then, is we can say
H two minus H
one is equal to
Cp times T two
minus T one, right?
And for this
difference, it
doesn't matter
if it's Kelvin
minus Kelvin or
Celsius minus Celsius,
but it has to be
like the same units
because you
want the right,
you want the
difference in that.
And so if you substitute
this above, you can
then rearrange,
and what you can
say is that T two
is then equal to T one,
plus, plus V voltage
current time minus Q out,
and then that all divided
by M and cp, okay?
And CP, this is, again,
this is very common.
You know, this is
like Googleable,
you know, values.
They also exist and
are published in
the back of the
book in tables.
And as you get
comfortable working
with, like,
you know, air or
water, you know,
these things they'd be
provided on quizzes,
but it's also the kind
of thing that, you know,
you may be able to
remember just off
the top of the top
of your head, okay?
And the rest of it
you would know.
So this is the
table information,
but the rest of
it you have,
and the T one is given.
And so that's another
way to get to T
two to T two there,
okay? Yes, please.
Give us I'm going to
give you the whole back
of the textbook in
properties on all of
the quizzes, right?
And if I'm kind, sometimes
I will write, Hey,
here's the CP of
the substance,
so you don't need to
flip back and forth.
And generally, I'm kind
unless you make me not be,
all right? Other
questions?
So again, basically,
it's the same
drill as before.
What's interesting
about the ideal gases,
though,
is you can follow
this approach of
going with states and
properties and determining
enthalpies there, right?
And then from
that enthalpy
getting to the
temperature.
But the other thing
that you're allowed
to do is to go
this approach.
This is actually this is,
this is by
definition, right?
So dH is equal to Cp dT.
This is not just
for ideal gases.
You know, so
you can go and
then write, you know,
Delta H, Cp dT and
do the substitution.
Right? The only
thing, though,
what's the what makes
this a bad assumption
sometimes,
right, is if I want to
get to this equation,
right, and you take
the integral, okay?
And what you're assuming
when you do this is
you're taking the CP
out of the
integral, right?
So you're assuming that's
a constant value, right?
And it's the
delta T, right?
Um. And to know whether
or not this is a good
or a bad assumption,
it only comes
with, like, time.
But my rule of thumb
would be for, um,
like, just gases,
like ideal gases and
stuff like that.
That's usually a pretty
good assumption.
Better than 5%
let's say probably
better than 5% error
most of the time.
For liquids and stuff,
too, also, you know,
it's generally, you
know, pretty good.
And then this is
also just faster.
It's much faster, right,
to just get to
this and jump to
that than what I've
done there, okay?
That's my first
comment about it.
So I would
recommend, you know,
do whatever you feel, you
know, basically
comfortable with.
Both are correct,
in my view,
for the purposes
of this course,
but that one is the
more exact, right?
That one is the
more exact way,
okay? One thing.
Second thing I want to say
is that the book, okay,
if you read it
has an approach,
and you'll see this
that comes later.
But they have, you know,
kind of funny approaches
when it comes to
these kind of
CP dT things, right?
So they'll have an
approach where,
you know, with
some math, right,
they'll be able to not
assume this kind
of constant,
you know, specific
heat and all of that.
And that's all
fine and well,
but, like, this is
what you start with.
And if you want to be
exact, just go to this.
Don't bother with any sort
of confusing tricks
because this gets
you exact properties
at those states and
will be the most
accurate, okay?
Okay. Um, The final thing
I want to mention
about this is that,
you know, you have
a free choice
when it comes
to the selection of
this CPE, right?
The fact that it's
going to be between
two different
temperatures.
My advice on this is just
go room temperature.
Most of this class, you're
just going to say,
what value do I take?
I'll go to the
table, look,
I'll choose one,
and just say,
I took this CPE at
room temperature.
That's it. So
I went there.
I went room temperature,
and I picked this um
You can also pick
from a different one,
that's perfectly
fine, too.
But I would say go in,
pick one, say where
you got it from.
You don't need
to defend it.
You know, you say,
press your shot,
you said so, you
know, that'll
work here, not
for a job, okay?
But, you know, you can
go room temperature
and just say,
and like I said, for
most of these problems,
that's going to be
a pretty accurate
approach.
And if you ever
doubt it, right,
especially in the
homework, you know,
by all means, go in and
do the exact
calculation, alright?
All clear? Yes, please.
Yeah, sure, sure.
This I cannot
slide. Sorry.
But it is all there. So if
you click it,
you'll see it.
All right. Cool. Let
me erase them. Do do.
Feels like repeats today.
All right. Do do do.
That was my least
favorite day of running.
Okay.
All right, that's gone.
And then these
examples that I had
there also may be
helpful for some
of the homework.
So some of the ones you
we don't know where
to get started.
Some of these ones
from class might be
helpful for some
of the homework,
especially let's say
Homework three there.
Okay to
do I
Okay. All right.
So now, you know,
we're just doing basically
fluids there or basically,
let's call it steam
as a vapor or
a gas and the nitrogen
that we dealt
with as a gas.
When we want to
evaluate changes in
internal energy or
let's say also
this, you know,
kind of new this term,
enthalpy when it comes
to liquids or solids,
you're not going to so
basically for
like a liquid
or so a liquid or a solid,
okay, um, C is
CP is CV, okay?
The reason, right, is we
got CP because when we
transfer heat in to
something at
constant pressure,
it could also transfer
workout, right?
So you would expect
there, essentially that
to be a bigger term,
which it is for
gases like that,
CP is greater than CV.
In liquids and solids,
when we heat them, they
don't generally expand
as much as you would
have in a vapor, okay?
So what we call
them is we call
these substances
incompressible, okay?
When you take ME
one oh one oh six,
you'll get more
into what it means.
But essentially, if I
apply a pressure to it,
does it change volume,
yes or no, okay?
And if it doesn't
appreciably change,
it's an incompressible
substance, right?
So in a solid, you know,
so in a solid here, okay.
So for this slide
here, right?
So the C is the
CP is the CV,
it's incompressible,
all right?
And for that reason,
um, you know,
it only depends
on, you know,
so change then in
internal energy
is, um, right?
Is only a function
then, of
temperature, right?
So basically this,
how to use this
in practice.
If you go to your
book, it will
not say C for a solid.
What you'll see is
that it's called CP.
I don't know. It is.
Okay?
It could just be
C, but basically,
when you go in, you'll
see that this is a CP.
And again, it's
right, CP is CV.
If dU is equal to CV dt,
Iso facto, right, this is
then Cp dT there, right?
Cool. One, and like
I said before,
for this case,
especially for solids,
there's not going to
be multiple values, right?
Most of the tables
and stuff that
you look up,
one poor guy
or gal went in
and measured this
probably 100 years ago.
They did it at this
one temperature,
and they put
them in a table.
Bless him for
that. We have it,
but you're not
going to see
this for like zero, ten,
20, 30, onto 100 degrees
C. It's just going to be
a one temperature,
all right?
Okay. So when you
want to do that,
you'll say, okay,
here's what I looked
up in the table.
That's my specific heat,
and there's my
temperature difference.
Cool.
All right. For
the enthalpy,
so going into
right, that's
our definition.
If I take a full
differential of that, right,
I'll have the DU, but I'll
have PDV VDP, okay?
And because it's
incompressible,
the volume doesn't
change, right?
So the DV term, it's
not there, right?
So that's out.
Um, And so you
can integrate.
And again, assuming a
constant specific key,
you'll have that
value, right?
And what I'm telling you,
what I'm going to tell you
here is that in solids,
it's a very low
value of V, okay?
It's like 0.001,
or less meter cube
per kilogram, okay?
So a very tiny value,
even times a big pressure
differential is not
a very big value.
Does it makes sense.
So like this
term, in a solid,
because it has a
very high density or
a very low specific heat,
also insignificant.
So you're going to
end up essentially
changes in
internal energy,
and the changes
in Xenthalpy,
which we'll go into
more, are just
going to be C delta.
And that's in a solid
in a liquid, okay?
The same statement about
internal energy,
you know, holds.
For enthalpy, though, Um,
the VDP doesn't
necessarily go away, okay?
And that has to do with
the fact that you can get
some pretty big pressure
differences when you pump,
okay? So you
have two cases.
One is that I don't
have a pressure drop.
That's a heat exchanger.
So I have a
heat exchanger.
There's not going
to be a pressure
drop across a
heat exchanger.
So the change
is going to be
C delta T. On
the other hand,
when you deal
with a pump, when
you deal with,
like, a pump,
and I'm transferring
work in
from a pump and I'm
moving a fluid,
those are generally
isothermal processes.
And so that change in
enthalpy is going to
be a V Delta P term, okay?
Um, If you were to say,
like, Hey, I have
a CDT and a VDP,
more likely than not,
this is not going to be a
big it's just not
going to be a big term
in the C delta T.
And we actually exploit
this fact when we
pump fluids that it
requires very little
work to pump a fluid.
Like a whole fricking
power plant basically
plays off of the game
that a vapor has,
you know, very
low density,
very high specific volume.
So VDP is very big
there from a turbine.
That's the workout, and
the work in is
from the pump.
And that's VDP, but it's
with a liquid, and
the V is very low.
The Delta P across
is the same.
That's pretty
much the name
of the game, alright?
Okay. Yeah, so we did
ideal we did this problems
energy analysis of
involving work in heat for
the ideal gas for
the pure substance in
the case of the
water vapor,
again,
click on the links
and review that
if you want.
The last one that
we'll do, I'll
start this now, and
if I don't have time,
I'll finish it in
the next lecture
is to deal with
incompressible
substances. All right.
So in this problem,
we're looking
at cooling of
a solid block.
So I think like
in this case,
we have hot, um,
you know, hot iron.
So we're in
a material science
department here.
So that's kind of an
appropriate example.
So here you basically
have, you know,
hot chunk of metal
that is being
dropped with some mass and
it's being dropped
into a liquid,
which is at a lower one.
And what we want to do is
to determine the
temperature when
equilibrium is
reached, okay?
We can draw, right?
I can draw pretty much
two control volumes
and the sum of the
control volume, okay?
So here, let's say
this is my liquid.
Here's my block.
I want to draw one
control volume,
which is just
around the block.
So let's call
this as CV one.
And the second
control volume
that I would like to draw
is everything that
contains the liquid, okay?
All right. This is
kind of a mess.
They took my blue marker.
So this is what you're
left with, right?
And so this part that has
the water is
basically CV two.
So we can call
this as water, and
we can call this as iron,
right? All right.
So if I want to write
my conservation of
energy equation,
I would like to
first start with
the combined
system, right?
So I'm going to
write my change in
energy from my
combined system.
So the Delta E CV one
plus CV two is
equal to the EN
of CV one plus
CV two minus E
out of CV one plus
CV two. All right?
You know, we're
going to neglect
kinetic and
potential energy.
Even if I drop
the rock in,
let's say now
it's, you know,
we're not it
wasn't, you know,
I wasn't throwing
it, you know,
Justin Berland or slinging
it at that thing.
So basically, you
just, you know,
you kind of you
put it in there.
And so what you'll
have then is,
we'll say that the
Delta U All right,
four CV one plus CV two.
So the change in internal
energy is then equal to
our W in plus our
Q in of CV one plus
CV two minus or
plus a negative of
W out plus Q out,
CV one plus CV two, right?
And what I'm going
to say is for
this process,
when I look at the
combined control volumes,
do you see any work or
heat transfer happening
to this combined system?
All right, on
the sixth row,
I see a head shake.
I like that. So
no. All right.
So there's no worker
heat transfer
in and no worker
heat transferred
out to the combined
one, okay?
There is heat
transfer, of course,
that's going to take
place between the
hot rock and
the cold water.
But if I look at
the combined thing,
it's adiabatic, right?
And I have no work
happening, right?
So this Delta U, right?
Delta U of CV
one plus CV two
is equal to zero.
All right. I Yeah,
which is the other way
to write this is that
I could just say
that Delta U
of CV one plus
Delta U of CV two
is equal to zero,
right,
because these things
are additive, right?
This is an extensive
property, right?
It depends on how
much is there.
So I can add the
internal energy of the
CV one to the internal
energy of the CV two.
That's the combined one,
and as I showed you there,
or as you said,
that there's zero
change, okay?
All right, for an
incompressible,
for our solid,
what I showed on
the slide before,
is that right dU is
equal to CV All right,
CV of T times
times dt, right?
We can integrate this
from state one to two.
We assume it's a constant,
specific heat, and we
can say then, right,
this is Cv times T
two minus T one,
iron, right? F, okay?
And again, we have
free choice as to what
in a sense as to
what temperature
we take the
specific heat at.
But as you'll see
in the textbook,
I believe this one's
only for room temperature.
And as I said
before, the value
that's given is a CP,
and for a solid CV
is CP, alright?
Cool.
Yeah, so then the
change in the
internal energy
then of our CV one.
Just give me a second,
and then we're done.
I have the mass of
the iron times the
specific heat of my iron,
and then that's
going to be times
T two minus t1f.
Okay. And with that,
I'm going to close it.
We'll pick up in
the next lecture
then with our second
control volume.
If you have questions,
I'm up here. Thank you.