Um, okay, so today,
we're going to continue
with the energy,
basically energy transfer.
We'll do a couple
more examples.
Throw one to you
guys also to show
me if you know what
you're talking
about, all right?
Yeah,
so we'll talk about
the concept of work,
electrical work and forms
of mechanical work.
We'll get more into
the first law.
I'll take you
through kind of
a very detailed problem
solving approach for
a first law problem.
You know, if time permits,
we'll get a little
bit of the fluid
flowing as
energy transfer.
Okay? So examples of,
like, mechanical work.
I mean, this should be for
mechanical engineers.
Not a slide I
need to present.
Um, All right,
like one of them is
essentially here.
I'm applying a force
basically over a distance.
So in this example, right,
the force I'm applying
is when I'm pushing.
What's resisting me is
essentially inertia
and friction.
And if I displace it
an amount S there,
right, it's going to
be FS is the work.
Another important form
that we'll go into,
especially when
it comes to
engines is what's
called shaft work.
Okay? So if you
think about,
like, everything in
a car, a turbine,
pretty much how
we produce all of
our electricity that's not
solar based
comes from this.
So just keep that
in your mind.
That's going to
come up in, like,
in Week five, okay?
So a quick example before
I turn it over to you.
So this, like I said,
should be very familiar.
So I have some
surface here.
I have a spring. Let's say
maybe there's a mass
on the end of it.
Um And when it's
at equilibrium,
let's say C 85
equilibrium, right?
It's not moving. It's
a rest position, okay?
And if I want to displace
that, you know,
from that position,
I'm going to have
to apply a force,
which means that I'm
going to, you know,
essentially be
transferring transferring
work into the into the
system, all right?
Um, So the way that
we write this,
right, for F is
Hook's law, right?
So what we
basically say from
our buddy hook is
that the amount
that we displace,
let's call it,
let's say X is
proportional to a
constant, right?
So this holds for things
like metals, you know,
other materials,
No hook in,
and so on and so
forth for our
purposes, right?
So force is linearly
proportional
to, uh, to displacement.
So we can take
that and put that
up into there.
So we go with
our D, right?
Our dw is then equal to
our K X, um, dx there.
We can go on and
we can integrate.
Let's say from
zero to X, right?
So let's say for this,
this could be
like from state
one to state two.
So this is state one,
then state two is
somewhere down here.
If I'm integrating
from zero to X,
I'll put like a
till day over here
because these are
the variables
of integration.
Um with it.
And so out of this then,
what you'll have
is a 1.5 right K,
because it's a constant,
so we can take that out
of our integral, right?
So that's one
half K X squared.
And what we assume in
this process that we do it
is that we basically
pull slowly,
right, what's called
reversible, okay?
Alright, so we basically
displace this,
and not really quickly,
we go, you know,
bit by bit and, you know,
pull and we apply this,
you know, to this point
to get to this force.
Maybe we add, like,
little weights
each time until
we end up with
that full force at
that position, okay?
Great.
If we wanted to do, right,
an energy
analysis of that.
So I just wrote
that as a DW.
Let's say we drew here's
my bluet Unbelievable.
Okay, here it
is. All right.
So if we drew, like,
a control volume, right,
let's say around
this, okay?
And let's say we're doing
that work transfer,
like, right at
this interface.
What we can write is Okay,
that the change
in the energy
in that control
volume, right?
So the Delta, let's
call it Delta,
let's call it Delta
E. We can call it CV.
We can call it Delta
E system, right?
It's going to be
equal to, right,
the E in minus
the E out, okay?
It's like, Okay.
Um, making sure
nothing's following.
Everyone's
standing and knock
and ye, at that equation.
Okay. So, what are
the ways that we
can, you know,
that energy can change
and control volume
like that, right?
We're talking normally
about, internal energy.
We could talk about
kinetic energy,
or we could talk
about potential
energy, okay?
So Delta U, that's clear.
We went through it
before. KE. These are
not two separate
variables.
This is the
book's notation,
Delta meaning change,
kinetic E energy.
And the same for
potential on
a Delta PE there.
All right. And then this
would be equal to what?
So what are the ways
we can transfer energy
in will work, right?
So we can have W in,
or we could have
Q in, right?
And then this would
be subtracted by,
write a W out plus
a Q out, all right?
All right.
So, all right, so we
have our schematic.
We drew a boundary
condition, um, you know,
here, I told you my
problem statement,
you know, I made
some assumptions.
We did our physical laws,
we apply, you know,
the hook law to it.
We did the first law
of thermodynamics.
All right.
So if we come back
to the assumptions,
we could say here,
for example,
um, that, you know,
maybe the internal
energy of
this system is not
changing, right?
So we could say
things like,
you know, that there.
So that could be out.
And we could say
here that if it
went really, really
slowly, probably,
then our kinetic energy
that we have there also
wouldn't change, you know?
But you can anticipate
because this is a spring,
that there would
be a change
in the potential
energy there, right?
That's usually what you do
with the spring, right?
Um, We can also
say here that there's
no heat transfer.
So if you looked at
that, probably, again,
if you went
very, you know,
slowly with it,
you wouldn't be
having any sort
of heat transfer
associated with it.
And my question
to you is this?
That is, like, insane.
That is not reversible,
what they're doing.
So does this
look like a work
in process or a
workout process?
This side of the room.
Up is a direction.
I want to know in or out.
Okay. Louder. In,
yes, it's a work in.
Okay. It's like a referee.
You give me the
signals there.
Okay, right? Yeah,
so it's a work in.
There is a no work
transferred out.
So then here from
this problem,
what you would have right
here is that the change in
the potential energy of
that system is
then equal to
the work transferred in.
And that's exactly what
we would have
here then, right?
So this W in is
there. Okay?
And then I think at
the end of this,
you're supposed to then
what are you
supposed to do?
The book says, give
me some reasoning,
you know, I mean,
you did some work.
You stretch something out.
Yeah, that's some
reasoning, okay? Good.
Alright, what would happen
if instead of doing
that very slowly,
I pulled that
spring very fast?
What would you expect
to happen there?
Anyone ever taken a
rubber band and,
like, do that?
So did a rubber band,
and you stretch that
really, really quickly,
as it get hotter
or colder.
Hotter. Do you know why?
So in the rubber
band, right,
you have lots of
polymers in their
chains, okay?
And it turns out when
you stretch them out,
you force those chains
to become more ordered.
They become more
aligned there, okay?
We'll get later into
what that means.
But basically, when
things suddenly go
from kind of chaotic
to very ordered,
there's
consequences to it.
And one of the
consequences
is if I do that
really quick,
the system will warm up.
And some people look
nowadays at actually
using that to,
like, run
refrigeration cycles.
So are called
solid state
refrigerators in that.
Yes, please. Why
did you take
a small you're
going to learn.
At the end of this
class, you're going
to be able to answer
that beautifully.
You go to your parents
and say, yes, this is.
Okay. But the answer
is in short entropy, okay?
All right.
Any questions about
this? Yes, please.
Squiggle X.
So you do this
because I want to
integrate to X as a limit.
And so in order to
do that correctly,
I'm told I'm thinking
back years now
into my calculus,
but you put a squiggle
for a variable
of integration.
So I can't just
write like a limit
of X and then
also dx, I think.
Yes, please.
It one more time
energy negative form.
In this problem? Yeah.
Yeah, so, you know,
it's a fair statement.
So I'm saying it's as
an assumption, okay?
So we can challenge and
look at the assumption.
In here and stretching
the spring,
if I do that
really so we can
look at the outside
environment,
I'm not changing
the temperature
of the outside of the
environment, right?
One, two, I'm also not
changing the pressure,
right on the outside
of this environment
or anywhere there, right?
Okay. So when we
looked at the energy,
when we talked about
internal energy,
we basically said
internal energy basically
depends on only two
properties there, right?
Let's say temperature
and pressure,
pressure and
volume, you know,
volume and
temperature there.
So, in that case,
it wouldn't
be implausible to
say for that case,
I assume that these things
these state properties
aren't changing.
Therefore, I wouldn't have
an expectation
of a change in
thermal energy there.
Okay. To be blunt, though,
and to be clear,
right, if,
like, the
temperature, right?
The most important
factor there
would basically be
the temperature.
If I'm not changing the
temperature of
that system,
I probably wouldn't have
an expectation of changing
the internal energy base
of the thermal
energy. Okay?
Good question.
Other questions?
You're on it for Friday.
I'm happy. Okay.
All right.
Cool. So that's
our spring.
Now what I want to do
is show you a spring,
another kind of spring,
basically a bubble.
So here what you
have while you
have a soap solution here.
You suspend that solution
between a frame, right?
There's basically this
rigid blue frame here,
and you pull, right?
So you basically
pull, right?
We basically pull
on that there.
And what you see
is I stretch
it down just like
the spring before.
And like any other spring,
it restores back to
where it was, right?
It's like, out
kindergarten,
first grade
days, you know,
for the bubble lovers,
maybe yesterday.
But yeah, so essentially,
you know, there
you see that
right I play this force.
And then when I
release it, right,
it goes back to
roughly where
it came from, okay?
So I want so given this,
given your experiences
in kindergarten,
I want you to analyze
this system, okay?
So you take here
a thin soap film,
and the thickness of it
doesn't really
matter too much.
Um, The you may not
be aware of this,
but at the interface of
the liquid in the air,
that interface is
under tension, okay?
We call that surface
tension, right?
And that acts parallel
to the liquid
interface, right?
So here, the
surface tension
is pulling on that
kind of movable wire.
It's pulling it
back inwards, okay?
So at the surface
tension that's there,
the units of
surface tension are
newtons per meter, okay?
I want you to reflect
on what the units
of K were, you
know, over there.
That's good.
And you assume
that this is a
reversible process.
So I'm not doing very
fast movements, right?
Slow, right?
Slow movements there.
So two questions.
What's the formula
for force?
For those that don't
have a Greek phone,
you know, put for Sigma.
And what's the
formula then for
work done if I
stretch it over a
distance dx, okay?
So I said 10 minutes.
I think this
group needs five.
You look like smart today.
So go there, do this.
I'll circulate a bit,
submit the answer, and
then we'll discuss.
All right, if there's
no other questions,
then where did you
read about surface
tension and Gamma?
Where did you read about
surface tension
being Gamma?
Yeah. That's your
critical thinking.
I like that. Okay.
Yeah. All right. Okay.
All right. So
coming in, right.
So the mechanical is
one type of work.
Another common one
that's going to be
there that you'll observe
is the electrical work.
We looked over
this last time.
There was one question
that was about,
you know, whether it's
work or it's heat.
So in order for it
to be heat transfer,
what do we require?
Sure.
Temperature grade,
you need
temperature, right?
So in this problem here,
if I take right
a resistor,
I apply a potential
across it.
I'm going to
generate a current,
and I'm going to the
electrons are
going to move,
and it's going to heat
that resistor, okay?
Right, if you apply
enough voltage,
it'll start on fire,
and it's kind of fun.
So, so we have this
as a resistor,
right? We have
some voltage.
Right, that
we're applying.
So here's a resistor,
here's a voltage,
and you're going
to generate
a a current with that.
And let's say we do that
inside of a control
volume, right?
If I draw the
control volume
to look like this, right?
The electrons are
going to move
through that
boundary, okay?
And then this resistor
is then going to
get warm, okay?
But because it's
the electrons
crossing the boundary,
and then things get
hot inside of it,
that's a work
transfer process.
If on the other hand, you
decide to be wild and
draw a control volume,
like that, right?
This resistor is going
to get hot, okay?
And then it's going
to conduct or
transfer heat
into here, right?
And then that's a
heat transfer process
to this control volume.
So it's very important
how you draw
your boundaries can
sometimes dictate
the solutions that
you follow, okay?
So when you draw that,
you got to be consistent,
then from there
on after, okay?
Great.
All right, so we
talked about this
right with the,
um, you know,
the first law of
thermodynamics.
So it's a conservation
energy, right?
It's not created,
it's not destroyed.
You're just, you know,
transferring it.
And it's like
accounting, right?
Thermo is pretty much
from the first
law perspective,
is nothing but, you
know, accounting.
And the way that
I like, right,
the way that I like
to write this,
you know, because this is
sort of a simplified form.
The way that I always like
to star with it is, right,
there's the change
in the energy
in the control
volume, right?
That's your bank account.
That's your salary,
that's your
Safeway, right?
So here you basically have
the in minus the out,
you know, dictating
what's remaining.
Um, for problems
like this, right?
The way that we have
changes in the energy,
the control volume
or internal energy,
kinetic energy and
potential energy,
right, on the account.
And then the
ways that we can
transfer energy in and out
of such control volumes is
only through work
in heat, okay?
So, and I will, when
I write solutions,
always be writing Wn
W Q in and Q out.
I don't get into
this positive and
negative game.
When you do see it in
the book, though, Q,
without an in or an out,
you should
assume then it's
just an in, right?
Or when it's
positive, it's in,
when it's negative,
it's out, and then W,
when it's on the
right hand side,
when it's positive,
it's out, and when it's
in, it's negative, okay?
Cool, right?
And so just to
remind you what I
wrote there and what
we did last time,
again, at the
risk of being,
you know, really
a broken record.
With it, this is how
the case looks like
for a system with
no mass transfer,
what we call is
a closed system.
All right? Um, All
right, so it's a
closed system.
How much time do
I have? Sure.
Let's do one more example
on the ice core cooling,
and then I'll
get into sort of
the mass transfer
problem, okay?
So let me move this
back to the left board.
Oh, the right board.
That's great.
Do, do, do, do.
All right. Cool.
So in this problem,
we have a container.
This container is rigid,
so it's a rigid container.
And it's at some
initial state,
which is kind of
warm and at a
higher pressure.
And we're going
to cool it.
What is wrong with?
Okay, that's
where I want it.
Trouble is if I put
it in the middle,
there's a huge
reflection I
noticed last time.
Um All right, so we're
going to draw this,
you know, rigid container,
which is here, okay?
There's some mass there.
There's a T one, and
there's a P one.
And we're also told that
from this container,
so I'll draw my control
volume like this.
There's some Q out
that we would like
to determine.
So, given this, what
we want to determine.
So determine Okay,
we'd like to
know what T two,
and we'd like to know
what Q out is, okay?
So, that's good.
So I've drawn
my schematic.
My problem statement
is up there.
What am I assuming, okay?
Okay. So what's
in here is air.
Okay? And what I'm
going to assume
is that this behaves
like an ideal gas.
One. The second
thing that I'm
assuming is when
you see the word
rigid said about
the container,
that's like code for it
doesn't expand
and contract.
That's code for
your volume, right?
Or let's say V
two big V two.
So the overall volume
is equal to B V one.
We're going to assume that
the container is also
impermeable, right?
Impermeable. What
does that mean?
It means no mass
in or out, okay?
And so what this
implies then is that
v2v2 divided by M
is equal to V one
divided by M, right?
So the specific
volume two is equal
to specific volume one,
and you're going
to neglect
changes in kinetic energy,
and you're going
to neglect changes
in potential
energy, right?
Cool. All right.
Good.
So we can write our
conservation of energy.
So here we can say,
right, the change
in the E of our system,
is equal to E in
minus our E out.
All right. Our E in then
is what W in plus Q
in minus W out plus Q out.
All right. The changes.
So one of the
ways that we can
have changes in
this in the system?
So that's how we can
transfer it, right?
But,
think about your
bank account,
your thermo account.
So, what are ways that
the energy can change
in a control volume?
So temperature, which is
then basically internal
energy, right?
So we can talk
about, you know,
Delta U plus Delta
E plus Delta P
is then going to be
equal to Wn plus Qn
minus W plus Q out.
From our assumptions
here, right?
We're going to neglect
kinetic energy.
We're going to
neglect changes
in potential
energy, right?
So that's going
to be equal to
our delta E system.
So we break that
down. Okay? Talk to
me about this formula.
So do we have work
transfer here for
an isochoric
process? No, okay?
So we have no W in
there and no W out.
What about Q in?
No, right? So we
just have that.
So at the end of it, so
our E in minus our E
out is nothing but,
um, Q out, right?
And the change in the
energy of the system
is only going
to be changes
in internal energy, right?
So basically,
Delta U is going
to be equal to Q out.
All right? Yes, please.
Negative.
You're on it, man.
I like that. Okay.
Right. Right?
This is a process
we're moving from
the plot that we see,
we're moving 1-2.
So estily this change in
internal energy
is U two minus
U one is equal to the
negative of our Q out.
All right.
Cool. Yeah, so
everything until now,
should make
sense. All right?
For an ideal gas,
what I'm going to
tell you right now,
I'm going to tell
you something.
I'll back it up
with an example,
and then we'll see
what time as we
go, all right?
Changes in the
internal energy
of an ideal gas only
depend on temperature,
okay? Not pressure, okay?
It's only temperature,
all right?
I'll back this up. You did
these simulations
of an ideal gas
with these particles
moving around.
Translational kinetic
energy, okay?
So it's only one half mv
squared for each
particle, right?
Okay. Um, This is good.
What I'm going to tell
you is that, like,
temperature is equal to
that energy times
a constant.
A constant is called
Boltzmann's
constant K, right?
So t is basically equal
to transition kinetic
energy, right?
Fine. Bear with me.
You'll see with
time, okay?
But the point
is that this is
kind of like lame to
stop here at U. I
want to go a little
bit further, right?
So some facts.
D is equal to the mass of
the substance involved for
an ideal gas
times a constant.
I'm just going to
call it C and give
it a little V. We'll
deal with that later.
N times dt, all right?
The units of CV here
have the units of
kilojoules per
kilogram per kelvin.
This is basically
a measure of if I
put some amount of
heat into a substance,
how much does this
temperature change?
It's very important,
and we're going
to we're going
to use it a lot.
So this applies
for ideal gas.
Alright. Alright, so if
we take this and
we put it to here,
what I can write is that
M times this
constant times
T two minus T one
is going to be equal to
negative Q out, all right?
And so now, with
that, right,
if we knew the mass,
which we're told,
if we knew the constant,
which I could
give you, okay?
And if we knew
the difference of
T minus T one,
we'd have to the
Q out, right?
So pretty much
until this point,
we've got our governing
equations good.
We've got how we're
going to get the solution,
and all we need to do now
is compute
properties, right?
That's the next stage
in our problem solution.
All right.
So how are we going
to compute the properties?
How do we compute
properties of an ideal gas?
Okay, I'll give
you that one.
So ideal gas
equation, right?
Idel gas equation,
all right?
So P vp1v1 is equal to,
which means the same.
R of air times
times T one.
We can put M to
the other side.
So we'll have P one.
Little V one is equal
to R air times T one.
This is not like
joules per mol Kelvin.
You can have these,
which are joules per
kilogram per
kelvin for, like,
all substances.
Alright? You can look
it up in your textbook.
Um Okay, we know P one,
we know T one,
we know R. We don't
know V one, right?
So the first step is
basically V one is R
A T one divided
by P one, right?
Cool. That's everything
for state one.
We have T one, we have
P one, we have V one.
Caput, all right?
Now we come to state two.
State two. What do we
know about state two?
What information is given?
Pressure, P two, okay?
So I can go p2v2 is
equal to R T two,
we'd like to find T two,
so T two is equal to
p2v2 divided
by R. So what don't
we know here?
R air, sorry.
R air, R air.
What don't we know on
the right hand side?
V two, similar or
identical, right?
So we know from from
over here, right?
This is little V two
is equal to little
V one, right?
Big V two is
equal to V V one.
The mass doesn't change.
Little V two is that.
And so what you'd
have here is then
V two, V one,
which we just
learned here,
divided by our air, okay?
With that, you have T two.
With then the T two,
you can plug it into here.
It's the negative
of the Q out,
but we can rewrite
this and say
the Q is equal
to the mass of
the air in the
control volume
times the constant
times T one,
which is the
hotter temperature
minus T two, okay?
And that's a
key part of it.
Because I've written
this as Q out,
this should just be a
positive number, right?
So if I did everything
right and I'm
doing a cooling
process, right,
I'd expect T two to be
lower than to T
one there, okay?
At least today, we got to
compute a temperature
in a heat, right?
Next time, you know,
we'll get a bit
further, right?
And then if you
click on this link,
you can go through some of
those numbers and see,
and that's what this
process looks like,
right?
And this is a straight
line up and down,
one to two on a
constant volume, okay?
With that, I'm
going to close.
I hope you all have
a great weekend.
I'm up here if you
have questions.