All right, I got 210.
So I'm going to
get started.
Today, we're going
to continue with
mass and energy analysis
to control volumes, okay?
So after today, you
should be able
to start solving
some of these energy
balance problems
for steady flow devices.
So the problems
basically in
Homework five there, okay?
Um Last lecture, we
derived flow work, right?
We talk about
flow work there,
just to remind you
what that was, right?
Imagine we have a
control volume,
defined here by the
dashed red line.
Let's say we have a
single inlet and we
have a single
outlet there.
At this inlet, let's
say we have some
specific volume,
a pressure, And we
can imagine then a
fictitious or an
imaginary piston, okay?
So we kind of, like,
push push this
in some amount.
That is an area and a move
a distance, that's
displacement, right?
And if there's a
pressure there,
there's a work associated
with that, okay?
What's the take
home message?
The take home message is
that sometimes it requires
work to bring a fluid
into a device, right?
Or alternatively,
maybe there's work
transferred out
from it, right?
And if we do our kind of
traditional energy
analysis where
we just talk about W,
that total W is going to
have that in
it, all right?
And so what we did
is we took out
the flow work from
the total work,
and we got, you know,
useful work and flow work,
and we basically
merged that flow work
with internal energy to
form what property?
Phenthropy.
Yes. I can go home.
I don't need to be
here today. Cool.
Yes, so we had
this, right?
And so what was
the way that
these fluids could
carry in energy, right?
Right? It can possess
internal energy,
it can possess
kinetic energy,
and it can possess
potential energy,
um, there, okay?
And we write that as like
little E. Just
to remind you,
this, you know, beautiful
equation, right?
The conservation of
energy written in
rate format where we
work with specific
enthalpy, right?
So we can write the
rate of change of
energy in the control
volume is the net heat
transferred in minus
the net useful work
transferred out.
M dot, right in
the enthalpy kinetic
energy potential,
that's in and then
basically out, right?
But the point is
that because we have
enthalpy internal
energy plus
pressure times
specific volume,
this is the useful.
On the other hand,
in this summation,
you go with
internal energy,
this is going to
be overall work.
And an example that
we did last week,
if you do the
overall work,
you're going to have
an answer that's off
by about like
20% there, okay?
So really with
steady flow devices,
so when you can bring
mass in and out
of the device, you know,
we're going to be working
with enthalpy only with
enthalpy changes
to figure out if
heats transferred is work
transferred and so on
and so forth, right?
Okay, and that's
what we'll work
on today. I'll
show that to you.
Um, Yes, right?
And so when we
talk about steady,
so when we talk about
steady in these processes,
steady didn't
mean, you know,
so when I talked
about steady here,
we were saying, I have
some control volume.
The change in the mass in
the control volume
as a function
of time was equal to m.in,
you know, minus, you know,
M dot out, right?
This is dm in dt minus
dm out. Right, dt.
And when we talked
about steady,
we don't mean that
all of these
terms are zero.
What we mean is that
this term goes
to zero, right?
So what does this imply?
DM in dt is equal to
dm out dt, right?
So I don't know,
the amount of mass then in
the control volume
does not change.
It's constant. And
the same applies
then for conservation
of energy.
So our conservation of
energy would then
be the rate of
change of energy in
the control volume, right?
Dt is equal to e.in
minus E dot out.
When it's steady, right,
this is zero, right?
And so then
basically D E in
dt is equal to
d out DT, okay?
And I think all
the examples I'm
going to work
on for the next couple
of lectures are going
to be for this.
I'll have one example
where I can show
you a process
that's unsteady,
and actually,
it's a problem
from some of the
research that we do, okay?
This case here
is one inlet in,
one inlet outlet or one
inlet and one outlet.
But you can also have
cases where you have
one inlet and two
outlets here, right?
One example of that is,
Sometimes you want to
separate like a stream.
You can have a stream
that's like a mixture of,
like, liquid and vapor.
Something like this
could be a separator.
Only vapor goes through
and then liquid,
you know, comes out
the bottom, right?
So that's a common thing.
But the point is that
it's still
conserved, right?
I could say, you
know, that's
still satisfied
in the sense of,
right, the m.in is
equal to the M dot out.
It's just that M
dot two plus M
dot three is going
to be equal to
M dot one there, okay?
Questions? This is
all very clear.
Cool. All right.
I forgot my water
today, so devastating.
Alright. So examples of
some devices, right?
So turbines, basically
how we still
produce most of our
power, propulsion.
So you think
about nozzles,
heat exchangers, you know,
compressors, and so
on and so forth.
These are all steady flow,
right, steady flow
devices, okay?
Just for
some terminologies,
for some notation.
So when we were where
to begin with this?
Um, Right?
So when we were
talking about our,
you know, conservation
of energy, right?
So if we think about
like our piston,
it's instructive I think
to think about
the piston here.
So the mass in this case,
right, with the
piston was equal to
a constant. So
that didn't vary.
The way that we wrote
the energy equation here,
right, was Delta E,
CV is equal to E
in minus E out.
The way that energy
can change here is
we can have Delta U plus
Delta E plus
Delta P, right?
And then this is
equal to the
ways that we can
transfer energy in
and out, right?
So this could be
Q in plus W in
minus Q out plus
W out, right?
Okay. I'll put
this to the side.
Now, what side should
I put this to?
All right. Maybe I'll
put this here and
bring this back.
Oh, okay.
So in the case of the,
um, you know, energy
transport by mass,
so we can, you
know, again, write,
uh, we have
two conservation
equations now, right?
So dm CV dt is equal
to what I would call.in
minus m dot out,
and then we have
our energy, right?
So d CV dt is equal to
e.in minus E dot
out. All right.
Um, Let's focus on
the right hand
side for a second.
So we think about
the way that we can
bring it in, right?
We still have our Q in.
We call it Q dot because
it's a rate, right?
We can still have w.in.
And now we have
the flow, right?
So here on this side,
we only had heat and work,
but now we can bring
in energy associated
with flow.
And then that's going
to be let's call
it dot I or.in.
And that'll be times,
the, uh, you know,
U plus PV, right,
plus velocity
squared divided
by two plus GZ, right?
And then this
is all applying
to the in case, right?
And then plus a
negative associated
with the out, right?
So Q dot out
plus w dot out,
plus dot, what should
we call it here?
We can call it M
dot O for out,
U plus PV plus W
squared divided
by two plus G Z.
And again, we
can call this as
like an out term.
So it's instructive
to basically
compare the right hand
sides that you have
here with the heat in the
work with here where you
have the rate versions
of heat and work transfer,
and then plus the
flow work term, okay?
Because I have the
PV written here,
what does this mean
about the work terms?
Go ahead, okay.
Second. Do you want
something else?
That's the
question I asked.
GZ, what do you think
GZ is G is what?
Not a wrapper.
Okay. So it's
gravity and then
what's Z? Or Z.
Yeah, height.
So basically it's
potential energy?
It's potential energy.
W right here I'm
writing is velocity,
it's kinetic energy
as we derived
it last time.
PV pressure is
pressure via
specific volume and U
is internal energy.
So what type of
work is this then for
a steady flow device?
I think I heard it,
right, hallucinated.
Shaft Shaft work,
right? This is
useful work here.
And it's a useful
work term, right?
And this U plus PV,
right is then internal
energy, okay?
And the point is, if
you read the book and
you look at it,
this U, right?
So basically,
maybe I'll do the
top one like this.
Now I can do it with
red. All right.
So if you see it in
the book, right,
you're going to see, um,
But essentially,
this term that
I've highlighted
here is what they define
as being little E,
right? Little E, okay?
So it's like internal
energy, kinetic energy,
potential energy on a
per mass basis, right?
That's essentially
what the
little literally is.
If you add to this also
the PV term, right?
So again, maybe I'll
take the Oca here,
then this is going to
be equal to what they
write as Theta, right?
So Theta is then little
E plus PV, okay?
Again, this is just to
make life easier in
terms of the math
because it can
get exhausting.
Um, You know, it can
get exhausting to
write that a bunch
of times, okay?
And then on the
left hand side,
you can still have the
same things, right?
So you can have, you know,
you can still have
internal energy,
the kinetic energy and
the potential energy
that's that's
stored there.
And we'll get into this
analysis next week.
So we'll get into how to
deal with the unsteady
case on Monday, okay?
Informational.
Okay. Yeah, so the
second important thing,
there was a student
who had raised this
to me before that you
can have cases, right?
So when we did, maybe it's
instructive to
come back to here.
So how do we write
the work term here?
So when we talk about
boundary work term,
what's the, let me
write it another way,
I can write basically.
So when we talk
about boundary work,
how do we write
it for like a
piston expansion
or compression?
PDV, right?
So you have PDV
like that, right?
Okay. In these processes,
so you think
like a turbine.
A turbine produces
a ton of work,
but it doesn't
change volume.
It doesn't change
volume. Okay?
How would you write
that work term?
Okay, let's think,
like, to the basics.
So what makes a fan blow?
Never had one of
those as a kid,
like the spinning wheel?
What do they call those?
The Oh, my God,
my brain today.
Pin wheel things,
right? You blow.
Okay? So what
does that mean?
Tanential but simpler.
I'm a kindergartener,
you know?
Yes. Okay. And
then a fluid,
how do we call
those constant
kinds of forces?
A steady flow or a
pressure, right?
Basically, I have
a higher pressure
in front of it than
I do behind it.
So I have a Delta P. And
I'm telling you that
the volume doesn't change.
So how would you write
work in that case?
It's dimensionally
the same, guys.
It's Friday, so
I'll give it to
you, all right?
But you can get
into, right?
You can have basically
a V and a DP, right?
So if I keep
that, you know,
if I basically
have the specific
volume that I know,
and it's a constant
volume there,
it's steady flow, so the
mass doesn't change.
So the volume is constant.
The mass doesn't change.
Specific volume is
the same, right?
So that means
that's a constant.
I right?
And so write this little W
just to, you know,
keep it like that.
Basically, it's a VDP.
You end up basically
with a VDP.
So it's PDV when
it's expansion.
And then when it's a
device like, you know,
our pinwheel there,
you'll end up with a VDP.
I think I saw a hand
raised on this side.
Yes, please.
Yeah, so energy,
unfortunately, is confusing.
Feinman, when he
used to teach,
said, like,
entropy was easy.
You're going to
learn entropy.
Not today, okay?
But energy was
hard because
there's all kinds of
forms of it, right?
So what you need to
do is you need to
start to classify,
right, in your mind.
So this is a boundary
work, right?
It's an expansion process.
You can call it
whatever you want.
Feinman was also
a fan of that.
Have it this name
and that name and
that it doesn't
matter, right?
This ps and expanding
is going to be a PDV term,
okay? We had other
kinds of work.
What's another way that
we had work transfer?
Remember this?
Electrical, right?
We have electrons
that can flow
in and transfer work
into the system, right?
I have a voltage and
I have a current.
The electrons flow in.
They kind of heat up
that resistor there,
and that energy is
transferred into
the control volume.
That's electrical
work, right?
So you have kind of a
W electrical there,
okay?
We had flow work,
you know, right?
So when we had this
open system and we
tried to bring the fluid
in, it was kind
of flow work.
It resembles, in a sense,
something like,
um, PDV here.
Actually, it was the
same, right? It's a PDV.
It's just that
in this case,
there's no real piston.
It's just like
this is the work
necessary to
actually bring
you into the system, okay?
So that was a flow you
know, a flow work term.
And then the
final one that
we've talked about so far,
I believe, is then
shaft work, okay?
So I would say boundary,
electrical, flow,
and shaft work are
probably most of the forms
of work that we'll deal
with in this class.
It's a good question.
Other questions?
Building on these.
Now, just the
front row today.
Cool. All right. Yeah, so
you can produce
work, right?
Remember before when we
had this case and it
was kept at constant
volume, right?
No work transfer
possible here.
However, when you if you
allow a fluid to
flow in, all right?
Again, just like your
pinwheel example,
if you allow a
fluid to flow in,
you can keep
your system at
constant volume and
produce work, all right?
And that has to
do with the fact
that there's a pressure
difference, right?
Basically, that
pressure difference
across the device
that's making it spin.
No different than
a wind turbine
and that, okay?
Yes, blah, blah, blah.
Yeah. And again, in order
to make this
the shaft work,
right, we need to separate
out the flow work, right?
Basically, we
got to take PV,
you know, out of out
of the work term,
bring it here,
and then write it
essentially in this
format, all right?
Cool. So with that,
I'm going to now actually
do some examples
because I feel like
it's a lot of
math and talking.
So I want to go through
and analyze this problem.
And then once we've
done that, I want
to throw it to you guys to
go through and
try to clarify
any misunderstandings
we have, all right?
Great. Have you been
recording? Yeah,
I have been.
All right. I'm probably
going to regret
erasing that.
Sorry. All right. That do.
This can go here.
All right,
so what do we have
in this example?
In this example,
we're looking
at analyzing a compressor.
Okay. So how does
the compressor work?
Compressor works by
taking we have
shaft works.
We have, like, a motor
that's spinning,
and it draws air in
or a gas in that's
at a higher a
specific volume
and compresses it, right?
So expectations out of
this device is that
at the end of this,
the pressure will
be basically
the pressure will be
higher. That's the goal.
It's basically the goal of
your of your
compressor. Okay?
Great.
And for those who want
to follow on, we can,
what I'm going to
assume is that we have
ideal gas
properties of air,
and here we're
going to neglect
kinetic and potential
energy changes.
As I mentioned
before, there will be
devices when we start
to care about this.
The one that's most
important is the
nozzle, right?
The nozzle that I
mentioned before, okay?
So like anything
else, at this point,
I'm just going to do
things with, like,
painfully detailed
and show you my
assumptions,
and as time goes on,
I'll skip through
those, right?
So we have two
conservation equations.
So the first is
our conservation
of mass, right?
So DM, CV, dt
or the control volume is
drawn here with our
dashed red line.
Is equal to m.in
minus m dot out.
We're going to
assume steady,
so we're going to
assume steady
operating conditions.
So what this
implies is that
dot N is equal
to m dot out,
which I'm usually
just going to write
as dot, okay, dot.
Now conservation
of energy, right,
DE CV dt so the change
in the energy in
the control volume
is equal to
e.in minus E dot out.
Again, we're going to
assume steady conditions.
So e.in is equal to
e dot out, right?
We can we can
separate this into its
different components.
So for the e.in, right,
I can have w.in plus
q.in plus dot, right?
So it will be m.in,
but I'm just writing
it as M dot.
I'm going to
write then H one.
So we're state one.
State one is defined here.
So I'm defining
this enthalpy
at state one here.
Plus velocity one squared
divided by two
plus G Z one,
where G is the
acceleration
constant due to gravity,
and Z one is then
position, okay?
And then this is equal
to exactly the same thing
here that I'm going
to write except
it's going to be out
and the number two.
So then what I
have here is W dot
out plus Q dot out plus M
dot times H two plus
W two squared divided
by two plus g z two.
What can we get rid of?
Name? Arturo.
So Connecticut
and Potential are out.
What else on this
side of the room?
You have a brave soul
in the back there?
No. Okay. Yes,
please, Maya?
Qn.
Q. Yeah, because we
don't have a Q in,
so Qn is out.
What else?
K workout, workout
is also not there.
Work in has to
remain because that's
the whole point, right?
We have some work
we're transferring in,
and that's ultimately what
we want to determine.
The dot is a given.
H one will determine
from properties.
Q dot out on a per
mass basis is given,
so I can redefine that.
The Q dot out here
is let me think
about this.
So Q dot out is
equal to m dot
times little Q out.
This is like a
definition, Q out
here is kilojoules
per kilogram,
mass fluorid is
kilogram per second.
So I multiply those
together kilowatts, right?
So what this means
is that we can
just write we can
substitute into this
term dot times Q out.
So both of those
things are known.
The dot is known,
and the tube will know
from from
properties, okay?
Cool. So we can
simplify this.
Let me just simplify
it. So what do we have?
We have w.in, is equal
to our M dot Q out.
What's on our
left hand side,
two plus dot times
that's H two, right?
And then this will be
subtracted by one.
And why does this
make sense, right?
Why does this
arrangement make sense?
So this arrangement
makes sense
because if I transfer
work in the system,
Uh, I would
expect, and again,
because I've written
this in notation,
this is going to be a
positive value, right?
This is positive values.
My expectation is
that the enthalpy
at the exit will
be higher than
the inlet, right?
Because I'm
putting work in.
If I'm going to
put energy in,
I would expect
that the thing
that also means
kind of energy,
you know, should basically
be larger than that.
If this wasn't the
case, if it was less,
then this would end up if
we forgot that
for a second,
if this was less
than H one,
then the work in would be
negative, which
means what?
Work out, right? Okay.
Because remember, when
I write ins and outs,
I'm not doing anything
with signs, right?
So if I write
in, I'm going to
stick with the magnitude
for that term, all right?
Super. All right.
So let's see
how I did it in
my um Notes
here that I do.
Yeah. Okay, so for
H two and H one,
we can do this two
different ways to start.
So for H two,
let's focus on
this for a second,
because we need to
know this is a
question mark,
and this is a question
mark, this we got,
this we got, this
we got, okay?
So for H two, all right,
we can focus on State two.
So at state two,
we know that P
two is equal to 600.
KPa, and we know
that T two is
equal to 500
Kelvin, right.
What this means
is if you went to
property tables or Pi
Kilo or whatever
and did it,
you have complete
information here, right?
So you'll be able
to determine H two,
V two, V two, right?
Like,
all these things you
could know from this.
We care at the
moment about H two.
The same for
state one, okay?
For state one, P one
is equal to 100 kPa.
All right. And T one is
equal to 290 kelvin.
It's the same
thing, right?
You'll be able
to know H one,
U one, and V
one from that.
For the purposes
of this problem,
we only care about
H one, okay?
Great. Yeah, so if
you go in and
you substitute
values for these things,
so we know, right,
the M dot So the
M dot there,
we have a 0.02
kilogram/second.
The Q out, we have as
one kilojoule
per kilogram.
If you substitute in,
you know, you click on
the notebook
and go through,
but substitute in
the values from H
one and H two,
that you'd have.
What I end up with
as my w.in in
watts is 4278 watts,
which is equal to
4.278 kilowatts, okay?
So this is one way
to do it, alright?
Maybe I will
move it to this.
What's the best
thing to do?
No, I'll keep this here,
and I'll move to
the left hand side.
What's another way
that we could do
this that might
seem easier?
I mean, I think this
is pretty easy.
I like this.
But what's another
way that I taught
you changes an enthalpy
for an ideal gas?
Okay.
So if I transfer
heat into something,
what changes?
The temperature.
Okay? All right?
When we did a
closed system
at constant volume,
and I transferred
some heat
into that, what
was that equal to?
So constant volume,
closed system.
Okay, right?
So we had Q is
CV, Delta T, right?
So Q is CV Delta T, right?
What I showed you
is because this is
isochoric for a
closed system,
there's no boundary
work, right?
And from the first law, if
I don't have any
work transfer,
d is going to be
equal to Q, right?
So then what we
could say, right,
was that CV was
equal to, um,
right, d, Oh, sorry.
Yeah, basically du dt
for constant V.
The point was
that changes in
temperature times CV
would give you changes
in internal energy.
All right? Does
anyone remember
an analogous formula
for enthalpy?
Louder.
Name high, and high,
and then a name.
Yes, please. Name? A Yes.
Or constant pressure.
And that's it,
right? So changes
in enthalpy can be
related to changes in
temperature by CP, okay?
All right.
And then for an
ideal gas, right,
the internal energy only
depends on temperature.
So the point is that for
a problem like this,
what you could do
is we could write H
two minus H one
as being equal
to Cp times T two
minus T one, right?
It's possible, okay?
So this is another
way to do it.
It's less precise than
looking up right exact
properties in this way.
But over the
temperature range
that we have here,
so 290 to 500,
probably taking a value
of specific heat at
room temperature
and multiplying
it by the Delta T
would get you within,
like, you know,
a couple of
percent of the
answer, okay?
Yes. And this is
like kind of the old
school way of doing it.
So when you see
in the textbook,
a lot of the stuff that
was done before with
enthalpy changes
of ideal gases
are usually specific heats
times temperature
differences.
I think nowadays with
electronic tables
and stuff,
these approaches like
this are just as
convenient as
doing that, okay?
Questions? That
all makes sense.
Cool.
So, since you have
no questions,
I'm sure this will be
a walk in the park.
So what I'm going
to give you here,
give me a second
I'll launch it.
But in short, you're given
an adiabatic
steam turbine.
What does adiabatic mean?
No. No heat. No heat
transfer, right?
So it's only
work transfer.
You're prescribed
the upstream state,
and you have the
downstream state.
And what I want
to know is what's
the rate of work
transferred out?
We'll continue with
this then on Monday.
I hope you have a great
weekend. Thank you.