PROFESSOR: Here's
what I want to do now.
We're going to apply this.
So here is your Carnot cycle,
again, showing you here.
So we have this
cyclical process, the A,
B, C, D, with the high
temperature being T1,
the low temperature being T2,
and the high entropy is S2,
and the low entropy as being S1.
There's a series of questions
where you go through and answer
about what each of these sort
of steps are and formulas to do.
So I say take five minutes here.
I have 10:34.
So let's say at 10:40, we'll
come back together in plenary.
Are there any questions about
this activity before we get
started?
Okay, let's go.
[LAUGHS]
Okay, so we look here.
So if we now start with A
to B, so the transformation.
So the majority is in for
isothermal, the reason
being that here A to B is a
constant temperature process.
So that is by definition
isothermal there.
If you have questions about the
adiabatic, we can discuss it.
But that's going to be,
I think, taken home here.
So in the in the B
to C, so with this
we have a process that's
isentropic, right?
So there's no change in entropy.
Entropy is constant.
Due to this relation between
the entropy and the heat,
you can infer from
that that that's also
an adiabatic process.
So there will be no heat
transfer that happens to here.
Isochoric is constant volume.
Isobaric is constant pressure.
C to D, again, it's the inverse
of A to B. So that's isothermal.
Remember constant temperature.
And D to A is again,
this is the link
between the entropy
and the heat transfer,
so that's an adiabatic process.
So these are like
heat in, heat out.
And then that's your various
work that's done on this system
or transferred out of it.
Okay, so what's the
change in entropy
during the
transformation to A to B?
So the first thing
to note is that we're
dealing with the reservoir
here at the at temperature 1.
And then this is going
to be heat transferred
into the system, right?
So we have S2 or SB
minus SA, so that's
going to be a positive
quantity here,
because that's bigger than that.
And so that's at the
T1, so that's there.
And the Q1 is how we write it.
So of course, here you'd
have the right magnitude,
but you'd end up
having the wrong sign.
So if you calculated this
minus this, that's positive.
And so write the
integral of that DQ2
for the constant temperature
then should be Q1 divided by T1,
and not dealing with
the Q2s and T2s.
C to D or B to C, so
if we go from B to C,
what's the change in entropy?
So that's again,
what you said before,
isentropic, so very good.
So that should be a 0.
Continuing along, C to
D, so with C to D here,
now we're taking heat
out of the system.
So again, in the power plant,
this is like our cooling.
We're sending this
to the cooling tower.
And all of this, this
is the low grade heat.
So that's at the temperature 2.
So your reservoir
is at temperature 2,
isothermal, so you would
be able to integrate that.
It's reversible, so the DQ
just becomes Q. So that's
the Q2 divided by T2.
The key thing to note
is that the entropy
after this process
minus the entropy
before is going to be negative.
So the signage here, you have
to be consistent with it.
But this would be Q2--
according to the convention we
have, this would be minus Q2
divided by T2 there.
Okay?
All right.
So one may make
arguments for this,
but again, you have to be
consistent with your signage
from your previous answer.
Okay, and then from D to
A here, so this is again,
an isentropic process,
which is adiabatic.
So then that should be 0 there.
So what is the net change
in entropy in the cycle?
So for those who
have put this here,
whoever wrote out the
word "zero," why is it 0?
STUDENT: Just based
on stage, right,
just start that at the
same [INDISCERNIBLE] 0.
PROFESSOR: Yeah,
that's exactly--
that's well-stated, again,
better than I said it.
So hey, they even wrote it.
Great, that's it.
So that's the-- that's
the point of that
is that if you start then you
stop at the same point there,
then the entropy
will be the same.
Of course, when we're dealing
with heat transferred in
and heat transferred out, those
are not necessarily the same.
Actually, in this
case, it's not.
So the net heat
transfer in, which
would be the difference between
the area under the top curve
and the area under
the bottom curve, we'd
have a net heat transfer in.
For this closed volume as
we're dealing with here,
that's going to be
equal to the work out.
So if we just simply
focus on the entropy,
though, as a classmate
said, it's going to be 0.
All right?
We'll have more chances to
work through this and probably
nice problems to ask from
other students who proposed.
Okay, are there any questions
about that before we move on?
Yes, please.
STUDENT: Can you use like those
given equations to find Q1?
Is that a true statement?
Is Q1 over T1 minus Q2 and
T2 equal 0, or is that not?
PROFESSOR: I'm not
saying it's not wrong.
Let's think about it.
So here you have
a Q1, which is--
is this a big number or a small
number relative to Q2 or to TQ2?
Yeah?
STUDENT: [INDISCERNIBLE].
PROFESSOR: It's big, right?
What about T1?
Is T1 a big number or a
small number relative to T2?
STUDENT: Big.
Big.
PROFESSOR: Big, right?
So I've got a big number
divided by a big number.
And now I have Q2 divided by T2.
So what is Q2--
a big number or a
small number relative?
STUDENT: Bigger.
PROFESSOR: Smaller, right?
And what about T2?
STUDENT: Smaller.
PROFESSOR: Smaller.
So now I got a small number
divided by a small number.
So big divided by big minus
small divided by small,
it might follow that that
ends up being also 0.
So it's not wrong.
I didn't say that
was wrong, did I?
So but yeah, maybe
that's worthwhile.
Also an example in the
homework to give that.
Okay, other
questions about this?
Yes, please?
STUDENT: Is this the Carnot
cycle just rewritten?
[INDISCERNIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Wait a second.
This is temperature
and entropy, right?
STUDENT: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, so
Carnot-- last week,
did we do something
with-- we did something
with pressure, right?
We did do a plot
with the p-V yeah.
So this is a representation
of what I showed you
with those adiabatic
and isothermal processes
in the p-V diagram, now
represented on the TS diagram.
Yes?
And hopefully you see
the convenience of it,
because it's like a square.
And these are really
easy to integrate.
[LAUGHS] Other questions?
Yes, please?
Thomas.
STUDENT: Are TS plus
isomorphic [INDISCERNIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Say that again.
STUDENT: Are TS plus
isomorphic to [INDISCERNIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Isomorphic,
describe isomorphic to me.
STUDENT: The 1 to 1
mapping [INDISCERNIBLE].
PROFESSOR: I mean,
1 to 1 mapping,
there's formulas that can
draw you between them.
Topologically they
look the same, right?
So I'd have to think about it.
That's a good question,
though again, that's a--
yeah, maybe that's a
nasty question to ask.
So other questions?
All right.
Let's talk about it in
office hours, Thomas.
Exactly.
So now, again, as was explicitly
alluded to by the classmate,
so the heat absorbed
by the system--
so again, the shaded area
that would be within here
is the Q, which is
equal to Q1 minus Q2.
So heat transferred from
the high temperature
and heat transferred out by the
low temperature gives you the Q.
So since the work
done on one of these
closed volume cycles
is equal to the heat
in is equal to work out,
well, what we can write
is that that work is then equal
to the shaded area, right?
So that's going to be S2, S1.
So the rectangle, one
length is S2 minus S1,
the other length is T1 minus T2.
So that gives you
the work there.
If you recall, for the
isothermal process--
so remember, we integrated
that DQ divided by T,
so the T is isothermal.
So that doesn't change
with the integral.
The little d in
dQ can be written
as a definite differential.
So then we get Q1 is equal to T1
times the change in the entropy
from state 2 to state 1.
If we now take the
work transferred out
divided by the heat transferred
in from that high temperature
reservoir, this is
efficiency, okay?
Why?
Because that heat that we
put in is like the stuff
that we pay for, right?
At the moment you pay
for fuel that you burn,
that makes that heat, that
runs your power plant, that
makes your shaft work there.
So that's what you get out.
That's what you put in.
If we write that--
again, for this, if the heat
is transferred in isothermally,
then we can write that.
This cancels.
And so what you have
here is 1 minus the ratio
of the low temperature reservoir
divided by the high temperature
reservoir is the efficiency
of a Carnot cycle.
So what's weird
about this equation?
Okay.
STUDENT: [INDISCERNIBLE].
PROFESSOR: That's
excellent insight.
So if you have a high
temperature reservoir,
you will have a more
efficient system.
If you're low temperature
reservoir is colder,
you will also have a
more efficient system.
So on the absolute scale,
remember, on the absolute scale.
What's the other
thing that's kind
of weird about this equation?
Thomas?
STUDENT: It's only
temperature dependent.
PROFESSOR: Say that again.
STUDENT: It's only
temperature dependent.
PROFESSOR: It's only
I didn't say anything
about a fluid.
I didn't even say
really much about how
this system would work.
We did all of this math, like
there was all this complex stuff
on the board and
we got to there.
And then in the end,
that's your formula.
So in a Carnot cycle-- so again,
this idealized, reversible cycle
there, in the end, it's
only the temperature
of the reservoirs that
determine the efficiency
of the system, which is
also kind of interesting.
Okay.
So I'm not going to read it,
but this is Carnot's theorem.
So as we stated it, as
Thomas just said there,
so that's the theorem.
So it doesn't depend on
the working substance.
It's only dependent--
the efficiency
is only dependent on the
two operating temperatures.
And so with that, that's
these first two points.
What I'd like to do now
with the last six minutes
is to at least start giving
you the knowledge base
to answer the question
from your classmate there,
which is to establish the
increase of entropy principle.
So I'm just going to
give you a statement.
So things are more likely to
occur in an isolated system
if the change in
entropy there is 0,
or if the change is to increase?
So we talked about
taking these two
things at different
temperatures,
putting them
together to analyze.
Then if those things are going
to come to the same temperature,
the transformation, if that's
what we hypothesize to happen,
then this statement
would have to be true.
Okay?
And this inequality
holds, so not the equals.
The inequality holds if the
isolated system is not initially
at equilibrium.
So if it initially, like
in the example there,
we have two things with
different temperatures,
we suddenly bring them together,
they are not in equilibrium,
they will tend towards
equilibrium there.
So then the most
probable processes
that might occur in
an isolated system
are those in which the entropy
increases or remains constant.
I could derive this for you.
But for that, we need
statistical mechanics.
There's a great video on
MIT, Professor Lenhart,
who sort of goes into it.
I thought what might
be more instructive is
to come back to this
video that we had before.
So in the video we had
before, we did this experiment
with heat transfer.
We had one reservoir
with particles
at a lower temperature,
another one of them that
was at higher temperatures.
And we looked at the
direction that things moved.
All right.
So as a function of
time, what we had noticed
was that the things that were
at the higher temperature
tended to diffuse towards the
things at the lower temperature.
So there was a net heat
transfer in this case
that I'm showing here
from right to left.
And the question I
want to ask from this
is, so you're watching
this going forward.
And one way to
think about entropy
is to think, okay, what if I
saw this as my initial state
and I tried to rewind?
All right, so you see this.
What is the probability--
an experimentalist
doing-- what's
the probability that if
you waited long enough
that these things would
spontaneously go back
to being all cold and all hot?
STUDENT: 0.
PROFESSOR: I mean,
it's not 0, but it's
like in an engineering
sense, it's 0.
All right?
It's very, very unlikely.
Okay?
This is also-- have
you ever thought
about why time has a direction?
Entropy.
Why the universe
is going to end?
Entropy.
All right?
[LAUGHS]
The thing is that it
can decrease, though.
So if I take a system that's not
isolated-- so if I take, again,
maybe with the example that was
put before, if I have a box,
I can of course transfer
heat out of that.
So the entropy within
that box will decrease.
But the total entropy for
all the systems involved--
SO I'm transferring
out, this has
to be transferred somewhere
else into the environment.
So the delta S1
plus the delta S2
has always got to be
equal or greater than 0.
So the importance
of the second law
is it tells you what things
can happen, will occur.
All right?
And you know, we need to--
in order to describe that,
the first law, we talk about
the conservation of energy.
There are processes, like I
said before, this unwinding
where things can go backwards.
They comply with the
conservation of energy,
then take particles
out and all that.
But they're improbable because
they violate this second law.
And this is going to be
important for you going forward
in your engineering education is
that this principle of increase
in entropy, along with
conservation of energy, mass,
momentum, they're the basic
rules that govern the universe.
So there's some, there's
like-- this is actual,
honest to god truth that
you are seeing today.
When you get into
fluid mechanics,
you're going to be dealing
with conservation of mass
and conservation of momentum.
When you get into
heat transfer there,
you're going to be dealing with
conservation of mass, momentum,
and energy.
All right?
And to tell you, let's say, in
something with heat transfer,
if things are going to
move spontaneously and flow
from one direction to the
other, that second law.
Things move from regions
of high concentration
to low concentration.
All right?
Again, when you're the party
and talking to your friends,
you can say that.
I'd go through this.
I'm out of time.
I'll just leave
you with a quote.
So Rudolf Clausius,
this is what he
wrote as the first and
second laws of thermo.
So this is in German.
The first is that the energy
of the universe is constant,
and the entropy of the universe
strives towards a maximum.
Okay?
So with that, you have
the increase of entropy.