Alright, I got 210. I'm
going to get started.
So today we're talking
about steady flow
energy analysis again.
So far we've done
compressors and turbine.
Today we'll work
on throttling
and heat exchangers,
if time permits,
I'll also either
start or hopefully
completely finish an
unsteady flow process
that's actually
relevant for
some applications
in research, okay?
Exactly. So we can
start with this.
So we'll look
at this system.
This is does anyone
know what this is?
Air conditioner,
refrigerator.
Yeah. Essentially, here,
what you have is
a compressor that
takes a fluid,
usually a refrigerant
transfers
work into it, right?
Creates a higher
pressure forces
this refrigerant to
condense, right?
So you go from this
vapor to the liquid.
You get a lot of heat,
right, that's
transferred out of it.
So this is in
the fridge right
in the back of it.
You'll see typically
like a you know,
a heat exchanger and a lot
of warmth coming
off of it.
Out of that, then, right,
we have an
expansion valve.
So this is something
that goes from
very high pressure
to low pressure.
Essentially, you get
the liquid ready
to evaporate,
which is then what happens
in the evaporator.
And then this is where
it cools, right?
So he transferred,
for example,
into a fridge, right,
that keeps the
inside of it cool.
Or if it's a Right.
An air conditioning
unit, right?
That's when you
would pass air over
to then cool the
building and then loop.
Key aspects to this
system in solving
it, right?
We'll go through
this today,
but essentially
heat exchangers.
For the purposes
of this class,
we assume that
there's, like,
no pressure drop
across them, right?
We can get into, you
know, validity of that.
But essentially, we assume
these are
isobaric devices.
Right the compressor.
We'll analyze some of
that you know,
a bit later.
Again, a heat exchanger.
And then the
expansion valve,
what we'll get
into is that
this is an isenthalpic,
an isenthalpic process.
What does it look like?
So in order for this to be
an isenthalpic process,
it means, right,
we don't have any
heat transfer,
work transfer.
So work transfer is
pretty straightforward,
right?
We have a control volume
that has constant volume,
nothing spinning in
there to transfer work.
To make it be adiabatic,
so basically no
heat transfer,
what do you think
you would do?
Insulated?
Insulated. Yeah, you
basically insulate it
or make it very small.
So insulating make
it very small,
then makes it do that.
So these are typically
then, like, you know,
a very small orifice plate
that you would have
there or a porous plug.
But under these
conditions,
you can treat
the process as
isomthalic, okay?
And that temperature
decrease
effect, if you want
to read about that,
that's the so called Jewel
Thompson Jewel
Thompson effect.
So when you get
a big expansion,
then in the fluid, there's
a corresponding cooling
that goes with it.
Okay? So what does
it look like if
you were to try
to represent
this on a diagrams?
Remember we talked
before about All right,
PV diagrams, a lot
of PV diagrams.
For air conditioning
processes
or refrigerator
stuff there,
it's also common to see
this represented on
a so called pressure
pH diagram or
pressure enthalpy
diagram, right?
So, this would be
like the entrance,
you know, out of the
condenser, right?
So you're a
saturated liquid
at some higher pressure,
and then you have a
nice enthalpic process
which then reduces
your pressure,
keeps these specific
enthalpy constant,
and you end up
here, right?
So you go from
essentially being
a saturated liquid to
something that's
a mixture, right?
So you get it there.
Alright, so
we'll go through
that example of what
that looks like.
And again, this
is only then
one leg of what
otherwise would
be what otherwise
would be a cycle,
right, a cycle there.
So the refrigerator
we're working
with in this is R 134 A.
Okay. You'll see R is
like a designation.
R just means
refrigerant, right?
So C R 134 A. Pi color
can handle this.
Your book tables also have
this tabulated
there, okay?
And to be consistent
with the notation
that I had before,
so the process we
want to analyze
is this three to four,
which we call as
throttling, okay?
Um, right?
So that's what we're
doing. So we
have our fluid.
We're looking
at throttling.
We know that we have
P three defined,
and we also have
X three, right?
Let's see. So based
on that, right,
we know it.
What is X three,
based on what I
showed you there?
Numerically is a value.
It could only be 0-1.
So I guess that's a lot
of numbers that
it could be,
or it could be very few.
It's not one. Zero.
Okay. Why is it zero?
Saturated liquid, right?
It's a saturated liquid.
It comes out of
a condenser.
A condenser
condenses, right?
And so you basically leave
as a saturated liquid
out of your condenser.
And, you have this P
three as a pressure.
This P three is
equal to P two
because that's out of
the compressor, right?
So there's no
pressure drop
across the heat
exchanger, right?
So with this, right,
we have complete
information.
We know, for
example, H three,
but we would also
know T three, right?
If you use Pi Klor
or your tables,
right, you could
look that up.
The other thing that's
given in this problem is
we're told that
we know P four.
So we know the pressure
that's what we
call downstream,
basically after
the device, right?
So if we were to
analyze this,
so if I just looked only
at the throttling process.
So let's say I
have something
here with a
very tiny hole.
This is then let's say
upstream in state three.
Our fluids flowing
in like that.
And basically
downstream, we have
um basically have
state four, okay?
And the control
volume that we're
interested in analyzing
here is then around,
right around this
throttling device, okay?
Our assumptions that
we had before, right,
is that we had no right?
We have no heat
transfer, okay?
We call it adiabatic,
and there's no work
transfer, right?
So we have no work
transfer here, okay?
And it's a steady
flow device,
so we can look right
our two conservation
equations,
our conservation
of mass and
of energy.
So this is our CV or
control volume, right?
So the DM CV,
dt is equal to m.in
minus Rm dot out.
And the same then
for the change
in the energy
of our control
volume is equal to
e.in minus R E dot out.
We're going to assume
that this is steady.
Basically, it's a steady,
a steady flow here.
Okay, so it's not
So a steady flow.
So in this case,
right, this
is going to be
going to zero,
and then this basically
goes to zero, right?
And so what this
means is that m.in,
m.in is equal
to M dot out,
and I'm just going
to call this
as dot, right?
And this implies that e.in
is equal to E dot out.
So what's another
assumption
you think we're
going to have here?
Before I start writing
the energy equation.
Exactly. So we're
going to be
neglecting neglect,
KE and PE.
So we're going to neglect
kinetic and potential
energies, right?
So if we write our
energy equation, right?
So building on
that, so our e.in,
so the ways that we can
transfer energy in, right?
We're going to have W
in plus q.in plus m.in,
which I'm just going to
call as m dot, right?
And then this would be
times, in our case,
H three plus, right,
we'd have W
three, which is
our velocity
squared by two.
Plus GZ three,
and that's equal
to our W dot out plus Q
dot out plus dot
times H four plus
W four squared
divided by two,
again, velocity plus G,
which is the acceleration
due to gravity,
Z four there, okay?
So we're neglecting
kinetic and
potential energies.
SC, sac, sac, sac, gone.
We said it was
adiabatic, gone, gone.
And we said no work
transfer, gone and gone.
Okay? All right.
And these m.in and the M
dot out are both dots.
So that means that gone
and gone. All right?
So from this, what
you see is that H
three is equal to
H four, all right?
Ice, fall, big, okay?
And isobaric, isothermal.
Here's another ISO, okay?
I think there's also
a defense that's ISO.
I don't know how
that works, though.
All right?
Cool. All right,
that's basketball.
Yeah, exactly. You
go ISO on someone.
Alright, so basically
a three is a four,
and that's your omthopic.
And we can use
this, right?
So if we look
at our Right,
if we look at the
board here, right?
So we know our
upstream condition.
We knew P four,
but we needed one
other piece of
information to
determine the
downstream state,
okay?
And so by knowing that
H three is H four,
our state four Right?
We now know our P,
we basically know P four,
and we now know
that H four
is equal to H
three, right?
So essentially from this,
right, we have
complete information.
We can then
determine things
like T four, right?
T four there, okay,
which is what we're
interested in.
Remember what
I said to the
whole point of, um,
right of this device
here is that we want
to get this thing ready to
evaporate right at
a cold temperature.
So through this
throttling process,
we're able to drop
the temperature.
So again, by having
this date with T four,
right,
we're going to determine,
right, essentially,
Delta T is then
equal to our T
three minus R T four.
Okay. Great. What else?
Um Yes.
So just to give you some
values that we have.
I mean, I know
you can see it's
roughly on the board here.
But I'm going just write
this as state one.
So with our state one,
What I have is I
have P one here,
which is equal to
0.14 MPA, okay?
And I have a Oh,
I'm sorry, I
don't want T one.
Apologies. I
What I want is
give me a second.
Apologies. I want
state three, right?
So for our state three,
S three pressure
for, like,
basically these pretty
realistic operating
conditions,
we have 0.8 MPA.
That's about eight times
atmospheric pressure.
Eight bar and,
you know, there.
So that's basically
a pretty reasonable
pressure.
And then, as I mentioned
before, X three,
as you all pointed out,
was then equal to zero.
So those are values
that we had.
The P four that
we have here.
So the pressure drop
that you experience across
the throttling device
is then 0.15 MPA.
Okay, so about 1.5
times atmospheric
pressure. All right.
A typical flow rate
that's then given here,
which is also given
into the problem
is that we have
an M dot here.
So this M dot
get rid of that.
So the M dot that
we have here is
equal to 0.05
kilograms/second.
Remember, the MDOT in
is the M dot out is
the M dot, there, okay?
And so if we use all of
this and we determine
our states,
what you'll have is
then a Delta T here.
So a cooling, pretty
significant cooling of
about 48 degrees Kelvin,
right, which is
also because
it's a Delta, right?
It's 48 degrees
Celsius, right?
That's how much
of a temperature
change you're
going to have from
this state here down to
this state this
state here, okay?
Because we have
complete information,
we can also
determine things
like specific
volume, right?
So we can have
V three here,
and we can have
V four, okay?
And so if we go then
with the Delta V as
being V three
minus RV four,
this is then
going to be equal
to a negative 0.040
9 meters cubed
per kilogram.
Why is it negative?
It's Yes, please. Okay?
Decreases.
So it decreases,
but what decreases?
Yeah, so your
specific vome,
what does it mean?
Are you more like
a liquid or
you're more like
a vapor when the
Delta V is negative.
You're more like
a vapor, right?
You're basically,
again, you're getting
ready to evaporate.
And that also makes
sense because
if you were to analyze
the process here,
we end up somewhere
below the dome, right?
So you're
intermediate between,
you know, you're no
longer just a
liquid, right?
You're somewhere
between the liquid
and the vapor
and the liquid.
And when you're a
vapor, you have
a higher specific volume
than when you're
a liquid, okay?
All right? We
can also look
at the pressure drops.
I mean, obviously, we
have we would know
that from the beginning
because it was given.
But yeah, you're
going to have
something like
a seven bar,
seven bar of a
pressure drop.
And you can also compare.
It's instructive.
If you go back and look at
the definition of enthalpy
and actually what's
going on here.
It's instructive to
look at the difference
in internal energy, right?
So U three, um,
minus U four,
and that's equal to 5.587
kilojoules per
kilogram, right?
So if we think
about enthalpy,
so the enthalpy
doesn't change.
Enthalpy is by definition,
U plus is enthalpy
is U plus,
um, uh, PV, right?
So here, it says to
be a constant value.
So here what I'm telling
you, is that right,
the internal
energy at State
four is essentially less,
right, than the
internal energy
at State three, okay?
And so what do you
think is the
consequence of that?
If I have less internal
energy downstream
than I have upstream,
what do you think a
consequence of that is?
Temperature, right?
So the whole point
is that that's where
you see it, right?
Because, you know,
the P, right?
So downstream, the
pressure goes down.
The specific volume is
basically going up.
But the net effect
here is that the
internal energy is down,
right?
All of these things
work together to
keep this as a
constant value.
But the thing you
care about is that
the internal energy,
essentially,
you know, the temperature,
as you see it here,
decreases when you drop
across that device, okay?
So it's a humble device,
but it's an important
device, okay?
Right? 50% of the
electricity consumption
in this country
looks like that in
the summer, right?
Okay. Yes, please?
So it's interesting.
Where do you
see on this device
the temperature
being raised?
And so my reply
would be a question.
What's one way that
you think that
could happen
through a valve?
I mean, one way is
you just have a lot
of friction, right?
If I want to warm
something up, that's
pretty easy Actually
what's much more
challenging
usually is to cool
something down.
Other questions?
All clear? Great. I
love the thumbs up.
I appreciate feedback
from the crowd.
Okay. Yeah, so
we're going to do a
lot more with this.
We'll get more into that.
If you want to see
what throttling
looks like, this
is like a video.
So in this experiment,
what you're going
to see is upstream,
I have very high pressure.
I have a high
pressure refrigerant.
This refrigerant
is not R 134 A.
This refrigerant is
carbon dioxide, okay?
And what I'm doing is
I have a very tiny,
hole in it's orifice
plate, right?
Like I mentioned here,
it's a couple of
millimeters or a
millimeter or so,
I think, in diameter.
And then to the
right here,
this is open air, right?
So basically
low pressure is
about 1 bar, okay?
So I have something
that's like, you know,
40 or 50 times
atmospheric pressure
going to something
that's like one,
you know,
which is basically
atmospheric pressure.
And what you'll
see, right,
is essentially
you get like
a condensed phase
that's there, okay?
And it's very cold, right?
So if you put basically
a thermocouple in there,
it would be very
cold. Um, Yeah.
Has anyone ever seen
an experiment like
that done before?
Have you ever seen a
fire extinguisher?
That's what it is, right?
A fire extinguisher is
the same principle.
I have high pressure
carbon dioxide
that's there
in the bottle,
and I relieve it, right?
So I get a big cooling
effect that expansion,
so called Jewel
Thompson effect there.
So it lowers the
temperature a lot.
And for the case
of the fire,
and it lowers it
really a lot.
Like the temperature here,
you see this frost.
Like this is so
cold that I have,
like, you know,
very thick layer of ice
that's forming on it.
This will basically
go down to, like,
-70 Celsius,
which is essentially
the temperature
of dry ice.
That's also why you
never pick up dry ice
with your hands
because you will burn.
I mean, it will not feel
very pleasant to you.
So, this can basically
get very, very cold,
so that can help
with, you know,
from a temperature effect
of putting a fire out.
But the second part is,
obviously, you just
extinguish you
suffocate, right?
Don't allow any oxygen
to go to it, okay?
Cool. All right, so
that's throttling.
Continuing with the
device that I presented.
What I want to go
through now is
the heat exchanger
component of the device.
Not exactly the
same conditions,
as I said, for
running the
refrigeration cycle,
but it's going
to be helpful.
I'm going to show
you some of the tips
and tricks then
that we use
then for analyzing
a heat exchanger.
Let me just
erase the board.
Okay.
Cool. So what do we have?
So we have here,
R 134 A, again,
which is a common
refrigerant.
We're entering, right?
So we have R 134
A again, 134 A.
We have an M
dot of R 134 A,
R 134 A, which is
equal to 6
kilograms/minute.
Um It enters as a vapor.
So when we look
at the R 134,
I think we'll wait for
the properties
in a second.
We we neglect pressure
drops in that.
Let's start talking
about some states.
So if I have state three
as it's defined
here, okay?
One piece of
information that
I see with state three.
So it enters as a vapor.
Vapor, but it doesn't
say saturated vapor.
And the other part that I
see here is for
state three,
I'm giving two pieces
of information.
So I can put this
in and determine
properties.
The thing you need
to check, right,
when you do that
analysis is that this
is actually a
vapor, right?
You can see what
type of vapor
that that it is.
If it's a
superheated vapor,
this is enough
information.
It could also be with
these conditions that
it's also a
saturated vapor.
What I'm going to
assume based on
this is that
it's a superheated vapor.
So we have a T
there, T three,
which is 70 degrees C,
and I have a P
three, which is then
equal to 1 megapascal.
Okay? All right. And
presumably with this,
we have subject to
verification, right?
We have basically enthal P
three, which
we care about.
Okay? Now we exit, right?
We exit from here
to state four.
All right. And
in state four,
we're only given
the temperature.
So we have T four,
which is 35 degrees
C. And what we're
told is that
it's sub cooled.
So basically,
we're told sub
cooled um liquid.
What do you think we
do here? What would
be like your
first reaction?
I'm told this temperature
and I'm told
subcooled liquid,
what would you do with
this information if you
wanted to get a property?
X equals zero,
right? Yeah.
So essentially, for now,
we'll start with
and say X four
is equal to zero, okay?
All right, so,
essentially what
you're saying is that
the properties
of the liquid
when it's sub
cooled to this
are not very different to
the state when it's
a saturated liquid, right?
And if you read the
textbook, old school,
like if you went
to the tables
the property
tables in a book,
this information
would normally
not be given, right?
You would not have
subcooled liquid
properties,
which you'd be given
as essentially
a saturated liquid.
What is the other
thing that I
said about a heat
exchanger, though?
At the beginning.
What property
doesn't change
across the heat
exchanger in this class?
Pressure, right? So
the other way to
look at this would
just be to say,
so that's an
approximation.
Another way to
look at this is
to say that I'm
going to go with
my pressure and say that P
four is equal then
to P three. And it
is instructive.
I won't do it
now, but it's
instructive for you
to compare the values
when you do T
four and X four equals
zero and determine
H four or to do T four and
P four equals to P
three and also determine
an H four, okay?
What you see is
that they're
not that different, okay?
All right. That's
very good.
So we have this
with State three.
We basically have
two approaches
when we look at
State four and on
an exam or something
like that.
Again, as long as
you justify for me,
I thought this,
I did this,
that's perfectly
acceptable, okay?
So if you look at
this and you make
a judgment call that
this is the right way,
do that, but
write that, okay?
Give me a reason.
All right.
So those are State
three and State four.
I'm pretty sure
we have that
done also with the
mass flow rate.
I feel pretty
comfortable with that.
We're going to
be able with
that to determine
then the heat
transferred out of
the refrigerant.
Let's focus for
a second now at
state at state one.
So if we go to
state One here.
All right. So
we have water.
That's at T one and equal
to 15 degrees Celsius.
And we're told that
P one is equal to
300 pa so three times
atmospheric pressure.
And then at state.
And so with this,
it's very likely there
is a pretty high pressure.
It's a pretty
low temperature.
With this, you're going
to be able to have H one.
It's going to be like
a subcooled liquid there.
You're going to be
able to get H one.
And then for state
two, All right,
State two. All right.
What we have there is
we have T two is equal
to 25 degrees
C. And what's the
other property?
Pressure.
Pressure is what?
Thank you, Kai.
Okay. So then
P two is then
equal to P one,
which is equal to
300 pa. All right.
P two, P two.
Let me just check
my assumptions
here. Yeah, so
this is good.
I have that.
You have T two,
right? So that's
getting warmer.
That makes sense.
So this all
looks good to me.
Let me just check on
my refrigeration side.
T three, which
was 70, P three,
which is one MPA, T
four. Yeah. So in my.
So again, this is
one way that you
can do it in my,
um, In my solution
that you can
launch from there,
I've gone this way, right?
So I've assumed
that it's isoberic.
So the pressure three
that's given is equal
to pressure four,
and I've gone with T four
to determine H four.
If you want to do
it old school,
and by the book, you have
to remember this
trick, right?
So this is book, okay?
And then this is
Pi Klor, okay.
All right, so
we got a handle
on the states now, right?
So from this, right,
I'm going to be
able to have H two.
And so what we've
got to know is
we want to know
the mass flow rate of
the cooling water and
the heat transfer
rate from
the refrigerant to
the water, all right?
So now, again, I'm not
going to, you know,
what I have drawn there in
the control volume is
right, the entire thing.
What I'd like to
do at the moment
now is to break that down
into two separate control
volumes, which I'll do.
So let me do my best
to draw a serpentine pipe.
Okay. That's horrible.
Okay. All right.
So, so into the pipe here,
we have state
three coming in.
We have State
four exiting,
and I'm drawing my
control volume exactly
around the pipe.
All right.
Okay.
Let's call this, for
example, CV 34, okay?
All right, CV 34
corresponding to
the states, right?
We can write our
conservation equations,
right?
So the rate of
change of mass in
CV 34 dt is equal to
m.in minus M dot
out of CV 34. Okay.
We're going to
assume, right,
this is a steady
flow device.
So if we assume it's
a steady flow, well,
we can call then.in of
CV 34 is equal to M
dot out of CV 34.
And what I would like to
call that is just m.r1,
three, four, A, okay?
So we're good
there, right?
Now we're going to write
our energy equation,
the same thing, right?
So D E, CV, three, four,
dt is equal to e.in minus
E dot out of CV 34.
Steady flow. This
is gone, right?
So what comes
in here is to
equal to what exits, okay?
Um, So we can write that.
So what enters energy
can be carried in
from work, right?
So I can have w dot
plus q.in plus dot, um,
dot R one, three,
four A times three plus
w squared divided by
two plus G three,
and that's equal
to W dot out.
Okay, plus Q
dot out plus.r1
34ah four plus velocity
four squared divided by
two plus the
potential energy
at state four, right?
Okay, what are we
going to neglect here?
Neglect KE and PE.
So this means gone,
gone, gone, and gone.
All right. One.
What about work?
Do you see
anything spinning?
No, right? So there's
no work transfer
here, no work.
Okay. Well, yeah,
no shaft work here,
right? So we
have no shaft.
Let me see there
no shaft work.
All right. All right.
So these are gone.
And what about heat?
Do we have any heat
transferred in or heat
transferred out 3-4? Loud.
N and loud here.
This side of the room.
Someone not
named Kai? Okay.
Cody.
If you transfer
it out, right?
So basically, we
don't have it in,
and we have it
out right because
the temperature
is lower, right?
So we can do then
from this is we
can determine that
our Q dot out, right?
So the heat
transfer rate from
the refrigerant to
the water then here.
So Q dot out is
equal to m.r1 34 A,
which is given
times H three,
which we know minus
H four, okay?
So basically
we've answered
part B already there.
So this is good. So
answer Good. All right.
All right, now let's draw
our control volume
in for our water.
So if we look
at the water,
okay. There's the water.
Okay, I have it
coming in here,
right? And out here.
So this is state
state one here.
We have state two here.
Let's draw control volume.
So here's the
control volume that
I am going to
attempt to draw because
it's going to
get complicated.
So the other point is
that I have this pipe,
this serpentine pipe,
which is right.
Okay, which is
going there.
And so when I draw
this control volume,
I want to draw around
this pipe, right?
I only want to have
the parts that
are that are water
there, okay?
Difficult to represent
in two dimensions.
This is kind of
a mess, okay?
So, you know, basically,
everything but the
pipe here is what I'm
drawing the
control volume of.
Right? The same
thing, right?
So conservation of
mass, it's steady.
So we have, right,
m.in is equal
to M dot out.
Rate of h2o.
Or let's say we can call
this then as CV 12
to be consistent.
So CV one, two, CV 12.
And what I would
like to just call
this is maybe.h2o, right?
So that's the
mass flow rate of
the cooling water, which
is what we're trying
to determine.
So that's one conservation
of energy, right?
So we neglect kinetic
and potential energies.
We have no work transfer.
So what we'll
have then is for
the energy transferred
in, right?
So we'll have
q.in plus.h2o.
What's the inlet?
The inlet is H one.
Okay, and that's
equal to It's Q dot,
Q dot out plus m dot O.
All right. And then that's
the enthalpy
that's leaving,
right? That's two, right?
So I don't have
work, no kinetic,
no potential energy.
And now we have to
deal with the heat.
So do we have q.in
or Q dot out here?
Say it again.
Q.in your name?
Had Hayden, q.in, right?
So we don't
have Q dot out.
We have heap transferred
that makes sense, right?
The water is leaving
hotter than here.
What's the other
assumption
for this whole
analysis to work?
What's the other
assumption I have to
make about my water
control volume?
So I'm saying that
there's q.in, right?
But q.in could come
from the refrigerant,
but it could also come
from the
environment, right?
So what's the
other assumption
I need to make?
It's insulated.
Basically it's
adiabatic, right?
So basically on the
outside of this, right?
So we assume that this is,
this is basically
an insulated
thermally insulated
there, okay?
So we do have q.in, but
it's not from the
surroundings, right?
So it's coming in
from from that.
So we have q.in
then is equal to
m.h2o times the enthalpy
at state two minus
the enthalpy
at state one, okay?
All right. So if I want to
get to so I know H two,
I know one, okay?
I want to find dot HO.
I don't know q.in.
I do know all
of this, right?
So I know Q dot out.
What is, like, a matching
criteria you think has to
happen for this system
to work? Q plus.
That's it, right?
So basically, the q.in,
which I'll make it clear.
I'll call this
as q.in h2o,
must be equal to the Q dot
out of RR 134 A, right?
They what we
would call, what
I call this CV one, two,
right, is equal
to then, right,
the CV 34, okay?
So there's no energy
exchange with
the environment.
There's only
energy exchange
that's happening
within it,
heat exchanger. All right?
So the heat is
exchanged then.
If it's done right,
then within it.
Okay.
That's very good.
So if we set
these things equal
to each other,
so I'll have.h2o is
equal to I'm sorry.
So, sorry, sorry.
M.h2o times H
two minus H one is
equal to m.r1 34 a.
And that's times. So
where's our thing,
H three, minus R H four,
just do a sanity check.
So the cooling
water should
be hotter leaving, right?
So that enthalpy should
be greater than the inlet.
And the R 34 A
is entering hot and
getting colder, right?
So this enthalpy entering
will be greater than that.
Both these things then
are positive values.
And so if we
divide both sides
by H two minus H one,
we're going to
have.h2o is equal
to.r1 34 a, okay?
And that's times H three,
minus H four, and that's
divided by H two
minus H one, okay?
And then that's the other
formula that we
need, right?
And we know all
this information.
We know one, two, three,
four, and the dot
is given, okay?
If you want some numbers
to put into this,
so for our Q dot out,
so essentially the heat
transfer rate from
the refrigerant
to the water.
If we substitute
our values here,
I have 21.3 kilowatts.
That's a pretty
substantial chiller.
So a 20 kilowatt
chiller is like,
Yeah, well, it's
like a $20,000
chiller. It's a
nice chiller.
Okay. So you have
you'd have that.
That, of course,
would be equal,
right to the q.in,
right, that we had.
The mass flow rate
of the water,
if you substitute
your numbers,
I have here as 0.49
basically 0.49
kilograms/second, okay?
Good. Yes, kilograms
per minute.
1 minute is 60.
Yeah. And one
thing that's kind
of instructive
here to compare
is actually the
values between this.
So the MO 134ar 134 a,
we said was equal to what?
Six kilg per minute,
1 minute and 60 seconds.
So what do I have here?
0.01 kilogram/second.
I So what's
interesting about
this is that the
enthalpy change, right?
So these things have
to be equal, right?
So the MDOT times the
enthalpy change in
the refrigerant is
the M dot times
the enthalpy change
in the water.
And an interesting
feature about
phase change processes is
the enthalpy changes
are massive, right?
So we go from these
liquids to these vapors.
We have very big
changes, and
that's the whole
of them, right?
So the whole point of
a a vapor
compression cycle
in a refrigerator
is that you
condense a liquid and
you boil a liquid,
and the process of
going from one to the
other has a huge
change in enthalpy.
It has a lot of capacity
to absorb heat,
so you don't need to
pump a lot of it, right?
On the other hand,
something like
liquid water, right,
which we use a lot of
for cooling in systems,
because it's not
boiling or evaporating,
this is only sensible
heat transfer.
You're not going to have
a very large
enthalpy difference.
So it means you
got to crank up
the mass floor
and a lot more to
match the heat
transfer rate
that you're going
to have from
the refrigeration
side, right?
Um, If you think about,
like an actual
refrigerator,
the way that you get
this balance is a lot of
times it's now with
an MDOT of water,
and it's natural
convection of air.
And so what you end up
really needing is
actually very large.
Maybe this section
where you pump,
the fluid is small,
but if you look in
the back of them,
you're going to see
big, like, radiators
or a lot of
metal that's on
there to kind of
enhance the area
such that you can
get a balance, okay?
All clear? That's
heat exchangers.
Another thumbs
up. Awesome.
Okay. So I have 8 minutes.
I think I'm doing
it off notes today.
With notes. Okay. So
the last one I want
to get into then and look
at is a bit of
this unsteady.
So this might be a moment
where I would say,
like We're not going
to do a lot of
practically probably
any unsteady
flow processes
in the course.
But it is interesting,
and I'll show you one,
you know,
application of this.
So one is, like,
here they show
sort of charging
of a tank.
I mean, one of the
ones that's, like,
most relevant is
pump hydro, right?
So if you think about
pump hydro and you
want to store
something kind
of like a battery, right?
You're going to be
pumping some fluid,
storing that as like a
potential energy and
then bringing it back.
That's like one, one
example of that.
Here they have things
like charging a tank,
In addition to,
like, pumped
hydro, another
common way of,
like, renewable
energy storage
is essentially
this process,
but imagine like a cavern
underground, right?
So I have my renewable.
I then take that air, I
compress the heck
out of it in
a huge geological feature
underground,
compress that,
and then later
on, I take that,
and let's say I
run a turbine
or something liquid.
So these are
kind of examples
of unsteady
flow processes.
The way that we
do this, right?
So I'll erase this
is the same as
we did the other
things, right?
We have our conservation
of mass, okay,
and we have our
conservation
of energy, right?
So it's pretty much
the same thing,
but I'll show you
kind of one
important difference
of these devices compared
to the way we were solving
steady steady
flow devices.
And then I'll
hopefully finish
with at least getting
started with an example.
Mm, do do, do,
do. Okay.
All right, right. So
again, we have this.
Let's say, you know,
we have our system there.
Okay. Um, Let's
say, you know,
we have some piston
cylinder type device,
but with an opening, okay?
So this thing is kind
of like free to
move up or down.
We have the control
volume here,
where we can bring
mass now in or out.
So that's kind of like
our piston cylinder,
but now we can bring mass
in from one
direction, right?
So let's say here,
we're dealing with
some amount of mass from
the inlet that's
coming in.
Okay? We can define
an initial state,
which is then M M one.
So we have M one of
this control volume,
and then we have a final
state, which would
be basically M two, right?
So you're going to have
some change of mass.
Um, you know, in
this control volume,
and that's going to
be equal, you know,
just like our
thermal accounting,
the mass that comes
from the inlet
minus the mass from
the exit, okay?
So that's basically our
conservation of mass.
Of course, for
this problem,
we don't have any,
we don't have any exiting.
If we look at the
change in the energy,
so the change in
the energy of
our system here.
So the E let's
say, uh, you know,
let's say E
Delta E, Right,
CV is going to be
equal to the
energy that enters
minus the energy
that exits.
Okay? The way that
this can enter is just
like we had, right before.
So you can have you know,
W in plus our Q in plus,
you know, M in, right?
So this could be M
in that M can carry
some, some
enthalpy, right?
That could carry some
kinetic energy, right?
And that could also
come in from a height.
Okay. So does that look,
that looks
basically right.
And then plus a negative,
the out, right?
W out. Plus, you know,
Q out plus, you know,
out times the
enthalpy out,
plus the velocity out
squared divided by
two plus G, Z out, right?
This is a minus
sign. Okay.
Um, you know, and
again, the book, right?
The book tries
to sometimes
make things more
convenient.
So this enthalpy plus
kinetic energy plus
potential energy.
The book we'll call,
right, as Theta.
So you can call this
basically a Theta
in if you wanted to,
and then basically the
same thing here as
a Theta as a Theta
out, right? Okay.
Um, So what makes this
kind of impractical,
okay, is that right?
I just spent all
this time talking
about steady flow devices.
The steady flow devices
dealt with rates
of something.
So I have a
rate of, right,
something that's coming
in and coming out.
Um, right?
And that's convenient.
In this case,
I don't have
anything with rates.
So I look at this,
and I say, okay, there's
some final state,
maybe it's totally
discharged
is the final state.
Or let's say something
that's totally discharged
the initial state,
and then I charge it
and it's fully primed.
So I guess you could
go in and do that.
And you could look at
these things
and say, Okay,
that's how much
mass changed,
and that's how much energy
in the control
volume changed.
Um, For, like, real
systems, though, like,
the rate that I want
to bring mass in will
probably depend on how
pressurized
this is, right?
So if I have a device here
that can probably get
something to a pressure.
As I fill this more,
the rate that
I fill it will
probably be less, right?
So you'll probably
end up having
something, you
know, asymptotic.
And analyzing
and figuring out
those timescales of a
filling a compression
or sort of decompression,
that's kind of, like,
important, okay?
And this you know,
approach that's here, you
know, doesn't
totally get you.
So if you want to analyze,
you know, systems
that look,
you know, again, like
I said, this one,
you know, here with
the discharge,
what you'll have
to do is to
think about
these things in,
like, little nuggets,
like in little
steps, right?
So I'll have a control
volume, okay? Right?
I'll have some rate,
maybe that I'm
bringing it in,
right, you know,
let's say there's
like an MI.
Let's see if there's an
M dot I trash. Right?
So maybe I'll have
a rate, right,
that I'm bringing, you
know, something in, okay?
And I'll have maybe
a new rate at
something like an
I plus one, right?
Or maybe another way
of saying this
is that I have
an M dot I at T,
and then I have an M dot
I at T plus Delta T.
Okay? And so the way
that you can figure out,
sort of, you know,
how much mass you have
sort of in the vessel.
So the mass that I
have here at time T,
might be equal to some
original mass
that I have in
there plus the dot
I times the delta
T. And again,
if you're very interested
in these things and
you want to see
how actually to
analyze this,
which I want to ask
on, like, quizzes,
you're going to do
a hybrid between
an unsteady flow problem
and a steady flow problem,
and you will
solve this what's
called numerically, okay?
So, you know, in
between each step,
you'll have something
that's kind
of like quasi equilibrium,
so I fill it a little or
I discharge a
little, right,
to figure out
what my state is,
and then I go on
with the rest
of my analysis.
So in order to do this,
right, like I said,
you're going to have
some version of
some M dots there.
You have to know,
like an initial mass.
You have to know
sort of your
initial states that
you start with.
And if you go
on, like I said,
kind of iteratively
with, like,
Delta Ts, you know,
you can basically
analyze it, right?
And again, in
the interest of
time, I'll take
you through it.
So in this problem here,
this would be
the experiment
that I mentioned before.
So,
let's say you have a
refrigeration system,
there's a fire,
you need to
evacuate this
whole thing, okay?
And you got to
do it safely.
So you have some volume
associated with it,
some pressure, a fluid,
a pressure, a quality.
You have some heat that's
coming in, let's
say, from the fire.
For now, because I'm
not going to teach
compressible
flow theory yet.
You'll have an MDOT,
um you know,
with it, okay?
And so, again, what you
can end up with here
as you can see,
here's my mass flow rate.
Here's the pressure drop
that happens with this.
Here's the change
in internal energy.
And you could go on
and, you know, plot
a process like that on
a pH diagram of what
a relief event
would look like.
But this whole curve
that I produced
is essentially
Little Delta Ts,
doing a numerical
scheme like
this to figure out
the changes, okay?
Alright, with that,
I'm going to stop.
If you have any
questions, I'm up here.
Otherwise, on Wednesday,
we kick off with,
I think, second law.
Alright, thank
you, everyone.