Yeah, so we choose to use
PICLor to get to
the states and
these properties.
Or, again, we can navigate
using the isentropic
relations.
I use your steady flow
processes, right?
So the change,
right, if I draw
control volume on each
of these devices,
there's going to be no
change in energy or
mass inside of each of
those devices, right?
And if I draw
control volume
around the entire thing,
it's the same, okay?
The energy that I
put in is equal to
the energy that
I'm taking out.
To.
Yeah, and the heat
exchangers are
treated isoberically.
So let's start
with, again,
the steady flow analysis
of each of these devices,
develop our relations
for heat and work,
define efficiency,
and then let's get
into how we're
going to use
the isotropic
relations to get to
the actual enthalpies
there, right?
So again, maybe I'll
draw the first one,
and then Yeah.
Okay. All right.
So for our compressor,
right, our compressor
here is our inlet.
This is our
outlet, our state
one to state two.
My control volume
here looks like this,
do, do, do, do.
There, right?
Right? The change in
energy of the CV,
the change in the mass in
this CV are both
equal to zero, right?
So the DE CV dt
is equal to e.in,
minus E dot out, right?
And dm CV dt
is equal to m.in
minus M dot out.
Steady, steady,
gone, right?
So our e.in is equal
to our E dot out.
And our.in is equal
to M dot out,
which is equal to
M dot. All right.
Was that we can bring
energy in, right?
Work, heat, and then
dot enthalpy will
neglect kinetic,
and we'll say Delta
E and Delta changes
in potential energy are
both essentially
zero here.
So we'll have is aw.in.
We will not have a.in
because it's adiabatic.
We'll have our.in,
which is just dot,
and then that'll
be times H one.
We could have heat
transferred out,
but it's adiabatic, no.
We don't have work
transferred out.
It's a compressor.
And so that's
just going to be
the enthal PH two, okay?
And so our w.in is
just going to be our
m.h2 minus H one, right?
We can do the
same thing now
for our heat
exchanger, right?
So our heat
exchanger like this.
Again, our control volume.
I guess I should
have indicated,
I didn't indicate
here, but hold on.
All right. So I have a W
dot write aw.in like that.
Okay, our heat exchanger
is a state two to
state to state
three, right?
We have aq.in,
which is here.
Again, it's the
same thing, right?
We don't have changes
in energy or mass of
the control volume,
neglect changes in kinetic
and potential energy.
There is no work transfer
associated with
this device.
So if we write our e.in
and our e dot out,
our e.in, right,
we're going to have
aq.in plus an m.h2.
Is then equal to.
There's no workout,
there's no heat out.
So that's just going to
be dot times H three.
So then q.in, is equal
to m.h3 minus H two.
We do a sanity check.
I'm putting heat in.
This should be
getting hotter.
I'd expect then
that my enthalpy
exiting the heat exchanger
is greater than
entering, right?
That makes sense.
All right.
All right, onto
our turbine.
So our turbine here.
Okay, here's our turbine.
Okay. Here. All right.
I've got, like, you know,
work going in
two directions.
I'll just call
this in general,
then as a W dot out.
There's a portion
of the W dot
out that goes to
the compressor,
and then the
portion that is
transferred out
and is used.
We'll call that all
as dot dot out.
What's entering here
and exiting here
is then at state
three and state four.
Again, steady flow device.
We don't have heat in,
right? It's adiabatic.
We don't have work in,
but we do have an m.h3,
neglecting kinetic and
potential energy changes.
And that's going
to be equal
to the shaft work out,
W dot out, no heat out,
and that's dot
times H four.
So W dot out is equal
to m.h3 minus H four.
And again, that
makes sense because
I'd expect the enthalp
at stay three to be higher
than four, so that's good.
Okay. And then
our final one
is another heat exchanger.
So here's our last
heat exchanger.
Okay. So the
control volume,
do do do, do, do
do do, do do.
All right. Q dot out.
State four to state
one. All right?
Again, steady flow device.
No neglect changes
in kinetic
potential energy.
I don't have heat in,
I don't have work in,
but I do have a fluid
entering, right?
I have an M dot
times H four,
and that's equal
to my heat out.
I don't have workout.
I do have mass out,
and then that's
leaving with an
enthalpy of one, right?
So Q dot out is equal
to m.h4 minus H one.
And that makes sense,
right, because I'd
expect the gas here
to be colder and
the enthalpy
specific enthal will
be less at state
one, all right?
That is pretty good.
Let's define now
our backward ratio.
So our back work ratio
was equal to the
w.in divided by
the W dot out.
So the W dot out was
dot times H three
minus H four,
and the w.in was
then.h2 minus H one.
The dots cancel, so
you just have H two
minus H one divided by
H three minus H four.
All right. Then the
last thing that
we need to define is
the thermal efficiency.
This is, you
know, what I already
wrote before.
There it is, right?
So the thermal efficiency,
here's the W dot out minus
w.in divided by
q.in, right?
So the W dot out, again,
was dot three
minus four minus
M dot times H two minus
one, that's network.
And then this
is M dot times
H three minus H two.
Mm dots would cancel,
could also, um,
Yeah, your end dots
would cancel and you'd end
up with let's see.
Three to four, two to one,
three to two. Yeah,
that's right.
Okay.
The two We
could also write
this as the net,
the net heat in 34.
Let me think for a
second. So that's 32.
I wrote something
wrong in my notes,
but this is right because
this is basically
network out minus network
in divided by heat in.
You could also write this
as net heat in, right,
which would be MDOT
times H, right?
Our heat is coming in
at H three minus H two.
Minus the heat out,
which is then H
four minus H one,
and then this
is divided by
M dot times H
three minus H two.
We can rearrange this,
and then this would
essentially be
one minus H four minus H
one divided by H three
minus H two, okay?
And this is
possible because
it's a cycle, right?
All right, there's
our formulas.
So now what we
need to do is
we need to figure
out our states.
So we need to
figure out of
all of these
states. All right.
All right, do, do, do.
Okay. All right.
State one, we're good.
State one is like this.
State one, we have 100
and P one is 140 pa,
and T one is equal to
40 degrees C, right?
From this, I know H
one and I know this one.
Is there a question?
Yes, please.
And it. So this
has to do with
the fact that
this is a cycle, okay?
It means that I return
to where I start.
If that's a cycle and
I return to where I start,
the net energy
that I put in must
equal to the net energy
I take out, right?
So in this case, I right?
The net work that
I take out is w dot
out minus w.in, right?
That's going to be my
net workout, okay?
My net energy
transferred in
is going to be right
from my heat, right?
That's q.in minus
q dot out, okay?
So three minus
two is my q.in,
or little Q in here.
H four minus one, right?
Is going to be then
my little Q out.
I multiply that by dot.
I've got q.in minus
q dot out divided by q.in.
So both are valid, okay?
And just to show
you that they're
the same thing, I
didn't need to do that.
H three minus H two
is here, right?
Minus H four plus
H one is here.
So you could go
from here to here
with simple
rearranging too.
But what I'm describing
is that in the
numerator here,
right, it's the network
out divided by
the heat in.
That's the definition
of the therm
efficiency of an engine.
The network out is equal
to my net heat in, okay?
And what I've written
here in this way is
that w dot out minus
w.in q.in minus Q dot out,
but they're the same
thing because it's
a cycle. Now
the questions?
Okay. And since that
wasn't on the video,
yeah, that's what
I'm talking about.
Okay. The question
was about that.
All right. So we're
going to navigate
states now.
We got to navigate states.
All right. So
here we're good.
We now state one
to start with.
State two, State Two.
We're going to
start first with
dealing with State
two S, right?
State two S. State
two S is going
1-2 assuming
the compressor operates
isentropically.
I need to do that first
before I can then use
my isotropic efficiency of
the compressor to
determine my actual state,
right? This is the
way you do it.
So you write State
two S. State two S,
S two, Li S two is
equal to little S one,
and you know that P
two is equal to RP
times P one, right?
So where RP was the
pressure ratio.
And this problem, I'm
just giving you
pressure two.
So you wouldn't need
to know the RP.
You could determine
the pressure ratio,
but that's there.
So from this, I
now know my h2s.
I put a little S
there to denote that
this enthalpy is for
an isotropic process.
Okay. All right.
To get to state two A,
state to A,
I need to recall
the definition of
the isotropic efficiency
of the compressor.
Isotropic efficiency of
the compressor
is the ratio
of the minimum work
in divided by the
actual work in.
What is the
minimum work in?
What is that process?
Don't make me call on
Alex, right? All right.
It is isontropic, right?
It is the minimum organ
is with the one that's
done reversibly.
So here, that would
be h2s minus H one,
neglecting changes in
kinetic and
potential energy,
which we do for
these devices,
divided by H two
A minus H one.
If I rearrange then,
what I could have is
what H two A minus H one
is equal to H twos minus H
one divided by
the istropic efficiency
of the compressor.
And then this is all
plus H one, okay?
I know H twos. I just
determined it here.
H one we determined
up here, H one,
and E to C,
the isentropic
efficiency of
the compressor is given.
I know H two A,
P two is still
P two, okay?
And so with this
information
of H two A and the
pressure at state two,
I now know H two actual.
I can also then
compute the actual
temperature,
I use Piclor, right?
I can use this with
that notation and call
the enthalpy and
the temperature
because I know the
state, all right?
So that's how you use
the compressor
there. All right.
State two A. Let's
go with state three.
State Three.
Again, the heat
exchanger isoberic.
So what does it mean you
know about the pressure?
It's P two, P
three is P two.
Okay, so you know that,
and T three is given.
T three is a given.
So with this, you know,
S three, little S three,
and you know and
you know H three.
Again, just like we
did here with first
determining the
isontropic state
and then the actual state,
we'll start off
with state four S.
For state four S, S
four is equal to
S three, right?
And again, there's
another heat exchanger,
it means that the
pressure at state four
is equal to the
pressure at state one.
And so from this,
I know now H 4h4s.
All right.
The isotropic efficiency
of a turbine is
the ratio of the
actual workout
divided by the
maximum workout.
What is the
maximum workout?
Isotropic, okay?
All right.
So H three and H three,
right? And this is minus.
So the maximum workout
would be then if I was at
state four and I
arrived there
isentropically,
and the actual
one is H for A,
where a means
actual, right?
So then we can rearrange.
So then I have
what do I have?
I have H four
negative H for A plus
H three is equal to E to
T H three minus H four,
um, Okay, if I move
that to the other side,
then I'll have
minus H three,
okay, but there's a
negative sign here.
So then I have
to make this
negative and
that positive.
So the actual enthalpy
at state four
is equal to the enthalpy
at state three minus
isentropic efficiency
of the turbine times
H three minus h4s.
But the point is
that I know this.
So now I know state for A,
because I know H A
from this, all right?
And I know that P four
is equal to P one, right?
Just as I wrote it here.
And so from this,
I can determine
T I can basically
determine T for
actual, okay?
Yeah, and then obviously,
since I use it
as an input,
I also know my H
for A, all right?
Okay. And that's
pretty much it.
So for the case of using
pie color, All right.
So if I come back
to my efficiency,
so I have to modify
this a little bit.
So the thermal
efficiencies here,
H three is unchanged,
but H four is HA,
H two A minus H one,
H three is unchanged,
but then I have
H H two A, okay.
And each of those, right,
we could determine
by substituting
in from here at H
two A I have here,
H four A I have here,
H three I have here,
and H one I have here.
What's the one
thing that I
don't know, though, okay?
I guess I don't need
it to determine that,
but the one thing
that we didn't
determine yet was
the mass flow rate.
If you want to do that,
you need to know also
the specific volume one
or at the entrance
at state one.
So the specific volume
at state one you
could call here,
and then MDT, right?
Let's say MDT.
Is then going to
be equal to V dot,
the volumetric flow
rate given above,
divided by the specific
volume at state one.
Why at state one?
Because this
is going to typically be,
right, the volumetric flow
rate of air that comes in.
If air is coming
into this device,
it's entering
from the outside.
It means it's entering
from state one, okay?
Yeah, so it does matter,
you know, where
you take that up,
but you would call
it in this case,
it's stay one
because that's
where it's
entering, right?
All right. The
backward ratio,
again, we could
modify that.
That'll be H two
A minus H one,
and then H three
minus H four A.
In terms of the
temperatures
at the exits, again,
you can call that one
pi killer like that,
and where's my state two?
You can call the
other one like
that. Do do do.
All right. Are there
questions about
this before I show
you ideal gas?
So, for me, I personally
find this a rather
intuitive way of,
you know, going through.
So even if I could choose
to do ideal gas here,
my personal
preference is to
write down my
formulas and then,
you know, work
through my states
in this manner, all right?
Yes, please.
So that's in
this efficiency
that's given, right?
So before we had
talked about
the isotropic efficiencies
of compressor to turbine,
essentially,
devices that can
compress or
transfer workout.
And they are
by definition,
if you neglect changes
in kinetic
potential energy.
This for the
turbine, right?
So the ratio of the
actual workout of
that device divided by
the maximum possible,
all right? What is
the meaning of this?
The meaning of
this is that
you recognize that
in the real world,
things don't operate with
100% of their capacity.
It's Friday afternoon.
I'm up here.
I don't know
what my ETA is,
but I don't feel,
you know, it's
not 100, all right?
That's the meaning
of this, right?
So it tells you
that you know,
in a convenient way,
how to determine the state
at the exit of
these devices while
giving you
something that's
kind of real, all right?
But that's where it comes
through is with this.
And you would be
given this piece
of information.
The upstream condition
is always known.
So the inlets are going to
be given, okay,
for both of them.
You determine the
isentropic property,
via the way that
I did right
I did here,
where the entrance entropy
is equal to the exit,
and by knowing
another property,
then you can determine
the isentropic enthropy.
And then from
that you solve
for the actual enthropy.
Okay. Other
questions? Cool.
All right. We're going
to stay with this
because why not?
What should I erase?
I feel like that I want
to keep and this
I want to keep.
This I'm going to
erase because we're
going to work
through our
properties now.
So this right?
I know that,
um All right, whatever.
We'll kill this,
we'll kill this.
We'll kill this.
State three will
leave like this.
State four S we'll get rid
of State four A will
also get rid of.
This will also get rid of,
but we'll keep
that, alright?
Okay, let's start with
this, first of all.
Changes in enthalpy for
an ideal gas can be
approximated as what?
Cp Delta Ts, okay?
So Cp Delta T here,
Cp Delta T here.
This for an ideal gas
can be approximated as
T three minus T four A
divided by T three
minus T four, okay?
The same thing
here. Cp Delta T.
This is then going to
be T two minus T one
divided by T two A
minus T one. All right?
From the TDS relations
that I wrote before, okay,
here, in this
notation is T two.
So the isotropic
temperature,
the exit of the compressor
is equal to the entrance
one times the ratio of
the pressures in the
antibatic index.
So you know t2s, right?
So you know t2s,
you know T ones,
and you're given this.
You solve for T two A.
That's it, okay?
And vice versa.
You can do the
same thing for
right for the turbines,
tt4s is equal to
T three times
P four divided
by P three to
the kappa minus one
divided by Kappa, okay?
Again, you know T three.
You know this pressure
ratio as it's given.
You know your Kappa,
so you know T four.
All right. And so,
you know, T three,
you know, T
three, you know,
t4s from that,
you know, E to T.
And then what
you solve for
is T four A, okay?
Yes, please.
1.4. Other questions?
You can also figure
it out with PICO.
If you have a state, if
you have a state,
you can go,
let's say one dot cpp,
and then I'll call
that or dot CV,
and then we'll call that.
Chandler told me to
update the documentation,
but like Mario and stuff,
there's cheat codes.
So, say it again?
I didn't tell you.
Kindly, he did. He
asked me kindly.
He did ask kindly.
Okay.
But that's how
you could call
it and then you
take the ratio,
but 1.4 is what
it is for air.
Okay? Other questions?
Right? And then
when it comes into
these efficiencies
for the same thing.
So if I want to know
the efficiency
here, right,
this is going to be
one minus T four minus
T one divided by T
three minus T two.
This is going to be H A
for A and T two A, okay?
And again, we're
allowed to
do this for an ideal gas.
It's an approximation
of changes in
enthalpy or CP
dTs, all right?
Um, if you want
to do some math,
okay, like we did for
the auto cycle, right,
this Eta H of a
Brayton cycle
can be shown to
be equal to one
minus one over the RP,
that compression ratio to
the kappa minus one
divided by Kappa, right?
And that's kind of nice.
Again, with an ideal gas.
Instead of going
through all of that,
I could break this down
into two parameters,
the adiabatic index
of the fluid,
which is an ideal gas,
and the ratio of
the pressure at
the exit to the inlet
of the compressor.
So P two divided by P one.
And with that, you
can get a number,
all right?
But this number
here is, again,
would be assuming
it will be
slightly different
from what you'll
compute here because in
this derivation here,
there is nothing
about T for actual.
What you would
have here is
the isentropic
temperature at
state four and
the isotropic
temperature at state two.
So something like
this would be, right,
an approximation there for
an ideal cast for the
ideal Brayton cycle.
And that's
analogous, remember
to what we did
for auto, right?
The auto cycle and
the diesel cycle,
that's the one you
would have for Brayton,
okay? And what
does it mean?
It means that essentially,
if I have a huge
pressure ratio,
then I'm going to
have this approaching
one, and that kind
of makes sense.
A? If I take something
and I compress it,
the temperature is going
to go up like hell, right?
You're going
to have a huge
temperature
increase with that.
And so intuitively,
that would make
sense to me that in
increasing that value,
you'll get to a
higher efficiency.
Alright. Yeah, and
the back work ratio,
also the same thing.
You know what here,
but this could
also just be
the temperature
differences if you
assume the ideal
gas. Alright?
All right. Good.
Yeah, and if you want to,
you can click on that
and follow through.
I will just caution
you that at
least one of the
I think the one efficiency
formula I looked at
is wrong for now,
but I'll update it
probably the next
time I teach.
So that'll be fun
to see next year.
All right, um, Okay,
so in terms of where
are we at in terms of
efficiencies as a function
of the pressure ratios?
Again, just
like we did for
the auto and the
diesel cycle,
these are the
typical values
you'll have for
pressure ratios,
and then these are
the efficiencies.
So somewhere between
0.35 and 0.6,
so 30 to 60% efficiency.
60%, if that was true,
that's a pretty
big number, okay?
Thermo electric power
plants are somewhere in
the neighborhood
of 50%, 45, 50%.
So for the
theoretical one,
that's a rather high,
um, If you were able
to attain that,
that would be a
rather high value.
Again, applications,
electric power generation,
and then aircraft
propulsion.
Alright, sadly, I'm not
going to have time to
do jet propulsion today.
It'll be Monday,
but I want to tell
you one interesting
thing, all right,
about the Brayden
if you do want to
increase the efficiency
of the cycle, okay?
And it is called a
regenerator, all right?
A regenerator.
I'm going to
let you look at
that while I erase.
All right. All right.
All right.
All right. Before I
get into the
details of it,
I just want to tell I
want to describe this,
all right, then it will
make sense to you.
So we have this
compressor, which is here.
So something coming in.
This leaves the
compressor.
It goes through
this device, which
I'm calling a regenerator.
It goes from here into
a heat exchanger,
so a combustion chamber.
This then goes
down into Right.
My turbines connected
via the shaft here.
I've got some, you
know, work
transferred out.
I then have this exit,
which is then passing
through, again,
this regenerator, and
it's leaving, okay?
All right. Yes, please.
Number five.
I number things
intelligently, okay?
Let's leave it at
that. All right.
So let's draw
control volume.
Okay? Well, let's
say something here.
So the fluid coming out of
the compressor
is warm, okay?
But it's not as hot
as State three.
So State three
is the hottest,
and state two is lower.
Out of the turbine,
let's say you have
gases that are hot.
If you ever put your
hand near a muffler,
hopefully not too
close, you'll
feel it can be warm, okay?
If you ride a bike behind
these, like, buses,
you feel warm
and you're also,
you know, getting
smug there, right?
So you have this as a
higher temperature,
and this is going out to
atmosphere at State six.
So probably this
temperature here is higher
than this one,
okay? All right.
And without this device,
you would just
be exhausting
this into the
environment, right?
So this is something
really hot.
Okay. And the idea here
is maybe I could
take some of the
hot, you know,
the heat out of the
exhaust and warm
up the fluid before
it enters the combustion
chamber, right?
Right? Now, why is that
an interesting idea?
I'll show you now
with a drawing, okay?
So let's say I draw
my control volume
around Um, let's see.
I can draw it. Let's see.
I draw it like this. Okay?
So I've drawn it around
the compressor,
the turbine,
the heat exchanger,
basically, the compressor,
and the regenerator,
right? So what do I have?
I have a network
w.net out,
which is leaving,
and I have Q dot,
which is going into
the combustor.
1 second. Is energy
entering or
leaving the system
through that regenerator
as I've drawn it?
No. So it's like
you're heating
your fluid without
putting any heat in.
That's it. That is it.
That's why you do a
regenerator, okay?
It's like for free, ar?
And very rarely are
things free in
thermodynamics,
but that's something
that's for free.
So you can do that.
And so it means you need
less q.in, all right?
And if my whole efficiency
is Q dot N is in
my denominator,
if I make that smaller,
because I'm
preheating here,
I'm going to
automatically end up
with a higher
efficiency, okay?
All right, how does
the book talk about?
So what's the trick
that you need to
know to be able to
handle this device?
The book will talk about
regeneration
efficiency, right?
And again, I said here,
this was State
two entering it.
I have State five here.
I have State four,
which is here,
and I have State
six, which is there.
Five, two, and four,
right, which is there.
So I have that.
So there's five.
There's two and
four and two.
Okay. All right, so I
don't need state six.
All right. Okay, the
efficiency here or
the effectiveness.
I'm sorry, it's
called effectiveness.
So the effectiveness of
this regenerator
is the enthalpy
at state five minus
the enthalpy at state two,
right, entering
the regenerator.
H four minus H two, okay?
So five to two, that's
kind of clear, right?
That would essentially be
how much heat
is transferred,
right through this
process to warm you up.
And you want that to
be a large number.
So a more effective
regenerator is increasing
the enthalpy at state
five without heating
from the outside, right?
That's an effective
regenerator, right?
Um, On the other side,
we have H four, right,
minus H two, right?
This is essentially H
four would be like,
kind of like the
potential, right?
That's the higher
enthalpy state
that's exiting
the turbine.
Um, I don't you
could say that maybe
you want this
to be a really,
really high value
because that
will or if you
had a really,
really high value
here, it may not
be as effective
of a device.
And because it's
leaving a turbine,
it won't be particularly
high, okay?
But you have something
here, H four,
and you want to take
enthalpy out of
that on the way
to six, right?
So 4-6, you're going
to cool that down,
and you're going to
transfer it in, right?
But you're not going
to be able to transfer in
more enthalpy
than what you
started with, okay, right?
So you're not going to
be able to get more
out of this than H
four minus H two,
since this is what
you start with.
And this is the
effectiveness, right?
Okay, so that's all you
need to know about
Braden, literally,
how you solved it, and
then this little
twist and any quiz
I'm going to give you
on a gas power cycle,
you should be good to go.
There are other
things like
reheat and other
little things.
We'll probably get
into those when we do
vapor power cycle.
Yes, please.
So with combustion
chambers and engines,
don't you want the
highest concentration?
Like combustion Carno,
all I want is it hot.
The hotter it
is, the better.
That's all I care
about in Carnal.
Okay? Yes. But
you could get
hotter by having
more fuel,
right, and things
like that.
Enthalpies of vapor
enthalpy of combustion?
Yeah, you could have
that. Okay. I'm going
to close it here. That
was a good question.
Go bears. Sam