All right, I got 210.
So today we're
talking about
property tables
and ideal gas.
Before we get started,
just some words.
All right.
So in the first problem,
a lot of these problems,
when you do it Okay.
So when you use problems
there, a lot of the ones,
especially when you like
property tables in that,
you're able to open
this workbook.
This workbook is
essentially like
a constrained
Jupyter notebook.
It has, like, pre
installed packages,
like PiKlor and
all of that.
Right? So if you open
that and launch it,
you're going to see
the actual Jupyter
Notebook there.
If you double click on it,
you have this
thing, right?
So in most of the
problems, you have
an identical template to
this also in the
practice ones,
and this is going to
be the same exact one
that you will see
in a quiz, right?
So the idea is that
you practice on
actually what
I'll test you on.
I'm not to trick you.
Like, not in this
class anyways, okay?
So yeah, if you
click on that,
you can then run through a
and see that? That's one.
The second thing is
that I don't see this now.
I did out of
these slides and
now I don't see it,
is that when you use Pi
Killor with numbers,
it needs units. This
is not a math class.
It may be quite mathy,
but it's engineering.
In engineering, you got
to give a unit to it.
And so a lot of the book
problems and all of
that will give things
an MPA as an input,
especially on pressure.
Calvin is an
input for like
a default input
for Pi killor
also as the um
as the output.
Unfortunately,
the default input
or fortunately,
it really depends
on the problem.
The default input in
pressure is
like KPA, okay?
So I recommend, you know,
when you work at
these problems, like,
declare your
units, you know,
if you have them in
there and, you know,
and sort of best
practice with that.
So if anyone had
trouble with a
problem like this,
especially a
programming one,
that's probably
the source of
the errors that you
haven't declared.
The unit for that,
you've just put
P equals, you know,
P and then not declared
that actually that
pressure variable
is an NPA, okay? Units.
Questions about
this? Okay. The GSI,
Cassiine McCormick
could post
like a YouTube video that
goes along with
the problem
from Homework one,
hopefully that'll
assist you, okay?
All right. So
are we today?
We're going to talk
about ideal gas, right?
Give it go deeper
into that and
how it stands in
contrast to other
equations of state
that you can use
and essentially
get into the ones
where we can
predict, like
phase transitions.
That's what we care
about with water, right?
The fact that
there is a phase
transition right
a lot of times.
And we'll also talk
about go deeper
into these two concepts
of this constant.
I said before, like Q
is equal to C Delta T,
the meaning of those C's.
All right? Okay,
so a refresher,
right, for a pure
substance, right?
Before, if I take
two independent
variables, right?
I can compute a
dependent one.
An ideal gas is,
um, let's say,
like air or nitrogen
is a pure substance.
So that means that if
I take pressure
and volume,
I should be able to know
temperature out
of there, right?
So PV I should be
able to get the,
um, uh, the
temperature of it.
If you want to, like,
understand the form
of the equation,
right? It's PV and T.
I put them on the
left hand side,
then that equation
should be equal to,
uh to zero, right?
Okay. There's
two ways that
you will see
the ideal gas.
Normally, how
it's taught in
chemistry is
like this form,
PV equals N, right,
which is moles, all right?
RU, which is
the universal gas
constant right in
joules per mole
per degrees
Celsius N times
temperature, all right?
So when you see it
in this form, right,
you need to take
care of the fact
that that N is in moles.
And remember that the
temperature here that
you're dealing with
is in what unit?
Kelvin, okay?
The way to check
yourself is, like,
put in Celsius at
the freezing point of
water or the melting
point of water.
And then, like, what is
the pressure that you
would have at
that condition?
What are, like, the two
potential solutions
to pressure that you could
have for substituting
zero degrees
Celsius into that formula?
Zero or Infinity, you
know, and beyond, okay?
So to avoid Buzz Aldrin
and whatever, you know,
type stuff there,
basically stay with
Kelvin, all right?
Um Okay, that's one thing,
right? It is related.
This universal
gas constant
in joules per mole per
keelvin can be defined
also in physics.
If you've seen it in
a physics context,
sometimes you
will see pv is
kt where N is the
number of molecules.
The K there is
Boltzman's constant.
Boltzman' constant, I told
you before it is jule
Kelvin Actually,
it's joule per
something per keelvin,
joule per molecule,
you know, with it.
And it's related to the
universal gas constant
through Abagro's constant,
right, 6.02 times
ten to the 23rd.
I learned that in
second grade I think
if I haven't forgot
that shit since, right?
So it's like in here
burned in. All right.
So you've got, you know,
this thing that you can
use to interchange between
the chemists approach and
the physicist approach,
namely with RU
and KB, right?
Um, Great. All right.
If we want to write the
chemist approach in
this class, right,
a lot of times
we're going to
be dealing with,
you know, maybe
specific volume.
When I have something
that is like,
a specific per mole,
I'm going to put a
bar above it, right?
So if I have my V
bar here, right,
this is going to mean
that it's meters
cubed per mole, right?
I'm not really going
to use this very much.
It's not really going
to come up again,
I think, until, like,
I don't know, combustion,
whenever that's a
distant future problem
for us, very distant.
But for now, right,
that's what the
bar will mean.
It doesn't mean,
like, a mean value.
It means that it's on a
per mole basis, okay?
One thing. The second
thing is that,
um, a lot of
times, we're not
going to use this.
So how do we use it?
How do we typically
would use it?
Let's say we're going to
have P little V, right?
So that's going to
be meters cubed per
kilogram is equal to,
you know, let's say,
R times T, right?
This is one way or
we're going to see
P capital V is
equal to mass M
times R T, okay?
Now, this R is not
universal, okay?
It depends on the
substance involved.
Actually, that was like a
problem historical
development of
the ideal gas equation is
no one could figure
out exactly what R is.
Also, interestingly,
in my reading,
no one is quite
sure why we use
R. Maybe a French guy,
you know, but, like,
so there's the
universal R,
and that is universal,
and that's per mole.
But as soon as we
get into this R,
at the unit of
this R is right,
it's going to be energy.
So it can be joule
or let's say,
a lot of times in the
book, you'll see,
like kilojoule per
kilogram elvin okay,
or kilojoule per
kilogram degree Celsius,
are the same, um, um,
right, one degree
change in Kelvin is
one degree change
in, uh, in Celsius.
So there's going to be
this value for
water, right?
There's going to be this
value for, you know,
whatever substance that
exists there, okay?
And obviously,
like in a quiz
or something,
I would just give
you this value.
I don't expect you
to memorize it.
I didn't learn that
in elementary school,
so I don't
remember it, okay?
Um, Cool.
So but that's basically
the difference.
So like I said,
we're going to be
using pretty much
for most of the time
this form of it.
You're gonna have
the specific gas
constant rate,
which depends on
the substance.
And these things
exist, like in a table
or in a you know,
you'll just have a
value, and it'll be
given normally in
the problem, okay?
Questions about
that? Yes, please.
Name in question.
An M. Okay.
The reason why I use an
M is because there's
an M in mechanical
engineering
and we are biased, okay?
The real reason is
that it's mass, right?
A lot of times we're
going to be dealing
like this problem
later on when we work.
Maybe there's some on a
mass of air
that's in here.
I'm a mass of water.
Don't my ruler stick
is not moles, right?
If told me to
tell you how many
moles of, you know,
stuff in here,
I wouldn't know
what to put, okay?
So we use M because
it's practical.
And a lot of
problems in mechanical
engineering.
Like, if you measure,
um, You know,
a lot of the systems and
instrumentations
are going to
be about weighing
things when
you're in the
industry, right?
I measure, like,
a mass flow rate.
You know, I don't
measure like
a molar a molar
flow rate, right?
Does that answer
your question or no?
Good. Other questions?
Okay. Cool.
Okay. Yes. Yeah, and
you can go back and
forth, right, you know,
from being in a molar,
from a molar basis to
a kilogram by using
the molar mass.
So that's exactly
how you get to
an R value like
this is you
would take the
universal gas constant,
you know, RU, right,
and transform it
using molar mass.
So that's the value for
carbon dioxide
there, okay?
Mostly informational,
but, you know,
I have to say it
because if there's
one equation,
the most abused
equation in this class,
it is this equation.
Okay? You're
going to do shit
like I want to use
this for water, okay?
And you shouldn't
do that, all right?
That's like a
no, no, alright.
We'll get into why you
don't use that
basically for water.
But the other way
that it's abused is
people are using
basically the right,
the wrong value for
the gas constant.
Allright? Yeah, so
where is this valid?
This equation,
right, is valid for
things with very
low density, right?
Is a liquid low
density? No, okay?
A liquid is about
1,000 times
denser than it's
like vapor form,
okay? One. So liquids?
No, definitely out
of the question.
When it comes to
gases, you know,
usually it's sort of
okay as long as you're
not approaching the point
where a gas will
condense, okay?
So that's exactly why
water vapor doesn't
work, right?
There's an attraction,
to it, okay?
And so, really the
conditions where you have
low density is you have a
vacuum, right,
low pressure.
So lower pressure
conditions
or at very high
temperature.
It's a pretty
decent equation.
And then these are
the substances
it works for right,
air, nitrogen,
oxygen, and so
on and so forth.
You probably haven't
seen like well,
maybe you've seen
a liquid version
of this. You've
seen a rocket.
I don't know about CO two.
But otherwise, you know,
most of these ones,
you never would have
seen a liquid form.
And water vapor and
refrigerants should not be
used because you know,
a lot of times
in our systems,
when we put in
the values of
pressure and temperature
that are relevant,
we're near a
saturation point.
We're basically
near a point
where they're
going to condense.
And this model doesn't
include an attractive
term, okay?
Yeah, so let's think
back again a bit.
Like, what is
an ideal gas?
An ideal gas is, like,
molecular dynamic
simulations you did, right?
A bunch of billard balls
that all they do is they
crash into each other
and they never stick,
right? They never
stick, right?
All you're doing
is writing, like,
you know, the
sum of forces,
you know, with
some point mass,
and they hit, but there's
never like a transfer of
that kinetic energy or
an attractor where
basically they
start to stay together.
And because of that, it
will not work for
water, right?
You need a different
equation of
state if you
wanted to then add
an attractive term
to that, okay?
Yeah, so if there's
phase change
involved, no.
And by default,
in this class,
I swear to you
know, whatever.
You write the
ideal gas equation
for water, and
it's like a zero.
Like, I'm not even
I'm sympathetic.
I'm sympathetic
in so many ways.
But, like, you do
that, and it's like,
I need to send a message.
I've sent a message today,
but, you know, it's
just don't do it.
And especially don't
do it because you have
a thermo calculator to
deal with water, right?
Yeah. Okay.
Cool. All right.
Any questions about that?
Otherwise, I'll dive into
this beautiful
example here.
All right?
Okay. So what problem
are we looking at here?
We're looking at
a problem where
initially we have
some container of
volume V one, okay?
So I'm declaring,
like two containers.
One is container,
let's say,
capital I to the left,
Roman numeral
one to the left.
Then let's say
Roman numeral
two, you know,
to the right.
The volume of
Roman numeral one.
So this container
on the left is
equal to V one, all right?
And the volume on
this side is equal to
five times the
volume here, right?
So we'd say basically
five, five V one.
This side contains
mass, right?
So we have basically
some mass,
some gas or whatever
that's, um,
you know, ideal gas
that's in here.
And on this side, we
have a vacuum, alright?
The left hand
side, we say is
at 460 degrees Celsius.
Why not? And a pressure
P one that we don't know.
Alright? And what we're
going to do is we're
going to take
this partition.
So the thing separating
the left from the right,
we're gonna
remove it, right?
We're suddenly
going to remove it.
We're going to
let this gas
expand to the right
hand side. Fine.
And at the end
of this, what
we're going to do
is we're going to
transfer some
amount of heat into
this combined
system such that
the final pressure is
equal to the
initial pressure.
I'm exhausted saying that.
So who would bother
in their right mind
with doing this?
I asked myself as I
wrote all that
out and said it.
Jewel, right?
So I'll put this
to the side
so maybe it's easier
for everyone to
see Jewel James Jewel,
this was a problem
that really concerned
him, his thoughts, right?
Um, and it had to
do with the fact that if
you think about
sort of, you know,
these kind of ideal gas
relations and stuff,
and we're thinking
about how properties,
maybe like
internal energy,
might depend upon
temperature.
He was coming up with
kind of clever experiments
where he would keep,
you know, have a big
change in volume,
um, you know,
associated with,
you know, with
a process or
maybe a big change in
pressure associated
with the process.
And he wanted to see if
there was a change in
temperature with
that, right? There.
And I'll get to,
you know, in
the following part of
what his result was,
what he basically
learned that
ideal gases depend
on, all right?
Okay, so what can we do?
So I've got the values
here that I've
written, okay?
I've got, you know,
what I want to determine
what I've well,
maybe I can put
it to the middle.
Okay, into the middle.
But what I want to
determine is T two here.
I've got some
assumptions, right?
The other assumption
is that I'm going to
assume that this
is an ideal gas.
Okay. Now get rid of this.
We don't need this
anymore. Right?
Okay, I feel good
about this, right?
And we know that we have
this initial state,
in the final state
that we want to go to.
So the step one with
this is we'll go
to our, our physical laws.
So we'll say for the
initial state, right,
I'll have a P one
times a V one,
which is equal to the mass
one times the ideal
gas constant.
Um. I'm not sure
if we're told the
gas, but it's okay.
So we have some
value R, and then we
have T one there, okay?
And what we can also do is
we can write the
same equation at
state two when we're
in equilibrium.
So I can do p2v2 is equal
to two R times T two,
and we assume it's
the same gas,
so it's the same value of
R. We can do a
substitution, right?
So we know the volume
two as a function of
volume one, right?
So I would have,
P two times five.
You know, V one, that's
the partition that's on
the right hand side.
But if it's an
expansion process,
what's actually my total
volume? All right.
So if this is right, my
initial control volume
that I've drawn here
with my boundary,
and then I'm going to
allow that to expand.
You'll get some
nice colors.
So that's my state
control volume
from one if I then
expand that out,
you know, is basically
where we're at
that at state two.
And then this control
volume is what we,
you know, the size
of it for state one.
What's then the volume
at state two? So let
me write it this way.
So V two is equal to what?
661, right?
Yeah. Okay, so 61 there.
So this is plus
V one, right?
So six V one, and again,
that's equal to
R T two, okay?
So that's a pretty
decent equation.
And we have this one
here. What do we
know about P
two? It's P one.
Then we have
here P one times
six the one is
then equal to two.
Sorry, two R T two.
Now in this
process, we don't
have any mass transfer.
The amount of
mass that I have
here my initial state
is equal to the amount
that I have at
my final state.
So what I can do
then is I can just
call this I can leave it
as one or two or I can
just call it as if
I wanted it, right?
Now to compute T two
from this Let's see,
what we're going to do is
I'm going to take
equation one.
Let's call this
And let's call this
then equation two,
and I'm going to take
the ratio, right?
So I'm going to take
the ratio of equation
two divided by
equation one.
And so what I'll
have here then,
right is P one,
six, V one is equal to
two R T two, right?
And both sides
are then divided
by P one times,
right? This is V one.
And then on the right
hand side, right,
I have one R T one, right?
Is this visible?
No, not visible.
Yeah, that's visible.
This part is.
Okay. Maybe I'll just go
to full screen
for a second.
Hmm. Okay. Now,
what cancels here,
right is we're going
to lose the V one,
which is out, right?
There's no mass transfer,
so the M's are the
same. Idel gas.
We assume that
there's no change
in the composition of
the ideal gas that
we have there.
So the R goes away.
And so then if we
rearrange, what do I have?
And also the
pressure, right?
So here, the pressures
also drop, right?
So the pressures drop,
and it's like that.
And so then what
we'll have is that T
one or T two is going
to be equal to six
times T one, right?
I think. Yeah.
Pretty right.
Sure. Yes, please.
So what did I say was
on this side, though?
The vacuum,
right? So vacuum,
you know, here
and you do that.
Okay. The other way
that this experiment
is done is if you've seen,
like, a shock tube.
So if you ever
want to study
the species that
come out of, like,
the end of a rocket
nozzle and all of that,
they do these really
cool experiments
where you basically
generate,
like, a shock wave there.
And the way that you
can do that is you
have really high pressure
up here and then,
like a very thin
membrane that you like,
blow open, and then you
can watch the
shock and measure,
like, evolution and
cool stuff like that.
So for the aero
students in the room.
Yes. Yes, please.
Yeah, I mean, it's math.
You can do that, but
then at the end of it,
you wanted T two as
some form of that.
Yeah. Other questions?
No. Okay. Yeah,
and I'm assuming,
right, that you can
do the substitution.
It's just important
that for T one, right,
when we do the
substitution,
that T one, what
is it equal to?
We said two or
460 degrees C
plus 273.15 there,
and then that'll get
you into Kelvin, right?
So you basically have to
multiply six times that,
and then you'll
have actually a
very large that's
a pretty six,
it's like seven, that's
like a number approaching
the temperature
of the sun.
That'd be a fun
experiment.
Okay. Great. All right,
so if there's no
other questions
then with that,
we'll move on.
So what I'll do now with
this while I get
myself set up is,
again, kind of
repeating on
the property value
determination.
Hopefully, some of you
had had a chance to
try with the
PCulor otherwise,
you're free to go, you
know, with the table.
So in this problem,
what you're going
to start off with
is a superheated vapor
at this condition.
You're going to
cool it down with
constant pressure until
it's a saturated vapor.
And the question
here, there's two.
The first is, what
is T two for the
water vapor?
And then what would T
two be for the ideal gas?
And the idea out of
that second part is to
compare and contrast
what the ideal gas is
able to do for you
versus what is
actually the ground
truth for that, okay?
I have to launch
this, so just
bear with me of
any substance.
In this case, the
equals to one,
an ideal gas equation
is not going to
cut it, right?
How much air did I
say was allowed
in this class?
2%, okay? That's
much more than 2%.
Okay? Great. Any questions
about this? Okay.
Cool. So if you
do want to use an equation
of state, though,
to get at this process of
interaction and
condensation there,
you can add an
attractor term.
So you can take the
ideal gas equation,
go in and put a
term that says,
Hey,
the molecules now like
each other, right?
They're not indifferent
to each other.
They like each
other. And this
was the work of
Vandervals, right?
So Vander Walls,
maybe you've heard
of it before.
But he did his like,
doctoral dissertation
on this,
which actually, if
you look at it,
is kind of
unbelievable, right?
I mean, So what?
Like, 26-years-old,
you know,
going in there and
then writing this up.
And all at a time
when people weren't
really sure that,
like, Adams
existed, right?
So if you read about,
like, people like
Ernest Mach of
the Mach number,
Mach didn't believe
in the Adam, right?
So he was a positivist.
He thought if you couldn't
measure something,
it didn't exist.
Or, you know, it
can't you know,
it's not even a question,
you know, worth
asking there.
But Vandervo' probably
because he was
young, you know?
He's like, Okay, I don't
care what those
old guys think.
But, um, you know,
so you went in
and did it, okay?
So that's one part. So you
had, like, an
attractor term.
The other thing is that
with an ideal gas,
the gas molecules
don't occupy a volume.
Even if I show you
that Biller bolt
simulation, they
don't have a volume.
They're point
sources, okay?
So if you want to
get this right,
especially when you
look into the condensation
and processes like that,
they have to have
a finite volume
to them, okay?
Okay. So B is
the volume term.
So that says that
there's a finite volume
to these atoms
or molecules.
And the AV squared
term is the attractor.
This is basically what
says that at some point,
there's some amount of
that we like each
other, right?
So if I plot a PV diagram,
so let's say I take, um,
you know, a high
temperature,
let's say I take
the temperature at
the critical point
for for water,
okay, right?
I can produce a plot
that shows this
behavior, right?
This is nothing but Pi
killor and computing,
and that's like
how my isotherm
would look like in
a PV diagram, okay?
If I now take Vander
Wall's formula,
which I had before, okay,
I take that and I
can compute A and B.
I'll go into a second
how you compute
those A and B constants,
but I can compute them.
And the red line,
so the blue line
is Pi killor the
water properties,
and the red line is
Vandervals, okay?
Right? So, without, like,
any knowledge of an atom,
right, math and, like,
a bit of creative thinking
and some understanding
on things that were
measured, right,
he produced a line
that looked like that,
which I write a
lot of papers,
and that's pretty like
that's pretty not bad.
That's like our
better than our
2% error kind
of, you know,
without knowing
anything, getting to
that level is
pretty good, right?
Captures the trends
and all of that.
So that's pretty neat.
One, So that's the
super critical point.
Now, you can go in
and start to look
at this process.
You can analyze
this equation
when you actually
get near the
phase transition,
which I mentioned
before is what's
interesting.
So the blue line
here, so we'll
go to a lower temperature.
Let's say 90% of the
critical temperature,
which is 647
Kelvin for water.
I can plot the
blue line, right?
So I have the
I'm decreasing my
specific volume.
I hit a quality
of one of vapor.
I get to quality
of zero, right?
It's a saturated liquid,
and then I shoot up.
That's all fine and well.
You go through your
Vandervals, right?
That looks pretty good
until we get kind
of to the
saturated regime.
It overshoots.
It then undershoots,
and then it shoots
back up, okay?
And you could
say to yourself,
that's a pretty, like,
shitty model, right?
I look at that.
Like, actually, you,
you were raving
about this,
and maybe that guy
shouldn't have passed with
his PhD, you know, there.
But there's
some interesting
features of this.
So the first is that
at least he tried
to hit the dome here,
you know, with it.
Um, And
one thing that's
interesting about this,
and now this is
just me being
like an older guy
telling stories.
So if you want
to go to sleep,
you can, but I think
it's interesting.
You can go from this point
C to D, okay, right?
It's still kind
of moving with
a similar slope that
you had here coming in.
And B to A, right?
It's moving with kind
of a similar slope as
it exits from
the dome, right?
But from B to C,
you have an
inversion, okay?
And what's the consequence
of this, all right?
So from A to B and C to D,
so the change in pressure
divided by the change in
volume for a constant
temperature is
negative, okay?
Now, that makes
sense, right?
If I take something and
I increase the
volume, right?
So let's say that
experiment we did before,
I increased the volume.
Without heat addition, I
would expect a
decrease in pressure.
That's a negative
slope, right?
So DPDV should
be negative.
However, this shows
positive, right?
So that means, like, as I
would increase the volume,
the pressure should go up.
And that makes no
fucking sense, right?
That doesn't make
any sense, okay?
So this, probably B
to C, is not allowed.
Thermodynamically, it
is unstable. All right?
Um, Yeah, so that's
kind of neat.
But the other two
parts, A to B,
and C to D aren't
they're stable.
That's allowed, right?
That still follows
what we said.
And so what makes
this kind of
neat is that with this
kind of procedure
with Vandervals
defining point B
and point C for
substances,
you can produce
regions of what
we would call
metatability, okay?
And again,
you're not going
to be on an examine stuff,
but some things you should
just know, like water,
for example,
does not freeze
at 0 Celsius, right?
If I wanted to freeze,
you need to cool
it much below.
Much below zero, okay?
So when you have
liquid water,
that's a liquid water
below 0 Celsius,
that's a meta stable
liquid, right?
If anyone watches, like,
the Buffalo
Bills, you know,
play football, it's
like actually,
they're good now.
They're very good. But
for a long time, not.
But the point is,
you'll see like
sometimes there's
these videos
in like the fridge,
and they'll take a
water bottle out of
a fridge at a game.
It's like hilarious.
Fridge in a place
where it's like,
minus, you know, whatever
degrees Celsius.
They'll take the
water out and
then they'll
like flick it.
And then all of a sudden,
you see, like
solidification.
Like, suddenly that
otling it caused
it to freeze and that's
a metastable flu.
It's like beautiful tube.
You want to come
my lab I'll show
you some wacky stuff.
But that's a
metastable fluid.
It's the same
when you boil.
If you boil
something, it doesn't
happen at 100
degrees C here.
You need to push
way beyond that.
You have to make
the surface much
hotter in order to
get the liquid to
transition into
being a vapor.
And the same also
in condensation.
It doesn't happen
at the dew point.
You usually got to
cool it below, there.
And anyways,
the take home message
out of this is
that this kind of
pretty smart young guy in
his graduate studies,
not too much older
than you, you know,
went in and wrote
this kind of
seemingly simple
formula that
produced this kind of,
you know, results,
this insight,
which to this day
we look into.
So in my lab,
we look into a lot
of what we call
these metastable
transitions.
When does water boil?
When does it condense?
How does it freeze?
I'm going to
talk like we got
Boeing executives below
us at the moment.
So in like 30 minutes,
I'm going to go
talk to them about
some of the problems
and icing that
we have that are you
know, that exists there.
But it's kind of like,
you know, A, B, C,
D, it's kind of it's
kind of neat, okay?
And again, all
from young man
doing grad school
with it, okay?
It's also interesting to
look at the ideal gas.
So, you know, again, we
had property tables,
we had Vandervals you
can also put on
the same plot on
the ideal gas.
And from this, you'll see,
again, so very, um,
low densities out here,
very low pressures.
Everything aligns, okay?
So that's all valid.
But who cares?
I mean, like, who cares?
Like, that's not where a
lot of the action
happens, right?
A lot of the action
happens over when
you get here.
And at this point,
you see a strong
divergence of
the ideal gas equation
from the other
two cases, okay?
Great. What I want to
wrap up with here and
let's see if I have,
you know, the amount
of time for it.
Otherwise, I can
continue next week
is this business
into these constants so
these specific
heats, right?
So in that problem
we did before,
right, we took
basically a container.
We defined a mass.
We transferred
some heat into it,
and we wanted to know what
was the change
in temperature.
We knew the change
in temperature,
and we wanted to know
how much heat
that we put in.
We did a conservation
of energy.
We said the
change in energy
of this control volume is
equal to how much enters
minus how much is out.
These are little E, so
this is like per mass.
Um Right,
this system is kept at
constant volume, right?
So the change in
the energy of
the system is nothing
but the change in,
um, uh, the
internal energy.
The E and then the E
out of this are only
going to be heat
transfer processes.
And so what you're
going to end up
with is that
that heat in is this
constant times dt.
And we'll call
this a CV, right?
So it's constant volume,
we'll say C,
little V times dt,
and then that's going
to be equal to d,
um, to little D,
you know, little U.
And then, by definition,
so the definition then of
the specific heat at
constant volume, right,
is the partial
derivative of
the internal energy
of your control,
you know, of the
system with respect
to temperature for
constant volume.
We're going to
use this like
a ton, like a ton, okay?
So like this,
Oh, it doesn't.
We're going to use
it a lot, okay,
especially with
the engines
and and fun
stuff like that.
So this is kind
of like let's
call it factual, okay?
Factual, right? And we
do the same heat
addition process,
but not constant volume,
we have constant pressure.
You expect there,
there's going
to be not just
the warming,
but potentially
work, right?
I have a P Delta
V. So what
you're going to
expect is that
that value should
be higher, right?
Because when I
transfer some heat in,
I'm going to do
some work at
the same time that
I'm heating, right?
Um, We'll get into,
like, what this term
means as a little H,
but essentially
its definition
is the partial
derivative of enthalpy,
essentially kind
of energy with
respect to temperature
for constant pressure,
and we're also
going to use that
one a ton, okay?
Their units are
energy per mass per
keelvin or energy energy
per mass per degree.
So it could be degree
Kelvin degrees Celsius.
It doesn't
matter. A lot of
times, actually,
all the times,
it's going to be
a Delta T. We're
always going to be working
with differences
in temperature.
So it can be differences
in temperature,
Kelvin temperatures
and temperature,
Celsius, as long as you're
consistent, you're
good, okay?
But again, it's like heat.
Because I put heat in, I
expect the temperature
change, right?
And the constant
in front of it is
the specific heat, okay?
And so, coming back
to Jules experiment,
right, he was
basically very,
you know, very
concerned with
how this thing here.
So basically calculating,
especially CV here.
So if I kept things at
constant volume and
I made changes,
you know, will I actually
measure a change in
temperature, okay?
And it turns out,
I'm going to
foreshadow. We'll
get into it.
But for an ideal
gas, um, You know,
this internal
energy, you know,
is only dependent upon
temperature there,
right?
So when you get to the CV,
it only depends on that.
It doesn't depend on
temperature or it depend
on pressure or
volume, okay?
With 4 seconds ago,
I'm going to
close it there.
If you have questions
I'm up here.
Otherwise, I got
to run downstairs.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.