Nine. Okay. Lecture nine.
All right. So today
we're going to talk
about gas power cycles.
There's an
important moment
in this class where like
rubber road.
You know, here.
Okay. So after today,
you're going to be
able to evaluate
the performance of
a gas power cycle,
describe or develop
some simplifying
assumption
that's going to
make life easier,
and we'll solve a
problem based on
the auto cycle.
And if we have time,
we'll also go through
the diesel cycle, okay?
Okay, so power cycles.
Classify in two ways.
The first is what's
called a gas cycle.
Through the whole cycle,
the fluid is a gas,
a vapor cycle, um,
is a process where the
working fluid is a vapor,
but it also
condenses, okay?
So it is not a gas the
whole time, right?
There's a liquid.
The most famous one
of this, right?
So we have auto,
which is this diesel,
and for the aero people
in the room, Brayton.
Brayton is a very
important one there.
On this vapor cycle,
the most important
one is Rankin, okay?
This is how we
make most of
our energy
globally, is that.
Okay. If we focus just on
the gas power
cycle examples,
we have cycles that
run on closed systems,
and we have cycles that
run on control
volumes, all right?
So closed system means
piston cylinders.
So all those piston
examples that
I did for you,
it wasn't just for your
health, all right?
This is for, you know,
these applications
and done.
And the auto cycle
and the diesel cycle
run on piston
cylinder devices,
which we can do energy
analysis on from
the closed system.
So that's Chapter
four material.
For a for things like
the Brayton cycle,
which is a steady
flow device, right,
that consists
of compressors,
heat exchangers,
and the turbine.
There we do control
volume analysis,
all right?
And we will apply for
the closed system,
right, the different
analyses of
the different
states of this.
And for this
one, we'll do it
for the different
components, all right?
But again, those
fundamentals
we did for, you know,
Module one are not
going to be applied
into the Module
two here, okay?
So, what is the
auto cycle?
The auto cycle is
an idealized cycle for
how internal combustion
engines operate,
specifically ones that
are running gasoline,
right?
So gasoline
engines, they run
on what's called
the auto cycle.
Um, There's four there's
four steps in the process.
The first is that
you take, right,
your air and your fuel and
you compress this, okay?
Right? So you have this
compression process.
Then you ignite it,
and gasoline burns
very quickly, okay?
So this ignition
process happens so
fast that we consider
that as an isochoric step,
all right? Very fast.
Um, you have an expansion,
right, that happens
after that.
And then you have
exhaust and then intake,
and you start
again, right?
So this is the reality.
So the reality is
that Professor Suzi,
you told me that's
a closed system.
It looks an awful lot
like things are
coming in and out.
Yes. If we want
to analyze this
and idealize it and
make it more
straightforward to do,
what we can do is
we can say that
this compression process
is isotropic, okay?
The heat conditionion,
instead of dealing with
combustion and
saying, Okay,
that's a
complicated species
and enthalpy
of combustion,
that's going to be like,
you know, Module three.
We'll get to
enthalpy combustion.
For now, We'll
say that most
of what's in there is
actually nitrogen.
Nitrogen doesn't react.
Not very much anyways.
And so this fluid
is mostly air.
Thermodynamically,
it's air, okay?
And so we can
approximate the
combustion process
by a heat addition
heat addition, okay?
Then isotropic expansion,
and then isochoric
heat removal,
okay? So again,
the same thing.
We say, right, this is
mostly nitrogen,
not reactive.
This is pretty much
then air, and most
of the air is
nitrogen anyways.
And so this intake
stroke then and the
refreshing and getting
us back to the start,
we'll idealize them as
a cue out, all right?
This is what the
reality would look
like on a PV diagram.
And then this is
what the idealized
one is there, okay?
There's two other
terms that are here.
So it's well,
let me just describe it
and then I'll
give it a name.
What's important in
something like this,
a device like this is
that boundary work you're
going to do, all right?
That PDV, all right?
So the case when you
have the maximum volume,
that's called bottom
dead center, okay?
This is when this thing
is most expanded.
And then when it's
most compressed,
that's TDC top dead
center, all right?
Does that really matter?
I don't know, but
it's terminology.
So if you're, you know,
like cars, then that's
what that means.
But there is a
meaning in thermal
because then, essentially,
by knowing those
two, you know,
volumes there,
right, you can say
something about the work.
There's a final term
that's not listed here,
which is that if I have
that maximum volume,
which happens at the
bottom dead center
and the minimum volume,
which happens at the
top dead center,
the W net that happens out
of this device right,
is equal to the difference
in those volumes times
some mean effective
pressure MEP, okay?
Again, this is
informational.
You can read the
book, but that's
the meaning that's
the meaning of that.
All right. Cool. So again,
if we come back to
analyzing the ideal cycle.
So each of those
processes, again,
just restating it
now showing it
here is a TS diagram.
This process one to two is
an isotropic compression,
two to three constant
volume heat addition,
three to four
isentropic expansion,
and four to one constant
volume isochoric heat
heat rejection, right?
So what does it mean
then if I have isotropic
compression and
isotropic expansion,
what can you say
about that process?
Presley. It's reversible
and what else?
Is. Internally reversible.
And if there's
no change in
entropy, what else is
not happening, okay?
A. Adiabatic Adiabatic and
reversible is what we're
talking about here, right?
For the auto. For
the auto cycle.
Okay, so let's
get into it.
I'm going to derive. So in
this example, I'll
take you through.
I find in this case,
to do the math,
pairing the math and
the derivation of
the thermal
efficiency is done
best when I actually
solve a problem
here, all right?
So in this case,
what you're given is
an ideal a cycle that
has a compression
ratio of seven.
So this compression
ratio, what is that?
The compression
ratio is the ratio
of the volume
at state one,
okay, divided by the
volume at state two.
So the state
before I compress,
All right, and the
state after I compress.
So the state before it
compresses at state one,
so you have volume one.
And when you compress,
you go to the volume two.
And so R is then
the ratio of
those two things.
It's going to be
greater than one,
right, because
you're compressing.
So in our case,
this is equal
to seven. All right.
At the beginning of the
compression process,
we have this, right?
We're letting in, you
know, pretty much air
at state one, from
atmospheric conditions.
So we have P one,
which is equal to
90 kpa and T one,
27 degrees Celsius.
And so what it means,
if this is a
pure substance,
right,
you'll have complete
information, right?
If you decide to
go that route.
We're also given what the
volume is at state one,
and we're told that
that's 0.004 meter cubes.
So four liters,
right? All right.
The T max. So
additional information
that we're given.
This is state one.
The T max that we're given
is that we have one,
one, two, seven
degrees C, do.
Yeah. And what
we're told to do
is to assume a
number of things.
But constant CP and
CV is one of them.
And so we want
to determine.
So we're going to
determine Q
out is the first thing.
W net out,
the thermal efficiency of
this engine and the mean
effective pressure.
All right. So we
can begin with Yeah.
Calling that
from step one,
we're going to compress.
This is basically
from state
one to state two.
We're going to do a
compression process here.
That's good. For this,
we have isotropic.
If we assume that
this is an ideal
if we assume that
this is an ideal gas,
what we can rely on is
basically our
TDS relations
that we have here.
If I say that I have
dS is equal to CV,
dt divided by T plus
specific gas constant,
um, dv divided
by V, right?
And I say it's isomropic?
This is going
to be to zero.
And so what we'll have
is a negative CV,
dt divided by T
is equal to R,
dv by V. We
can put this to the
other side, okay?
Negative, um, a
negative there.
All right? We
can integrate.
If we treat this
as a constant,
right, we can pull that
out of the integral.
And so what you'll
have here is then
a natural log of T two
divided by T one is equal
to the negative R CV,
natural log of V
two divided by a
little V two divided
by little V one there.
This is a natural log.
I can put this up
to the exponent.
I have a natural log
of little V two divided by
little V one to
the power of
negative R divided by CV.
If I take the exponential
of both sides.
What I can have is then T
two divided by T one,
is equal to little
V two divided by
little V one to the
negative R by CV.
What can we
recall? How can I
relate R to CPs and CVs?
You can remember that R is
equal to Cp minus CV.
You can also remember
that Kappa is
equal to Cp divided by CV.
And so if you put
that in there,
what you can say is that T
two is equal to T
one, all right?
We can get rid
of the negative,
so we can flip that and
write V one by V two.
Cp minus CV over
CV is nothing
but kappa minus or
let me think about
this for a second.
So it will be cp minus CV,
so that'd be Kappa
minus one there.
All right. Does
this look familiar?
We related properties,
when we treated
ideal gas, our
TDS relations.
We took our TDS relations.
We wanted to know
how we went from
one state to
another one, okay?
And a nice way
to do that is
we treat it as an
isotropic process.
So we set that ds to zero.
And with that,
we're able to
relate things like
temperature changes
to pressure changes or
to volume changes.
That's why we
did this, okay?
Because now you can say,
I know my initial
temperature.
I know the ratio,
my volume, okay,
that's there.
So this what did I say?
I said R is equal to what?
V one divided by V two,
This is a closed system,
no mass in or out.
So it's fair for me
to write or this
is within my rights
to write N, right?
Little V one, N,
little V two.
There's no mass in or out.
And so that R
is little V one
divided by little
V two, right?
So this is T one times
R to the kappa minus one.
So by knowing this
compression ratio,
by knowing the
adiabatic index
and my initial
temperature in Kelvin,
I can determine
my temperature
at state two, all right?
Good. All right.
Whew. All right.
Cool. So we've done,
you know, and so for
this, I don't have to
do I'm not doing
an energy analysis
here, right?
I'm going with, you know,
assuming this is
ideal gas and
treating it as isotropic.
Let's go now to
two to three.
So states, two.
All right, let's
see. It was
compressed like
this. So I'm here.
This is two to
three is isochoric,
and I'm putting some Q in.
I'm putting Q
in, all right?
For this, I need to do
an energy analysis,
all right?
I'll draw my control
volume here. Okay.
And I'm going to
write my first law.
So my first law applied
to a closed system
is Delta E is
equal to what?
E in minus E out.
Now it's time for our
second assumption.
I'm going to say
that inside of that,
what assumption am
I going to make
about the energy
the change
in the energy that
control volume?
What are ways that
it can store energy?
Internal and what else?
Name. Say it again.
Okay. And your
answer volume.
There is no volume, right?
It's the isochork process.
Energy. That's it, right?
So what you have
here is Delta U plus
Delta K plus Delta P
is equal to the ways
that I can transfer in.
What are ways that I can
transfer energy into
this control volume for a
closed system for 400?
He didn't work, right?
So I have W plus Q in
minus W plus Q out, right?
It's an isochrk process.
What do we think happens
to the work terms?
Adios. All right.
So we don't have
work done here.
This is a heat
transfer in process.
I don't have any I don't
have any heat out.
I'm going to write down
on my sheet of
paper that I am
neglecting changes
in kinetic and
potential energy.
And so the change in
the internal
energy here is
equal to Q in, okay?
Good. Now, we assume
this is an ideal
gas, all right?
How do I relate changes in
internal energy to
temperature for
an ideal gas?
Right? MCV Delta T, okay?
I'm going to
assume I assume
constant specific
heats, too.
Over these
temperature changes,
I'm not going to have
a huge variation.
And we'll check
ourselves on that.
At the end of this,
I'll show you
the error associated
with treating this
as a constant
instead of getting
exact property values of
internal energy
because you
could also do that, right?
You could go in
and say, Well,
I'm going to do this.
I'll know the mass.
I'll look up my internal
energy at state two,
and I'll look
up my specific
internal energy
at state one.
What you'll see is
at the end of this,
the error is about 5% by
assuming that this value
was taken at state one,
so basically room
temperature.
All right, so my
delta U here.
Let's be precise
with this.
So U, um, sorry,
this is U three
minus U two.
So U three minus U two is
equal to N cv T
three minus T two.
Okay, we know T two.
We just determined it
there through
that process.
T three, what do
we think T three
is based on the
problem information?
So this is right,
State three is
after combustion.
Is this going to be
hot or cold? Kai?
Is it going to be equal to
T max? That's right.
T max, all right? There's
your T max there.
And in this
case, our T max,
I wrote as 1127.
One, one, two,
seven degrees
Celsius. All right.
So with this, I know
my heat addition,
which is good, okay?
By knowing how much heat,
that I'm adding, I
am halfway to being
able to determine
my network.
Why? Because network out
is equal to net heat in.
So by determining Q
out and Q in,
you know that.
That's much more
convenient, in my opinion,
doing it this than
getting into, you know,
into the weeds with
work transfer, okay?
Okay? You could
do it. What did
we say about the work
transfer process?
It's isentropic, which
means adiabatic.
Do I have relations for
pressure and volume
to do a PDV?
You do, okay? You have
an adiabatic expansion.
Now it's coming back.
This is useful,
all right? Good.
All right, so we're
good with this one.
So we know the T three.
What I would like
to do now I've
run out of space.
What can I kill?
I'll kill this. Okay.
Let's I'll keep
that there.
I'll move to the
middle board.
I'll block that out.
Let's go to the
middle board.
Can erase this?
Okay. All right.
And now we're
going 3-4, right?
Three to four, and
it's expansion.
So I start off
here at this.
Actually, I kind of
drew it upside
down, right?
So this is top
dead center.
Yeah. Okay.
Anyways, it's going
to move out here and
expand like that,
all right? Okay.
And remember, in
this process,
this is an adiabatic
and reversible process.
So what you can hazard
a guess is that
we'll end up
using our TDS relations
again, right?
So ds is CV,
dt divided by T plus R,
dv by V there.
This is gone, right,
because it's isentropic.
And so here,
we'll have CV,
dt divided by T is equal
to the negative of
R dv divided by
V. All right,
I can move this to
the other side,
CV I can integrate.
I can treat these as
like a constant
there, right?
And so what we'll
have here is
the natural log of T
four divided by T
three is equal to
negative R by CV,
natural log of V four,
little V four divided by
little V three, right?
The same drill. We can
make this an
exponent, right?
So I can write
negative R by CV here.
Move that up, takes
the exponential
of both sides.
All right.
And we have that. Now,
we have to remember.
So here at state four,
state three from state
two to state three
was isochoric.
So V two is equal
to V three, okay?
And V four to
V one is isochoric
heat removal.
And what that means
is that it's going
to be equal to V one.
And so what we
can do is we can
write swap this out,
and we can say
that it's V one
divided by V two,
And we can remember
then our definitions
for this.
This is going to
be in the end,
we have a negative
sign here.
So basically, I'll
leave it like this,
negative R by CV,
and then we'll clean
that up in a second.
The negative sign,
we can flip this.
So if I do the
negative sign,
that's V two
divided by V one,
R by CV, and this R
by CV is R is Cp minus CV.
So this will be V two by V
one to the Kappa
minus one.
All right. We'd prefer if
this was then put into
the compression ratio.
So remember, state two
is more compressed
than state one.
And so what this will
look like it will be one
over R to the Kappa
minus one will be T four
divided by T three,
which essentially
just means that T
four is equal to T three
to the one over R,
which is the
compression ratio,
Kappa minus one, right?
So now I've got,
State one was given.
State two I got
from TDS relations.
Temperature at state three
was given as the
maximum temperature.
And now assuming
isotropic expansion
and using TDS relations,
I now have T four.
And the final one
that I want to do is
this isochoric
heat removal.
So for that,
I'll move back
to the left hand side.
Okay. And now we're
going four to one.
Four to one, and this
is the expanded state.
So this is the
expanded state,
and now I have Q out,
and my control
volume looks
like this. All right.
So again,
first law applied
to a closed system.
The change in
the energy of
the control volume in
here is equal to
the energy that enters
minus what leaves.
The change in energy
of the control volume can
be changes in
internal energy,
kinetic or potential.
We neglect changes in
kinetic and
potential energy.
This is an
isochoric process,
so we don't have
work transfer.
It's a cooling process,
so I don't have Q in,
but I do have Q.
Q out. All right.
So Delta U is equal
to Q Cue out.
Cue out here. All right.
This is going to
be from state
four to state one.
All right. All right.
And then what I'm
going to have here
is that the change
in the internal
energy from
state four to state one is
equal to the mass inside
the piston
cylinder times the
CV times T four
minus T one,
where T four is warmer
than T one, right?
It's a cooling process.
And then we can
do it that way.
And this is, if we were
treating this as an
ideal gas assumption.
If you don't want to make
the ideal gas assumption,
knock your socks off,
then you got to determine
the internal energy
at state four and
at state one.
Okay? So now with
this, right, I know,
I have formulas for
my Q in and my Q out.
So Qn, Q in was
equal to M, CV,
T three minus T two,
my Q out was equal
to the mass,
CV, T four minus
T one, okay?
Let Center here.
Okay. So W net
is equal to Q
in minus Q out.
Remember this for a
cycle is a cycle here.
For a cycle, the
net work out.
Net work out is equal
to the net heat in.
So the Q minus the Q out.
And so we can
write CV The N
is three minus T two,
and the out is
four minus T one.
All right. Our efficiency,
so the efficiency then of
the cycle of any
thermal engine
is the W net
divided by Qn.
And so my W net
then is Cv times T
three minus two minus
T four minus T one,
and my Qn is Cv times
T three minus T two.
All right. Ms are
gone. This is gone.
And so what you
can do is you can
rewrite this as one
minus T four minus T one,
T three minus T two,
and then you can be a
little bit fancy
with this.
So right now, it's in
temperatures,
which is fine,
but we'd prefer to have
this as a function of R,
the compression ratio
and the adiabatic index,
which we are allowed
to do because
we're treating this
as an ideal gas,
and we use the
TDS relations,
where we can relay
basically ratios
of temperatures
to each other.
So for this, you
can do one minus
T one times T four by T
one minus one divided by T
two times T three
by T two minus one.
Okay. Let's think for
a second. Think
for a second.
So if we recall
the TDS relations
that we had here.
So we said that can
this be seen here.
Let me blow it up Foam
I have one TDS relation.
So here I have T four by T
three is equal to one
by R to the
Kappa minus one.
All right. I had
the other one,
which was then what
T two is equal to T
one times R to the
kappa minus one.
So if I rewrote this,
I could put it
as T one by T
two is equal to one
over R Kappa minus one.
This is one formula,
this is another.
Means they're equal.
The ratio then
of T four by T
three is equal to
T one by T two,
T one, what's wrong?
Is there a question? Okay.
Yeah,
so these things are
related to each other.
And so what you
can have in
the end is if
you put through
the whole derivation
on the substitution,
what you'll end up
with is the following.
So you can, as
usual, follow it all
the way to the end.
But if you put through
that substitution,
what you'll end up
with then is an Ea,
which is equal to one
minus one over R,
the compression ratio to
the Kappa minus one, okay?
And that's
interesting because
all I need to know
for this problem to
say what the
thermal efficiency
is of this auto cycle
is how much do
I squeeze it?
How much do I compress it?
And what is the adiabatic
index of my substance,
right, which in this
case is air, all right?
Cool. All right.
So if you go through
and you substitute
any substitute
values for this,
I'll spare you
the details.
But he rejected here for
this case is then
one kilojoule,
that's your network.
That's the efficiency.
And for the mean
effective pressure,
all you do is you take
this network and you
make it equal to the MEP,
you make it equal
to the network
out that I had there.
So your network out.
Is equal to the
max volume,
which is at state one
minus the mint volume,
which is at
state two times
the mean effective
pressure.
So you divide that
out and you'll end
up with the value, okay?
You can compare this with
the property
tables, right?
So I mentioned
here for Right,
the heat additions and
the heat removals,
you can work with, right,
the specific
internal energies.
How do you get to
the specific internal
energies there?
1-2. It's isotropic.
So I know my initial
state, okay?
I know how much
I'm compressing
it so I know my
specific volume,
and I know that the
entropy at state
two is equal to the
entropy at state one.
I've got two, okay?
2-3 now that I know two,
again, two to three is
an isochoric process.
So specific volume
at state three
is equal to the specific
volume at state two.
Good. So I know
the specific volume
is state three,
and another temperature
at state three,
because it was the
maximum temperature.
Good. Now, when
I go through
the expansion process
that's isentropic,
S four is equal to S one.
So that's good.
And the specific volume
at state four is equal to
the specific volume
at state one
because it's isochoric.
So you can round the
loop going that way.
That's also perfectly
acceptable.
And if you do
this alternative
solution, compute
the properties,
you know, call in the
internal energies
from Pi killer that way.
Um, what you'll get is
an efficiency that's
50.57 versus 54.
So if you want to
put that into, like,
error, the error
is about 7%.
The take home message too
long didn't read is
that you can write
this and have
an error that's
less than 10% based on
two things. Pretty
convenient.
Alright? Um, yeah.
And this is then how it
looks like in the diagram.
Just to remind
you all now,
this is getting
very important.
So in PICOor until now,
we've worked with
states, right?
So we've used
the state class.
From here on out, process
is going to be
important, right?
States, I expect.
You should be
able to do that
stuff in your sleep.
Yeah, in this notebook,
you can pull, right?
This is on the slides.
But to do that,
what you'll
do is you'll
define your state,
state one, state
two, all right?
That's one part
of a process,
two to three, three
to four, four to one.
There's your process,
and then you can
make plots. You p dot.
PR, let's say, is
then the object
I've defined.
If I go dot plot PV,
I get a PV diagram, Ts,
I get a TS diagram,
and that's what
that looks like.
If states are very
close together,
then obviously
they overlap,
just like being in a
crowded restaurant,
you'll be on
top of someone.
It can happen here.
Sometimes you'll
know differences.
The book is a
little bit, um,
uh, like dolly in
the sense that it
doesn't give it
to you exactly.
It gives you, what,
you know, the
meaning of it.
All right? Now, what I
mean to say is that,
like, this is exact.
So sometimes
you'll end up with
states that you really
can't see the difference.
If I take an
incompressible substance
and I apply a
Delta P to that,
there's not going to
be much change, right?
Those things are
going to overlap.
You'll see that
when we get
into the vapor cycle.
The book, on
the other hand,
exaggerates, right?
Big differences
between those points
because they want to drive
home the message of,
you know,
that something's
happening there, right?
But do this. Get
comfortable with this.
A very important part
of this class when you
leave is that you
can graph like that.
Thermo is
drawing boundaries
and graphing, right?
And if you can
represent these things
graphically, you really
know your stuff.
And this part of it
makes it I can't tell
you how much like,
how many lines of code, I
used to have to
write to do that.
Like, the fact that
you can do this,
you know, thank you,
Prossor Frank Locke
for doing this for us,
that you can do this in
such a
straightforward way.
It is also not trivial.
It is like graph theory.
So, you might
look at a plot
and say, I could be
a little bit better.
My response to you
is, then tell me how.
I will welcome that, okay?
But it is not trivial
to do that there, alright?
I don't know why you
chose the colors either,
which was like cowbo and
gold, but, you know,
maybe gold doesn't render
very well on that.
Okay. Are there
questions about this?
So again, with
anything like this,
when we deal with the
ideal gas, right,
there's two paths you
can always take
to analyzing it.
One which is determining
properties directly.
Great. And the other
one is ideal gas there.
The point on the
ideal gas is we
can use TDS relations to
deal with these
expansion and
compression processes.
Good.
And for heat additions
and removals,
if it's an
isochoric process,
we model those as CVDTs.
If you use Pi Kilo,
you wouldn't
have to do that.
You would just go and
do either the difference
in the internal
energy for those,
all right. Any questions?
Are you ready for diesel?
So diesel was a
rational engine, okay?
Professor, I think it
is it Munich
to you Munich?
I think he was in Munich.
But his goal out of
that was basically to
develop a rational design
for an engine, right?
So let's go through it.
All right. And
they're basically
the same thing except
for one difference,
except for one difference.
Okay, well, hold on.
Let's say one thing
before I dive into that.
Okay. So here what
I'm showing you.
So from the formula
that I mentioned,
so this efficiency, if I
want to make it very
large, what should I do?
Squeeze the hell
out of it, right?
Basically, get the maximum
compression that
I can there,
and you'll get to
a very high
efficiency, right?
There's limits
to it, right?
You're never going
to be Carne.
But if you stay
within what you
have, you can get some
pretty good ones.
So what you should do,
then, as an engineer,
let's say you live
outside Detroit,
you know, there,
you're working
for Ford. Good job.
Go in and say, Hey,
I want to have a
very, you know,
large compression ratio.
What's going to happen to
a gasoline engine if
you start to make
this very large?
Does anyone know? Loud.
Here. Say it again.
And what do we call that?
Knock. Basically, it's
going to knock, you
know, not like this.
It's going to detonate
before the spark plug
triggers it. All right?
So that's what
sets the limit.
Most of them have
this kind of values.
And so if you look
at that, then
the theoretical
efficiency,
what sets you then for
the constraints we have
is somewhere in
the neighborhood
of 50% to 60%.
But boy, it would
be nice if you get
to higher
compression ratios.
And that's what diesel is.
So a diesel engine doesn't
have a spark plug.
The ignition is all about
compressing the
shit out of it,
and then that triggers
combustion, ar?
The second thing about
a diesel is that
the combustion process
is not instantaneous.
It is not instantaneous.
This happens over
an amount of time.
It means that
it's not what?
So what was the
combustion process in
the auto cycle? What
did we treat that as?
Constant volume or
constant pressure?
Constant volume,
isochoric.
If something burns longer,
what would you expect
then that
combustion process
or that process would
be isochoric or isobaric.
Isobaric, okay? So
that's the difference.
So if you look
on a PV diagram
at a diesel cycle,
right, one to two is
this compression, right?
So this isentropic
compression.
Two to three is the
heat addition here.
I But that's constant
pressure now.
It's not constant volume.
Constant volume would be
going vertical, right,
like we did before,
but two to three,
it's an isobaric,
right? That's
how we treat it.
Three to four, isotropic,
which means here,
adiabatic, right?
That's an adiabatic line,
and then four to one.
The cooling off of
it, the heat transfer
out is still iso
cork, though.
That is still considered
rapid, right?
So the only difference
between the auto and
the diesel is this
process of two to three.
Let me
All right.
So let's come
back to this.
So we can take
care of that.
We'll have this RC.
Let's stay one. We'll
have to see volume.
We'll have to see this.
We'll have to see
what we determine,
and there's no max.
Okay. Um So the one
difference is this,
the two to three, and
that's a heat addition.
As a result of
this, we have to
somehow describe that
in the problem, okay?
And the way that you
do this is you say,
not only do I have that
compression ratio,
so one to two
in compression,
but I have another
ratio of volumes,
which is the volume
after combustion
divided by the volume
before combustion.
And this is called
a cutoff ratio
cutoff ratio.
So it's RC, right?
Not a race car.
Okay, RC, right?
V three by V two.
The analysis is
the same, though.
So we treat this
as an ideal gas.
So we'll treat it as
an ideal gas there.
That's one.
Expansion and
compression processes
are still isotropic.
So all the stuff that
I did before, right?
So when I, T two
is equal to T one
times V one by
right V two to the
Kappa minus one, right?
So this is right
V one by V two,
so that should increase
if that's good.
This was R, right?
That's the definition
of R. That's fine.
From T four being
to T three.
So V four is down here.
Here is V one,
also from V three, sorry,
to the the Kappa
minus one.
This is no longer.
This is basically
no longer
that same ratio
that we had before.
What's the reasoning?
So when I go from V one,
Let's say V one is equal
to V two times times
R. V three is equal
to V two times RC.
So that's the
cutoff ratio.
And so if I want to make
that substitution,
right, that's V.
If I want to make
that substitution,
this will then be T three
times V two times RC.
And for V four, V
four is still
equal to what?
If I'm returning
back, if I have
isochoric cooling,
right at the end of it,
so four to one
based on that plot,
what would you
say that V one
is relative to V four?
It's the same, okay?
So you have this.
And so what
you'll have then
here is that, okay?
And that's no
longer, right?
It's no longer
just, you know,
one over R here, right?
You have an RC with
an R that comes in.
And that's it, right?
Pretty much
everything else
is the same except
for, right, the QN.
So what is the Q in for
an ideal gas for an
isobaric process?
All right. Maybe too
fast. All right.
So if I go from,
this is two to
32 to three,
which is my heat addition.
My heat addition,
I'm going to
draw control
volume like that.
And I expand some
amount it happens,
and the pressure P two
is equal to P three.
Okay? So I have
Qn And what else do
I have happening?
What other energy
exchange am I
having for my
control volume here?
Work Out, right?
So I have W out.
So if I write
the first law,
neglecting changes in
Kineticut
potential energy,
Delta U is then equal to
Q in because
there's no Q out
minus W out
because there's
no W in Q in minus.
So it's an
isoeric process.
What is the formula
going to be for
the workout?
Right? V three
divided by V two,
can move that to the
other side, right?
So I'm going
to my Delta U,
which is U three plus p2v3
minus two plus p2v2
is equal to Qn.
What is this? Not
everyone at once here.
Enthalpy.
Enthalpy, right?
This is your H
three minus H two
is equal to Q in.
Of course, you can
write this as,
since it's a
closed system,
no energy, no
mass in or out.
Little H three
minus little H
two is equal to Q in.
You could pillow
that and get it.
Or what approximation can
I make because this
is an ideal guess?
That's it. Cp
Delta T. Cp T
three minus T two is
equal to n, okay?
So if you think about
the efficiency, then,
if we think about the
thermal efficiency
of this cycle, right?
All right. Or let's
start with W net, right?
W net is equal to
Q in minus Q out,
so W net out, right?
My Q in is CP,
T three minus T two.
My Q out is CV T four
minus T one, okay?
So the thermal efficiency
of a diesel cycle,
just like any cycle, W
net out, divided by Q.
And so what that
will look like is
CP three minus
two minus MCV,
T four minus T one,
all of that divided by
M CP three minus T two.
You could do some
simplifications,
you know, to that.
In the interest of
time, I'll spare
you for it and get
to the message.
Um But if you can do
some simplifications,
and what you'll
end up with is
a formula for
the efficiency
that looks just like auto
with a modification term.
So if the cutoff ratio
is equal to one,
you recover the auto
cycle efficiency, okay?
So if RC equals to one,
you'll end up with that.
But this can be simplified
down to that there, okay?
So if we want to compare,
then the efficiency
of an auto cycle as
a function of
compression ratio
of both cases,
remember this is auto and
the typical values
of compression.
For diesel, much
higher, right?
As a factor of two higher.
And also plotted
on here are
the different cutoff
ratios there from one,
which is auto excuse me.
Right,
which one is the auto
and on down, right?
And the take home message
is that by getting up to
these higher
compression ratios,
you're getting
efficiencies that
are then, you know,
well above, maybe 10%
above what you have.
And with that, I'm
going to close.
You should be able
to do all this here.
We got two more lectures
in the gas power cycles.
I'm very enthusiastic.
Have a good one. Let go.